{
    "questions": [
        {
            "Question": "The First World Conference on Women in __________, generated a new interest in and debate on women's issues",
            "optionA": "  Delhi ",
            "optionB": "  Hyderabad ",
            "optionC": "  Mexico ",
            "optionD": "  Copenhagen ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe First World Conference on Women, which launched the UN Decade for Women, was held in Mexico City. ",
            "keyString": "743774s5m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Narain Malhar Joshi founded",
            "optionA": "  the Social Service League in Bombay in 1911 ",
            "optionB": "  All India Trade Union Congress 1920 ",
            "optionC": "  Both A and B above ",
            "optionD": "  The Deccan Education Society 1884 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNarain Malhar Joshi founded the Social Service League in Bombay in 1911 and All India Trade Union Congress 1920. ",
            "keyString": "743808s5m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who of the following was for the first time designated as the Governor of India",
            "optionA": "  Clive ",
            "optionB": "  Comwallis ",
            "optionC": "  Warren Hastings ",
            "optionD": "  Wellesley ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first Governor-General was Warren Hastings. ",
            "keyString": "743822s5m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The English established their first factory in Bengal in 1651 at __________",
            "optionA": "  Hugli ",
            "optionB": "  Kassimbazar ",
            "optionC": "  Patna ",
            "optionD": "  Calcutta ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHooghly(Hugli) was also the first English settlement (1651) in Lower Bengal; it was abandoned in 1690 for Calcutta (now Kolkata). Chinsurah was an important 17th-century settlement of the Dutch, who built a factory (trading station) there in 1656. ",
            "keyString": "743835s5m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "'Swaathanthrya gadha' \u2013 was written by the great poet __________",
            "optionA": "  Cherusseri ",
            "optionB": "  O. N. V. Kurup ",
            "optionC": "  G. Sankara kurup ",
            "optionD": "  Kumaranaasan ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t'Swaathanthrya gadha' \u2013 was written by the great poet Kumaranaasan. ",
            "keyString": "743846s5m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The year of the foundation of the Women's Indian Association (WIA) is",
            "optionA": "  1947 ",
            "optionB": "  1937 ",
            "optionC": "  1927 ",
            "optionD": "  1917 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 8 May 1917 in Adyar, Madras, a multiethnic group of women established the Women's Indian Association (WIA). The WIA was one of the first organizations to boldly connect Indian women's social and sexual subjugation with patriarchy, poverty, and political disenfranchisement. ",
            "keyString": "822432s5m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "By the Act of 1858, India was to be governed",
            "optionA": "  By the Company ",
            "optionB": "  In the name of the Crown ",
            "optionC": "  By a Board of Directors ",
            "optionD": "  In the name of Governor-General of India ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Government of India Act 1858 was an Act of the Parliament of the United Kingdom passed on August 2, 1858. Its provisions called for the liquidation of the British East India Company (who had up to this point been ruling British India under the auspices of Parliament) and the transference of its functions to the British Crown. ",
            "keyString": "822468s5m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Ghadar Party was founded (November 1913) at San Francisco USA by",
            "optionA": "  Madam Bhikaji Cama ",
            "optionB": "  Lala Har Dayal ",
            "optionC": "  Shyamji Krishana Verma ",
            "optionD": "  Both A and B above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1913, Pacific Coast Hindustan Association was founded by Lala Hardayal with Sohan Singh Bhakna as its president, which was called Ghadar Party. The members of this party were the immigrant sikhs of US and Canada. The first issue of The Ghadar, was published from San Francisco on 1 November 1913. ",
            "keyString": "822485s5m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Poona Pact (1932) was an agreement between",
            "optionA": "  Nehru and Ambedkar ",
            "optionB": "  Gandhi and Ambedkar ",
            "optionC": "  Malaviya and Ambedkar ",
            "optionD": "  Gandhi and Nehru ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAn agreement between Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar and Mahatma Gandhi was signed 84 years ago on September 24, 1932. The agreement was signed by Pt Madan Mohan Malviya and Dr. B. R. Ambedkar and some Dalit leaders at Yerwada Central Jail in Pune, to break Mahathma Gandhi's fast unto death. ",
            "keyString": "822500s5m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following national leaders did not defended soldiers of the Indian National Army in 1945 case dealing with trial?",
            "optionA": "  Sir Tej Bahadur Sapru ",
            "optionB": "  Bhula Bhai Desai ",
            "optionC": "  ",
            "optionD": " Rajagopalachari ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNational leader Rajagopalachari did not defended soldiers of the Indian National Army in 1945 case dealing with trial. ",
            "keyString": "822516s5m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Gandhi wanted the students to spend their vacations in",
            "optionA": "  Studies ",
            "optionB": "  Social service ",
            "optionC": "  Games ",
            "optionD": "  Rebellious deeds ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGandhi advised the students to spend their vacation in social service. He wanted them to to work with dedication. He advised them to conduct schools. The students should visit harijan quarters and clean them. They should take the harijan children to recreational sights and give them the knowledge about nature. They should give the awareness of cleanliness to harijans. They should read them the stories from the holy books. ",
            "keyString": "933984s5m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Gandhi called for an all India Hartal (strike) to protest against Rowlatt Act on 6th April __________",
            "optionA": "  1918 ",
            "optionB": "  1919 ",
            "optionC": "  1926 ",
            "optionD": "  1925 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first major national campaign organized by Mahatma Gandhi was against the Rowlatt Act, which severely limited civil liberties. This movement began with an all-India hartal, observed on Sunday the 6th of April 1919. Gandhi had decided to lead the hartal in Bombay himself. ",
            "keyString": "934476s5m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following had authored the book, 'At the Feet of Mahatma Gandhi'?",
            "optionA": "  JB Kripalani ",
            "optionB": "  Rajendra Prasad ",
            "optionC": "  Jayaprakash Narayan ",
            "optionD": "  Vinoba Bhave ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRajendra Prasad had authored the book, 'At the Feet of Mahatma Gandhi'. ",
            "keyString": "934938s5m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Pitts India Act of 1784 was a/an",
            "optionA": "  White Paper ",
            "optionB": "  Regulating Act ",
            "optionC": "  Ordinance ",
            "optionD": "  Resolution ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPitts India Act of 1784 was a Regulating Act by this act dual archy has established by the formation Board of Control. ",
            "keyString": "935378s5m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which ot the following places was the Ryotwari settlement introduced by",
            "optionA": "  Uttar Pradesh and Punjab ",
            "optionB": "  North-West Provinces and Punjab ",
            "optionC": "  Madras and Bombay ",
            "optionD": "  Bengal and Bihar ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRyotwari settlement was introduced by Alexander Reed and Thomas Munro in Madras and Bombay. ",
            "keyString": "938298s5m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Maulana Abdul Kalam Azad Started an Urdu Weekly, The Al-Hilal in 1912 but on its being banned by the Government he founded Al-Balagh in",
            "optionA": "  1913 ",
            "optionB": "  1914 ",
            "optionC": "  1915 ",
            "optionD": "  1916 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1913 Maulana Abdul Kalam Azad started Al-Balagh. He was an Indian scholar and the senior Muslim leader of the Indian National Congress during Indian Independence Movement. He became the first minister of Education in the Indian Government. ",
            "keyString": "57020s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "My Experiments with Truth is the work of Mahatma Gandhi published in",
            "optionA": "  1901 ",
            "optionB": "  1902 ",
            "optionC": "  1906 ",
            "optionD": "  1946 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMy Experiments with Truth is the work of Mahatma Gandhi published in 1906. The Story of My Experiments with Truth is the autobiography of Mohandas K. Gandhi, covering his life from early childhood through to 1921. ",
            "keyString": "60207s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The battle of Balakot was in __________",
            "optionA": "  1806 ",
            "optionB": "  1821 ",
            "optionC": "  1831 ",
            "optionD": "  1896 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSikh Army tried to penetrate from the Garhi Habibullah (15 km downstream) with armies from Kashmir but were put to hold till the reinforcement arrived from Lahore via Timri near Shinkiari. On a little mound in the north of the city, by the Rou Nala, the Battle of Balakot was fought on May 6, 1831. Sikhs became victorious and all the Mujahideens including Syed Ahmad and Shah Ismail were killed. ",
            "keyString": "60835s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The immediate cause of the Battle of Plassey was",
            "optionA": "  The English attempts to strengthen their fortifications at Fort William ",
            "optionB": "  The English support and asylum to the political rivals of Nawab Siraj-ud-Daulah ",
            "optionC": "  Misuse of Dastaks (passes for free trade) by the Company and its officials ",
            "optionD": "  Siraj-ud-Daulah's attack on Fort William and capture of Calcutta (Alinagar) ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Battle of Plassey was a decisive victory of the British East India Company over the Nawab of Bengal and his French allies on 23 June 1757, under the leadership of Robert Clive. Clive defeated Siraj-ud-Daulah at Plassey in 1757 and captured Calcutta. ",
            "keyString": "61317s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1916 Mahatma Gandhi travelled to__________ to inspire the peasants to struggle against the oppressive plantation system",
            "optionA": "  Dandi ",
            "optionB": "  Sabarmati ",
            "optionC": "  Champaran ",
            "optionD": "  Chauri Chaura ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahatma Gandhi travelled to Champaran in 1916 to opposed the \"Teen Kathiya\" system related to the Indigo farmers. ",
            "keyString": "61780s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who spoke \"At the stroke of midnight, when the world sleeps, India awakes to life and freedom\"?",
            "optionA": "  Netaji Subhas Chandra Bose ",
            "optionB": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionC": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionD": "  Rajagopalachari ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThis statement used by Pt.Jawaharlal Nehru in the midnight of 14th - 15th August 1947. ",
            "keyString": "162329s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The enquiry Committee on Jallianwaia Bagh incident was headed by",
            "optionA": "  Dyer ",
            "optionB": "  Irwin ",
            "optionC": "  Hunter ",
            "optionD": "  Simon ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 14 October 1919, after orders issued by the Secretary of State for India, Edwin Montagu, the Government of India announced the formation of a committee of inquiry into the events in Punjab. Referred to as the Disorders Inquiry Committee, it was later more widely known as the Hunter Commission. ",
            "keyString": "163951s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel was equated with",
            "optionA": "  Mazzini ",
            "optionB": "  Cavour ",
            "optionC": "  Garibaldi ",
            "optionD": "  Bismarck ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBismarck was a german statesman who unified 36 states and established unified Germany. Sardar Patel also unified the 565 princely states to make India a federation by his diplomacy and political intelligency. That is why Sardar Vallabh Bhai Patel known as Bismarck of India.",
            "keyString": "169445s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Pitt's India Act brought the company in direct subordination to a body representing __________",
            "optionA": "  The Parliament of Britain ",
            "optionB": "  The English Merchants in India ",
            "optionC": "  The Indian Merchants ",
            "optionD": "  Princely States ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe East India Company Act 1784, also known as Pitt's India Act, was an Act of the Parliament of Great Britain intended to address the shortcomings of the Regulating Act of 1773 by bringing the East India Company's rule in India under the control of the British Government. ",
            "keyString": "172970s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Lord Mountbatten had held detailed discussions on the approaching partition of India with",
            "optionA": "  Mohammed Ali Jinnah ",
            "optionB": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionC": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Mountbatten held free and frank discussions with Sardar Patel, Maulana Azad, Jawaharlal Nehru, Gandhiji and other prominent leaders.",
            "keyString": "175608s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Communal Award, which was subsequently changed following Gandhi's fast unto death in a jail at Poona, had been given by",
            "optionA": "  Ramsay Mcdonald ",
            "optionB": "  Lloyd George ",
            "optionC": "  Stanley Baldwin ",
            "optionD": "  AV Alexander ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGandhi Ji subsequently embarked on his historic Poona fast in September 1932 after the \u2018Communal Award\u2019 announced by Macdonald had granted separate electorate to the Depressed Classes. ",
            "keyString": "321058s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "As per Act of 1919 the lower house of the Central Legislature was known as __________",
            "optionA": "  Legislative Council ",
            "optionB": "  Legislative Assembly ",
            "optionC": "  House of Representatives ",
            "optionD": "  House of Commons ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Central Legislative Assembly was the lower house of the Imperial Legislative Council, the legislature of British India. It was created by the Government of India Act 1919, implementing the Montagu\u2013Chelmsford Reforms. It was also sometimes called the Indian Legislative Assembly and the Imperial Legislative Assembly. ",
            "keyString": "321137s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who from the following leaders was not assassinated?",
            "optionA": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  Liaqat Ali Khan ",
            "optionC": "  Muhammad Ali Jinnah ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Louis Mountbatten ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMuhammad Ali Jinnah was the one who was not assassinated. ",
            "keyString": "321157s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Muslim League was established in December",
            "optionA": "  1906 ",
            "optionB": "  1905 ",
            "optionC": "  1925 ",
            "optionD": "  1926 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMuslim League was established in December 1906. ",
            "keyString": "321172s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Muslim League was founded in the year",
            "optionA": "  1900 ",
            "optionB": "  1905 ",
            "optionC": "  1906 ",
            "optionD": "  1902 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1906, All India Muslim League was founded by Salim-ullah-khan (Nawab of Dhaka) Jinnah, Aga Khan and others. It was proposed Sir Mian Muhammad Safi. ",
            "keyString": "321187s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following was not included in the Treaty to be negotiated as provided in the Cabinet Mission Plan?",
            "optionA": "  The Indian Union ",
            "optionB": "  Constituent Assembly ",
            "optionC": "  Indian National Congress ",
            "optionD": "  The United Kingdom ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian National Congress was not included in the Treaty to be negotiated as provided in the Cabinet Mission Plan. ",
            "keyString": "410299s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The members of the Board of Control must be paid from",
            "optionA": "  The Consolidated Fund of England ",
            "optionB": "  Indian Revenues ",
            "optionC": "  Funds Voted by Parliament ",
            "optionD": "  The revenues of Princely States ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt was provided that the payment of the members and the staff of the Board of Control should be made out of the Indian revenues. ",
            "keyString": "410338s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "On account of his differences with Mahatma Gandhi, Subhas Bose resigned the Presidentship of the Congress (April 1939) and organised a new party called",
            "optionA": "  Congress Socialist Party ",
            "optionB": "  Azad Hind Fauz ",
            "optionC": "  Congress Liberal party ",
            "optionD": "  Forward Block ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe All India Forward Bloc (AIFB) is a left-wing nationalist political party in India. It emerged as a faction within the Indian National Congress in 1939, led by Subhas Chandra Bose. ",
            "keyString": "410356s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "On which date was the announcement formally made that India and Pakistan would be made free?",
            "optionA": "  May 2, 1947 ",
            "optionB": "  June 3, 1947 ",
            "optionC": "  July 4, 1947 ",
            "optionD": "  August 5, 1957 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe actual division of British India between the two new dominions was accomplished according to what has come to be known as the \"3 June Plan\" or \"Mountbatten Plan\". It was announced at a press conference by Mountbatten on 3 June 1947 at 4 pm, when the date of independence of India - 15 August 1947 was also announced. ",
            "keyString": "410371s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Dadabhai Naroji has described his theory of 'Drain of Wealth' in the book",
            "optionA": "  Poverty and Un-British Rule in India ",
            "optionB": "  British Rule and its Consequences ",
            "optionC": "  Exploitative Nature of British Rule in India ",
            "optionD": "  Nature of British Colonial Rule ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1867, Dadabhai Naoroji put forward the 'drain of wealth' theory in which he stated that Britain was completely draining India. He mentioned this theory in his book Poverty and Un-British Rule in India. ",
            "keyString": "410386s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said \"Patriotism is religion and religion is love for India\"?",
            "optionA": "  Raj Narain Bose ",
            "optionB": "  Bankim chandra Chatterjee ",
            "optionC": "  Swami Vivekanand ",
            "optionD": "  Acharya Vinoba Bhave ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe statement was uttered by Bankim Chandra Chatterjee. He deliberately equated the patriotism and religion so as to in still the sense of nationalism among the masses. ",
            "keyString": "529705s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Land Revenue under Tipu__________",
            "optionA": "  Was mainly collected through revenue officers ",
            "optionB": "  Was mainly collected by Government officials\nappointed by Tipu ",
            "optionC": "  Was collected by interme-diaries ",
            "optionD": "  Was not allowed to go into the hands of Sultan ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe land Revenue under Tipu was like the Rotwari and collected by the government officials. ",
            "keyString": "530256s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mahatma Gandhi participated In the Second Round Table conference after",
            "optionA": "  signing the Gandhi-Irwin Pact of March 1931 ",
            "optionB": "  refusing to hold direct talks with the Muslim League ",
            "optionC": "  being permitted by the Congress ",
            "optionD": "  receiving assurance that independence was fast coming ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahatma Gandhi participated In the Second Round Table conference after signing the Gandhi-Irwin Pact of March 1931. ",
            "keyString": "530702s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Jyotirao Phule was born in Satara district of __________ in 1827",
            "optionA": "  Maharastra ",
            "optionB": "  Madras ",
            "optionC": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionD": "  Malabar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJyotirao Govindrao Phule was born in Satara district of Maharastra in 1827. His father, Govindrao was a vegetable-vendor at Poona. ",
            "keyString": "531117s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "To establish French political influence in Sothern India, Dupleix had an opportunity in the disputed succession to the thrones of",
            "optionA": "  Delhi and Awadh ",
            "optionB": "  Hyderabad and Carnatic ",
            "optionC": "  Travancore ",
            "optionD": "  Vijayanagar and Ahmednagar ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTo establish French political influence in Sothern India, Dupleix had an opportunity in the disputed succession to the thrones of Hyderabad and Carnatic. ",
            "keyString": "531540s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Of the following who transferred the capital from Murshidabad to Monghyr?",
            "optionA": "  Mir Kasim ",
            "optionB": "  Mir Jaffar ",
            "optionC": "  Siraj-ud-Daulah ",
            "optionD": "  Mir Mudan ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter the Battle of Chinsura, the British deposed Mir Jafar and placed his son in law Mir Kasim as Nawab of Bengal. Mir Kasim, soon began to show a will of his own, and to cherish dreams of independence. He eventually shifted his capital from Murshidabad to Munger in Bihar where he raised an independent army. ",
            "keyString": "590998s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the Nawab when Dalhousie annexed Awadh in 1854?",
            "optionA": "  Nasiruddin Mahmud Shah ",
            "optionB": "  Wajid Ali Shah ",
            "optionC": "  Sirajud  daulla ",
            "optionD": "  Alivardi Khan ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWajid Ali Shah (30 July 1822 \u2013 1 September 1887) was the tenth and last Nawab of Awadh, holding the position for 9 years, from 13 February 1847 to 11 February 1856. ",
            "keyString": "599257s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Maulana Abul Kalam Azad was the author of",
            "optionA": "  India Wins Freedom ",
            "optionB": "  New India ",
            "optionC": "  Gita Rahasya ",
            "optionD": "  Discovery of India ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMaulana Sayyid Abul Kalam Ghulam Muhiyuddin Ahmed bin Khairuddin Al-Hussaini Azad (11 November 1888 \u2013 22 February 1958) was an Indian scholar, activist and a senior leader of the Indian National Congress during the Indian independence movement. Maulana Abul Kalam Azad was the author of India Wins Freedom. ",
            "keyString": "599542s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "__________, second President of The Theosophical Society from 1907 to 1933, was described as a 'Diamond Soul', for she had many brilliant facets to her character",
            "optionA": "  Annie Besant ",
            "optionB": "  Krishnamohan Banerjee ",
            "optionC": "  Hari Mohan ",
            "optionD": "  Govind Chandra Sen ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnnie Besant (1847\u20131933), second President of The Theosophical Society from 1907 to 1933, was described as a \u2018Diamond Soul\u2019, for she had many brilliant facets to her character.She was an outstanding orator of her time, a champion of human freedom, educationist, philanthropist, and author with more than three hundred books and pamphlets to her credit. ",
            "keyString": "599588s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Aruvipuram installation was done by __________",
            "optionA": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  Narayana Guru ",
            "optionC": "  Chattambi Swamikal ",
            "optionD": "  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAruvippuram is a village in the southern district of Thiruvananthapuram in Kerala, India. It is famous for the Siva temple established by Sri Narayana Guru. ",
            "keyString": "599630s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which nationalist had stoutly preached \"Be proud that you are an Indian, proudly claim I am an Indian\"?",
            "optionA": "  MK Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  Lala Lajpat Rai ",
            "optionC": "  Swami Vivekanand ",
            "optionD": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSwami Vivekanand had stoutly preached \"Be proud that you are an Indian, proudly claim I am an Indian\". ",
            "keyString": "681295s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following was a leader of the Hindustan Socialist Republican Army founded in 1928?",
            "optionA": "  Khudiram Bose ",
            "optionB": "  Bhagat Singh ",
            "optionC": "  Chandra Shekhar Azad ",
            "optionD": "  Subhash Chandra Bose ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHSRA (Hindustan Socialist Republican Association) was formed in Delhi at Firoj Shah Kotla under the leadership of Chandra Shekhar Azad.",
            "keyString": "682096s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first vernacular paper, Samachar Darpan, was published during the tenure of",
            "optionA": "  Lord Hastings ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Minto ",
            "optionC": "  Lord metcalfe ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Macaulay ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first vernacular paper, Samachar Darpan, was published during the tenure of Lord Hastings. ",
            "keyString": "682500s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Madame HP Blavatsky had laid the foundation of the Theosophical Society in the year",
            "optionA": "  1853 ",
            "optionB": "  1864 ",
            "optionC": "  1875 ",
            "optionD": "  1886 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt was in the United States of America in 1875 that Madame H. P. Blavatsky, a Russian lady, and a Colonel H. S. Olcott, a former army officer of England laid the foundation of the modern Theosophical Society. ",
            "keyString": "763246s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The second session of the congress met in Calcutta on December 1886, under the president ship of __________",
            "optionA": "  Dadabhai Naoroji ",
            "optionB": "  Kadambini Ganguli ",
            "optionC": "  Pherozeshah Mehta ",
            "optionD": "  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe second session of the congress met in Calcutta on December 1886, under the president ship of Dadabhai Naoroji. ",
            "keyString": "763296s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Interim Government which took office on September 2, 1946 was headed by",
            "optionA": "  Rajendra Prasad ",
            "optionB": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionC": "  Vallabhbhai Patel ",
            "optionD": "  C Rajagopalachari ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Viceroy's Executive Council became the executive branch of the interim government. Originally headed by the Viceroy of India, it was transformed into a council of ministers, with the powers of a prime minister bestowed on the vice-president of the Council, a position held by the Congress leader Jawaharlal Nehru. ",
            "keyString": "763400s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The National Liberal Federation was founded by",
            "optionA": "  S. N. Bannerjee ",
            "optionB": "  Motilal Nehru ",
            "optionC": "  Abul Kalam Azad ",
            "optionD": "  Mrs. Annie Besant ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBanerjee later became a senior leader of the Indian National Congress. Surendranath welcomed Montagu\u2013Chelmsford Reforms, unlike congress, and with many liberal leaders he left congress and founded a new organisation named Indian National Liberation Federation in 1919. ",
            "keyString": "763494s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Pitt's India Act empowered the Governor-General with",
            "optionA": "  Power of vote ",
            "optionB": "  A casting vote ",
            "optionC": "  The power to dismiss the council ",
            "optionD": "  The power to add more members to the council ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Pitt's India Act empowered the Governor-General with a casting vote. ",
            "keyString": "763585s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Provision was made in the Act of 1773, for the office of a Governor-General of",
            "optionA": "  India ",
            "optionB": "  Fort William ",
            "optionC": "  Madras ",
            "optionD": "  Bombay ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per the act, Office of the Governor-General of the Presidency of Fort William was created in 1773, and on 20 October 1773, Warren Hastings became the first Governor General of India. The members of the council were Lt. General John Clavering, George Monson, Richard Barwell and Philip Francis. ",
            "keyString": "873608s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What benefits did the Poona Pact offer to the depressed classes?",
            "optionA": "  44 seats in the central legislature ",
            "optionB": "  20% reservation in the provincial legislature ",
            "optionC": "  18% seats in the central legislature and 148 seats in the provincial legislature ",
            "optionD": "  50% reservation in the ICS ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Poona Pact offer 18% seats in the central legislature and 148 seats in the provincial legislature to the depressed classes. ",
            "keyString": "873804s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "'August Offer' was issued by __________",
            "optionA": "  Crown ",
            "optionB": "  Parliament ",
            "optionC": "  Viceroy ",
            "optionD": "  Secretary of State ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 8 August 1940, early in the Battle of Britain, the Viceroy of India, Lord Linlithgow, made the so-called \"August Offer\". ",
            "keyString": "873909s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Government of India, 1919 is also known as",
            "optionA": "  Morley  - Minto Reforms ",
            "optionB": "  Montague  - Chelmsford Reforms ",
            "optionC": "  Regulating Act ",
            "optionD": "  Pitts India Act ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Montague - Chelmsford reform is known as government of India act, 1919 the main feature of this reform was provincial Government i.e introduction of Dyarchy. ",
            "keyString": "874005s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The founder-president of Indian Independence League was",
            "optionA": "  Rash Behari Bose ",
            "optionB": "  Subhas Chandra Bose ",
            "optionC": "  MK Gandhi ",
            "optionD": "  Motilal Nehru ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEstablished primarily to foster Indian Nationalism and to obtain Japanese support for the Indian Independence Movement, the League came to interact and command the first Indian National Army under Mohan Singh before it was dissolved. Rash Behari Bose handed over the INA to Subhas Chandra Bose. ",
            "keyString": "874096s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Whom had Gandhi named as Mira Behn?",
            "optionA": "  Annie Besant ",
            "optionB": "  Kamla Devi ",
            "optionC": "  Indira Gandhi ",
            "optionD": "  Madeline Slade ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMadeleine Slade, also known as Mirabehn or Meera Behn, was a British woman who left her home in Britain to live and work with Mohandas Gandhi, the leader of the Indian Independence Movement. She devoted her life to human development and the advancement of Gandhi's principles. ",
            "keyString": "929476s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who attended the Congress of Oppressed Nationalities at Brussels in 1927, on behalf of the National Congress?",
            "optionA": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionB": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionC": "  Dr. Ansari ",
            "optionD": "  Motilal Nehru ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJawaharlal Nehru attended the Congress of oppressed nationalist at Brusels in 1927 on behalf of the National Congress. ",
            "keyString": "929707s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Chanakya was known as__________",
            "optionA": "  Sumit Sarkar ",
            "optionB": "  R.",
            "optionC": "Majumdar ",
            "optionD": "  Panikkar K.N ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tNo explanation is given for this questionLet's Discuss on Board ",
            "keyString": "930201s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "This social reformer most ardently worked for the removal of untouchability and uplift the depressed classes before Mahatma Gandhi came on the scene",
            "optionA": "  M. G. Ranade ",
            "optionB": "  Jyotiba Phule ",
            "optionC": "  Dayanand Saraswati ",
            "optionD": "  Atmaram Panduranga ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJyotirao Govindrao Phule (11 April 1827 \u2013 28 November 1890), also known as Jotiba Phule was an Indian social activist, a thinker, anti-caste social reformer and a writer from Maharashtra. ",
            "keyString": "930641s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the single most significant contribution of Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel to Indian History?",
            "optionA": "  He was responsible for the acceptance of the Mountbatten Plan by the Congress ",
            "optionB": "  As the Home Minister of free India he brought about the integration of 600-odd Indian States with the Indian Republic ",
            "optionC": "  He was the leading light of Mahatma Gandhi's NonCooperation and Civil Disobedience Movements ",
            "optionD": "  As President of the Indian National Congress he engineered the passing of the Quit India Resolution ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVallabhbhai Patel (31 October 1875 \u2013 15 December 1950), popularly known as Sardar Patel, was an Indian politician. He served as the first Deputy Prime Minister of India. ",
            "keyString": "931039s6m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1907, after the passing of Col. H. S. Olcott, __________ became the second International President of the Theosophical Society",
            "optionA": "  Annie Besant ",
            "optionB": "  Sarojini Naidu ",
            "optionC": "  Ahalya Rangnekar ",
            "optionD": "  Bhabani Charan Mitra ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1907, after the passing of Col. H. S. Olcott, Annie Besant became the second International President of the Theosophical Society, an office which she held until her death in 1933. ",
            "keyString": "26047s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "To campaign for Home Rule, Mrs Annie Besant published the newspaper (s)",
            "optionA": "  New India and Commonweal ",
            "optionB": "  Young India and Home Rule News ",
            "optionC": "  Mahratta and Kesari ",
            "optionD": "  Home Rule Courier ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1913, Besant joined the Indian National Congress and the next year she started two publications: the journal Commonweal and the daily New India, both of which became influential mouthpieces for her political ideas. ",
            "keyString": "26090s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following libraries has the largest collection of manuscripts of historical value?",
            "optionA": "  Khuda Baksh Oriental Public Library ",
            "optionB": "  Tanjavur Maharaja Serfoji Saraswati Mahal Library ",
            "optionC": "  Asiatic Society Library ",
            "optionD": "  Rampur Raza Library ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKhuda Baksh Oriental Library is an autonomous organization under Ministry of culture, Govrnment of India. Governor of Bihar is its ex-officio Chairman. It houses the rare collection of around 4000 Persian and Arabic manuscripts. ",
            "keyString": "26111s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Through which Educational Report Calcutta University came into existence?",
            "optionA": "  Macaulay's Minute ",
            "optionB": "  Hunter Commission ",
            "optionC": "  Charter Act ",
            "optionD": "  Wood's Despatch ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder the Wood's Despatch report Calcutta University was established in 1857. The first governor and chancellor of this university was Lord Canning.",
            "keyString": "26128s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "__________ started The Adyar Bulletin, which continued until 1929",
            "optionA": "  Annie Besant ",
            "optionB": "  J. Krishnamurti ",
            "optionC": "  Durgabai Deshmukh ",
            "optionD": "  Kamaladevi Chattopadhyaya ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFrom 1908 onwards Dr Besant proceeded to enlarge the Headquarters estate at Adyar. In order to link Adyar more intimately with the rest of the Theosophical world, she started The Adyar Bulletin, which continued until 1929. Presently the Adyar Newsletter fulfils a similar function. ",
            "keyString": "26144s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The All India Muslim League was formed in 1906 at",
            "optionA": "  Lucknow ",
            "optionB": "  Dacca ",
            "optionC": "  Lahore ",
            "optionD": "  Aligarh ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe All India Muslim League was rooted in 1906 at Dhaka. It emerged from the Aligarh Movement, formed originally to promote a modern education for Muslims. Muslim League, political organization of India and Pakistan, founded 1906 as the All-India Muslim League by Aga Khan III. ",
            "keyString": "101897s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first Famine Commission was constituted under",
            "optionA": "  Sir Richard Strachey ",
            "optionB": "  Sir John Strachey ",
            "optionC": "  Roberts ",
            "optionD": "  Chamberlain ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first Famine Commission (1878-80) under Sir Richard Strachey was appointed and it made many commendable recommendations. They include provision of funds for famine relief and construction work in the annual budget. The Famine Code came into existence in 1883. In 1878, the Vernacular Press Act was passed. ",
            "keyString": "101941s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The number of members in the Simon Commission/was __________",
            "optionA": "  10 ",
            "optionB": "  20 ",
            "optionC": "  7 ",
            "optionD": "  12 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe commission consisted of seven members\u2014four Conservatives, two Labourites, and one Liberal\u2014under the joint chairmanship of the distinguished Liberal lawyer, Sir John Simon, and Clement Attlee, the future prime minister. ",
            "keyString": "102070s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is commonly known as the 'Iron Man'?",
            "optionA": "  Sardar Vallabh Bhai Patel ",
            "optionB": "  Vittal Bhai Patel ",
            "optionC": "  Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "optionD": "  Bipin Chandra Pal ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSardar Vallabh bhai Patel is Commonly known as the Iron man (for his patience), and also known as Bismark (for political expertness), Sardar (title gave him by Gandhi ji during Bardoli Movement). ",
            "keyString": "102183s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Charter Act of 1793 Renewed the Company's monopoly for __________ years",
            "optionA": "  20 years ",
            "optionB": "  10 years ",
            "optionC": "  30 years ",
            "optionD": "  15 years ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Charter Act 1793 or the East India Company Act 1793 was passed by British Parliament to renew the charter of East India Company. This act authorized the company to carry on trade with India for next 20 years. ",
            "keyString": "102286s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "August Offer' was issued on __________ 1940",
            "optionA": "  08 August. ",
            "optionB": "  15 August. ",
            "optionC": "  20 August. ",
            "optionD": "  30 August. ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe August Offer was a proposal made by the British government on 08 August, 1940 promising the expansion of the Executive Council of the Viceroy of India to include more Indians, the establishment of an advisory war council, giving full weight to minority opinion, and the recognition of Indians right to frame their own constitution (after the end of the war). ",
            "keyString": "162553s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"India for the Indians\" was the political message of",
            "optionA": "  D E Wacha ",
            "optionB": "  Vivekanand ",
            "optionC": "  Dayanand ",
            "optionD": "  Hume ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t\"India for the Indians\" was the political message of Dayanand. ",
            "keyString": "162624s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Baba Ram Singh passed away on November 29, __________",
            "optionA": "  1885 ",
            "optionB": "  1887 ",
            "optionC": "  1889 ",
            "optionD": "  1923 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRam Singh was promptly deported to Rangoon. Later on he was sent to Andaman under life imprisonment. He passed away on November 29, 1885. ",
            "keyString": "162643s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Murshid Quli Khan, Alivardi Khan and\nSirajuddaullah were all nawabs of__________ ?",
            "optionA": "  Lucknow ",
            "optionB": "  Varanasi ",
            "optionC": "  Hyderabad ",
            "optionD": "  Bengal ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMurshid Quli khan, Alivardi khan and Siraj-ud-daullah,were the Nawab of Bengal. At the time of Battle of Plassey the Nawab of Bengal was Siraj-ud-daullah. ",
            "keyString": "162658s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was not among the three revolutionaries who were hanged on March 23, 1931?",
            "optionA": "  Bhagat Singh ",
            "optionB": "  Azad ",
            "optionC": "  Rajguru ",
            "optionD": "  Sukhdev ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAzad was not among the three revolutionaries who were hanged on March 23, 1931. ",
            "keyString": "162669s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Province of Bengal Constituted by the Act of 1935 would cease to exist as per __________",
            "optionA": "  The Cabinet Mission Plan ",
            "optionB": "  Wavell's Plan ",
            "optionC": "  The Indian Independence Act of 1947 ",
            "optionD": "  The Dikie Bird Plan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indian Independence Act was based upon the Mountbatten plan of 3rd June 1947 and was passed by the British parliament on 5 July 1947. It received royal assent on 18 July 1947. ",
            "keyString": "252367s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The All India Muslim League was founded in December 1906 at",
            "optionA": "  Karachi ",
            "optionB": "  Dacca ",
            "optionC": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionD": "  Aligarh ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMuslim League was founded in 30 December 1906, the All-India Muslim League was founded at Dhaka. ",
            "keyString": "252588s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statements is not correct? Provision was made In the Act of 1935 for",
            "optionA": "  The Central Subjects ",
            "optionB": "  Provincial Subjects ",
            "optionC": "  Concurrent Lists ",
            "optionD": "  A List of Subjects for Princely States ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA princely state, also called native state, feudatory state or Indian state (for those states on the subcontinent), was a vassal state under a local or regional ruler in a subsidiary alliance with the British Raj. ",
            "keyString": "252787s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During the Second World War Churchill replaced __________ as Prime Minister of England",
            "optionA": "  Chamberlain ",
            "optionB": "  Attlee ",
            "optionC": "  Disraeli ",
            "optionD": "  Asquith ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWinston Churchill, First Lord of the Admiralty, is called to replace Neville Chamberlain as British prime minister following the latter's resignation after losing a confidence vote in the House of Commons. ",
            "keyString": "252968s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was the Gandhi Irwin Pact made?",
            "optionA": "  1935 ",
            "optionB": "  1931 ",
            "optionC": "  1929 ",
            "optionD": "  1932 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGandhi - Irwin pact made in 1931, as per this pact Gandhi accepted to attend the second round table conference at London and suspended the civil disobedience. ",
            "keyString": "253137s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Presidents of early English Settlements (Madras, Bombay and Calcutta) were responsible to __________",
            "optionA": "  The House of Common ",
            "optionB": "  The House of Lords ",
            "optionC": "  The Home Government of the Company ",
            "optionD": "  The Council of Senior Merchants ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Bombay Presidency, also known as Bombay and Sind from 1843 to 1936 and the Bombay Province, was an administrative subdivision (presidency) of British India. The presidents of early English settlements (Madras, Bombay and Calcutta) were responsible to the home government of the company. ",
            "keyString": "314815s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Lucknow Session of INC and the Lucknow Pact (1916) were significant on account of",
            "optionA": "  unity between the Moderates and the Extremists with the return of the Extremists to the Congress ",
            "optionB": "  the pact between the Congress and Muslim League ",
            "optionC": "  both A and B above ",
            "optionD": "  the beginning of the tide of Indian Nationalism ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Lucknow Session of INC and the Lucknow Pact (1916) were significant on account of unity between the Moderates and the Extremists with the return of the Extremists to the Congress and the pact between the Congress and Muslim League. ",
            "keyString": "315005s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "By the Act of 1858, the powers of the Board of Control and the Court of Directors were transferred to __________",
            "optionA": "  The Secretary of State ",
            "optionB": "  Parliament ",
            "optionC": "  Viceroy ",
            "optionD": "  Commander-in-Chief ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBy the Act of 1858, the powers of the Board of Control and the Court of Directors were transferred to The Secretary of State. ",
            "keyString": "315171s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Portuguese Governor who abolished Sati in Goa was",
            "optionA": "  Albuquerque ",
            "optionB": "  Cabral ",
            "optionC": "  Almeida ",
            "optionD": "  De Braganza ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPortuguese Governor Alfanso-De-Albuqurque abolished Sati in Goa. He conquest Goa in 1510. ",
            "keyString": "315331s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who formed SNDP Yogam?",
            "optionA": "  T. K. Madhavan ",
            "optionB": "  Nataraja Guru ",
            "optionC": "  Narayana Guru ",
            "optionD": "  Dr. Palpu ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Sree Narayana Dharma Paripalana Yogam (SNDP) was founded in 1903 with the guidance and blessings of Sree Narayana Guru. ",
            "keyString": "315487s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following wars decided the fate of the French in India?",
            "optionA": "  Battle of Wandiwash ",
            "optionB": "  First Carnatic War ",
            "optionC": "  Battle of Buxar ",
            "optionD": "  Battle of Plassey ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBattle of Wandiwash was fought in 1760. It was the end of future for the French in Bengal and also in India. ",
            "keyString": "406502s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Whom did Bal Gangadhar Tilak refer to as his Political Guru?",
            "optionA": "  Swami Vivekananda ",
            "optionB": "  Ram Mohan Roy ",
            "optionC": "  Sisir Kumar ",
            "optionD": "  Dadabhai Naoroji E.  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option E",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahadev Govind Ranade was born in 1842 at Biphad in Nasik, Maharashtra. Known to be the mentor and political guru of famous freedom fighters Gopal Krishna Gokhale, and Bal Gangadhar Tilak,he himself was deeply involved in the freedom struggle of India. ",
            "keyString": "406538s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following pair is incorrect?",
            "optionA": "  Comrade  - Mohammed Ali ",
            "optionB": "  Indian Sociologist  -  Lala Har Dayal ",
            "optionC": "  Young India  -  Lala Lajpat Rai ",
            "optionD": "  Common Weal -  Annie Besant ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tYoung India was a weekly paper or journal in English published by Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi from 1919 to 1931. ",
            "keyString": "406552s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Young Bengal group published the __________(Quest for Knowledge) for propagating their views",
            "optionA": "  Jnananvesan ",
            "optionB": "  Parthenon ",
            "optionC": "  Hesperus ",
            "optionD": "  Enquirer ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Young Bengal group published the Jnananvesan (Quest for Knowledge) for propagating their views. ",
            "keyString": "406565s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indian Universities were first founded in the\ntime of",
            "optionA": "  Macaulay ",
            "optionB": "  Warren Hastings ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Canning ",
            "optionD": "  Lord William Bentinck ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian Universities were first founded during period of Lord Canning in three Presidencies. ",
            "keyString": "406577s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Netaji Subhash Chandra Bose had proclaimed the formation of the Provisional Government of Independent India (Azad Hind) in",
            "optionA": "  Vienna ",
            "optionB": "  Rangoon ",
            "optionC": "  Tokyo ",
            "optionD": "  Singapore ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 21 October 1943, Subhas Bose, who was now popularly known as Netaji, proclaimed the formation of the provisional government of independent India (Azad Hind) in Singapore. ",
            "keyString": "466477s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Idea of federation was first proposed in",
            "optionA": "  Indian Councils Act of 1892 ",
            "optionB": "  Morley Minto Reforms ",
            "optionC": "  Montague Chelmsford Reforms ",
            "optionD": "  Nehru Report of 1928 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t The Idea of federation was proposed in Nehru report (By Moti Lal Nehru) and rejected by Muslim league and others on differentmatters. ",
            "keyString": "466931s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The leader of the Anuslian Samiti was",
            "optionA": "  Barindra Kumar Ghosh ",
            "optionB": "  Pulin Das ",
            "optionC": "  Kanai Lal Dutta ",
            "optionD": "  Prafulla Chaki ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe revolutionary organisation 'Anuslian Samiti' was started under the leadership of Barindra Kumar Ghosh and Arabindo Ghosh II. ",
            "keyString": "467346s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the founder of 'Gadhar party'",
            "optionA": "  Sachindranath Sanyal ",
            "optionB": "  Chandarshekhar Azad ",
            "optionC": "  Lala Har Dayal ",
            "optionD": "  Batukeshwar Dutt ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGadhar party was founded in 1913 by NRI revolutionary in USA (San Francisco). Main leaders of the Gadhar Party were Lala Hardayal Ramchandra, Bhagwan singh, Kartar Singh Saraba, Barkatullah and Bhai Parmanand. It was dissolved in 1919. ",
            "keyString": "535336s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following novels was a source of inspiration for the freedom fighters in India?",
            "optionA": "  Pariksha Guru ",
            "optionB": "  Anandmath ",
            "optionC": "  Rangbhoomi ",
            "optionD": "  Padmarag ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnandmath was written by Bankim Chandra Chatterjee. It is about the Sanyasi Rebellion in 18th century. The famous slogan \"Vande Matrarn\" was taken from this epic and it was the motivation for the national leaders. ",
            "keyString": "535876s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following acts gave representation of the Indians for the first time in legislation?",
            "optionA": "  Indian Councils Act, 1909 ",
            "optionB": "  Indian Councils Act, 1919 ",
            "optionC": "  Government of India Act, 1935 ",
            "optionD": "  Government of India Act, 1935 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian Council act, 1909 gave representation of the Indians for the first time in legislation. This act is also known as Morley-Minto reform. This act gives the separate electorate for muslims.",
            "keyString": "536313s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "After the elections to the Constituent Assembly were held in July 1946, the Constituent Assembly met for the first time in New Delhi on",
            "optionA": "  December 9, 1946 ",
            "optionB": "  January 15, 1947 ",
            "optionC": "  February 10, 1947 ",
            "optionD": "  August 15, 1947 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Assembly met for the first time in New Delhi on 9 December 1946, and its last session was held on 24 January 1950. ",
            "keyString": "536733s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The most Important cause for the outbreak of the Ghadar revolution was the",
            "optionA": "  Commencement of World War I ",
            "optionB": "  Hanging of Kartar Singh Sarabha ",
            "optionC": "  Komagata Maru Incident ",
            "optionD": "  Arrest of Lala Hardayal ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe most Important cause for the outbreak of the Ghadar revolution was the Komagata Maru Incident. ",
            "keyString": "537179s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Whom would you associate with the Censorship of the Press Act 1794?",
            "optionA": "  Charles Metcalfe ",
            "optionB": "  Andrew Frazer ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Wellesly ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Auckland ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1799, Lord Wellesley brought the Censorship of Press Act, 1799. The idea was to stop the French from publishing anything which could harm British in any way. This act brought all the newspapers under the Government scrutiny before their publication. ",
            "keyString": "613087s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Woods Despatch of 1854 resulted in the",
            "optionA": "  Founding of several Indian universities ",
            "optionB": "  Introduction of the postal system ",
            "optionC": "  Establishment of the education system ",
            "optionD": "  Abolition of child marriage ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn accordance with Wood\u2019s despatch, Education Departments were established in every province and universities were opened at Calcutta, Bombay and Madras on the model of the London University. ",
            "keyString": "613724s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Charter Act of 1813 allotted Rupees __________ annually for Indian learning and spread of Scientific knowledge",
            "optionA": "  One lakh ",
            "optionB": "  Two lakhs ",
            "optionC": "  \u00a310000 ",
            "optionD": "  \u00a35000 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first real support came through the allocation of 1 lakh rupees per year by the Charter Act of 1813. Soon after, Hindu college was set up in 1817, which later came to be called Presidency College in 1857. ",
            "keyString": "614332s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The maximum number of additional members for the council of Bengal was raised from 20 to __________",
            "optionA": "  60 ",
            "optionB": "  50 ",
            "optionC": "  70 ",
            "optionD": "  25 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe maximum number of additional members for the council of Bengal was raised from 20 to 50. ",
            "keyString": "614702s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mahatma Gandhi's remark, \"A post-dated cheque on a crumbling bank\" is regarding the proposals of",
            "optionA": "  Simmon Commission ",
            "optionB": "  Cripps Mission ",
            "optionC": "  Cabinet Mission ",
            "optionD": "  Wavel Plan ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCripps Mission (headed by Sir Stafford Cripps) came to India in 1942 to secure full Indian co-operation for world war-II. Gandhiji remarked Cripps Mission as Post dated Cheque on a crumbling bank. ",
            "keyString": "614893s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Tilak started his career as a",
            "optionA": "  Writer ",
            "optionB": "  Professor ",
            "optionC": "  Journalist ",
            "optionD": "  Lawyer ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBal Gangadhar Tilak (or Lokmanya Tilak, 23 July 1856 \u2013 1 August 1920), born as Keshav Gangadhar Tilak, was an Indian nationalist, teacher, lawyer and an independence activist. ",
            "keyString": "701324s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which was the earliest settlement of the Dutch in India?",
            "optionA": "  Masulipatnam ",
            "optionB": "  Pulicat ",
            "optionC": "  Surat ",
            "optionD": "  Ahmedabad ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Dutch East Indian Company was established in 1602 with the monopoly of spice trade for 21 year. Its earliest settlement in India was at Pulicat. ",
            "keyString": "701849s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Upon whom was the title 'Punjab Kesari' conferred?",
            "optionA": "  Bhagat Singh ",
            "optionB": "  Sardar Baldev Singh ",
            "optionC": "  Lala Lajpat Rai ",
            "optionD": "  Ranjit Singh ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe title 'Punjab Kesari' was conferred on Lala Lajpat Rai. ",
            "keyString": "702324s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said \"Truth is the ultimate reality and it is God\"?",
            "optionA": "  Swamy Vivekananda ",
            "optionB": "  Rabindra Nath Tagore ",
            "optionC": "  M. K. Gandhi ",
            "optionD": "  Radhakrishnan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThis statement was given by the M.K Gandhi because he believed in non-violence and truth. ",
            "keyString": "702780s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "According to the Regulating Act, Directors were to be elected for a period of",
            "optionA": "  5 years ",
            "optionB": "  4 years ",
            "optionC": "  6 years ",
            "optionD": "  3 years ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to the Regulating Act, Directors were to be elected for a period of 4 years. ",
            "keyString": "703337s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1893 __________represented The Theosophical Society at the World Parliament of Religions in Chicago",
            "optionA": "  Annie Besant ",
            "optionB": "  George Thompson ",
            "optionC": "  GF Remfry ",
            "optionD": "  Ramgopal Ghosh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1893 she landed in India, made a tour of the country in the company of H. S. Olcott, and, by her splendid presentation of Indian philosophy and her undisguised personal preference for the Indian spiritual heritage, won the support of orthodox Brahmins to Theosophy.The transformation of the religious life in India, particularly among Hindus, is one of the wonders she performed. ",
            "keyString": "802686s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The All India Muslim league was founded by",
            "optionA": "  Maulana Ahmed Ali ",
            "optionB": "  Mohammad Ali Jinnah ",
            "optionC": "  Agha Khan ",
            "optionD": "  Hakim Ajmal Khan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll India Muslim League was founded by the Agha Khan and Salim-Ullah-Khan (Nawab of Dhaka) in December 1906. ",
            "keyString": "803148s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Frontier Gandhi actively participated in",
            "optionA": "  Khilafat Movement ",
            "optionB": "  Non-Cooperation Movement ",
            "optionC": "  Civil Disobedience Movement ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKhan Abdul Ghaffar was a political and spiritual leader known for his nonviolent opposition, and a lifelong pacifist and devout Muslim. Khan Abdul Gaffar Khan was an active supporter of The Civil Disobedience Movement from The North-West Frontier Province . ",
            "keyString": "803475s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Gandhi-Irwin Pact was signed on",
            "optionA": "  March 10, 1930 ",
            "optionB": "  March 20, 1931 ",
            "optionC": "  March 20,1932 ",
            "optionD": "  March 5,1931 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Gandhi-Irwin Pact was a political agreement signed by Mahatma Gandhi and Lord Irwin, the then Viceroy of India, on 5 March 1931 before the second Round Table Conference in London. ",
            "keyString": "803769s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Among the numerous followers of Gandhi's 'philosophy' was/were",
            "optionA": "  Bertrand Russell ",
            "optionB": "  Marshal Tito ",
            "optionC": "  Khan Abdul Gaffar Khan ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKhan Abdul Gaffar Khan was follower of Gandhi's 'philosophy'. ",
            "keyString": "804049s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Vivekananda felt that the Parliament would provide the right forum to present his Master's message to the world, and so he decided to go to America. Another reason which prompted Swamiji to go to America was to seek financial help for his project of uplifting the masses. Swamiji, however, wanted to have an inner certitude and divine call regarding his mission. Both of these he got while he sat in deep meditation on the rock-island at __________",
            "optionA": "  Mumbai ",
            "optionB": "  America ",
            "optionC": "  Kanyakumari ",
            "optionD": "  Chennai ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVivekananda felt that the Parliament would provide the right forum to present his Master's message to the world, and so he decided to go to America. Another reason which prompted Swamiji to go to America was to seek financial help for his project of uplifting the masses. Swamiji, however, wanted to have an inner certitude and divine call regarding his mission. Both of these he got while he sat in deep meditation on the rock-island at Kanyakumari. ",
            "keyString": "919394s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the founder of the Servants of India Society?",
            "optionA": "  G K Gokhale ",
            "optionB": "  MG Ranade ",
            "optionC": "  B G Tilak ",
            "optionD": "  Bipin Chandra Pal ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tServants of India Society was founded on 12 June 1905 by Gopal Krishna Gokhale to build a dedicated group of people for social service and reforms. ",
            "keyString": "919852s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who gave the slogan \"Inquilab Zindabad?",
            "optionA": "  Chandrashekhar Azad ",
            "optionB": "  Subhash Chandra Bose ",
            "optionC": "  Bhagat Singh ",
            "optionD": "  Iqbal ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe slogan \"Inquilab Zindabad\" was given by the Bhagat Singh. The meaning of inquilab is - Revolution. ",
            "keyString": "920071s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Subhash Bose selected the best soldiers from the three existing brigades (named after Gandhi, Azad and Nehru) and organised a new brigade which the soldiers themselves called",
            "optionA": "  Himalayan Brigade ",
            "optionB": "  Swatantra Bharat Brigade ",
            "optionC": "  Bhagat Singh Brigade ",
            "optionD": "  Subhash Brigade ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSubhash Bose selected the best soldiers from the three existing brigades (named after Gandhi, Azad and Nehru) and organised a new brigade which the soldiers themselves called Subhash Brigade. ",
            "keyString": "922135s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Aligarh Institute Gazette, an organ of the Scientific Society was started in March . . . . . and succeeded in transforming the minds in the traditional Muslim Society",
            "optionA": "  1766 ",
            "optionB": "  1866 ",
            "optionC": "  1869 ",
            "optionD": "  1870 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Aligarh Institute Gazette was the first multilingual journal of India, introduced, edited, and published in 1866 by Sir Syed Ahmed Khan which was read widely across the country. Theodore Beck later became its editor. The Aligarh Institute Gazette, an organ of the Scientific Society was started in March and succeeded in transforming the minds in the traditional Muslim Society 1866. ",
            "keyString": "922366s7m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was in favour of a partyless democracy?",
            "optionA": "  Jai Prakash Narayan ",
            "optionB": "  Bhupendra Nath Dutta ",
            "optionC": "  M. N. Roy ",
            "optionD": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJai Prakash Narayan popularly known as JP or Lok Nayak believed in Partyless democracy. J.P was an independence activist and advocated a program of social transformation which he termed as Sampurna Kranti. ",
            "keyString": "101630s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "According to __________ the mutiny was a purely military outbreak",
            "optionA": "  VD Sarkar ",
            "optionB": "  VASmith ",
            "optionC": "  Sir John Lawrence ",
            "optionD": "  Roberts ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to Sir John Lawrence the mutiny was a purely military outbreak. ",
            "keyString": "101868s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Aurobindo was arrested in connection with",
            "optionA": "  Alipore Bomb case ",
            "optionB": "  Kolhapur Bomb Case ",
            "optionC": "  Lahore Conspiracy Case ",
            "optionD": "  Kakori ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe 'Alipore Bomb Case' was \"the first state trial of any magnitude in India\". The British Government arrested Sri Aurobindo, a prominent Nationalist Leader at the time, Barindra Ghose, and many young revolutionaries. They were charged with \"Conspiracy\" or \"waging war against the King\" - the equivalent of high treason and punishable with death by hanging. ",
            "keyString": "102071s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Tata Iron and Steel Works was completed with the aid of",
            "optionA": "  Japanese experts ",
            "optionB": "  Russian experts ",
            "optionC": "  American experts ",
            "optionD": "  French experts ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe founder of the Tata Iron & Steel Company - now called Tata Steel - never lived to see it incorporated. TISCO was born in 1907 - three years after Jamsedji Nusserwanji Tata died. Tata had been pursuing the dream of setting up a steel plant in India since at least 1882. In 1902, he even travelled to Pittsburgh to seek the help of American geologist and metallurgist Charles Page Perin. ",
            "keyString": "102295s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A Federal Railway Authority was established by the Act of",
            "optionA": "  1909 ",
            "optionB": "  1919 ",
            "optionC": "  1935 ",
            "optionD": "  1861 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Government of India Act 1935 introduced the provincial autonomy and provided for an all India federation. This act introduced dyarchy at the central level. This act had 321 sections and 10 schedules. It made a provision for establishment of a Federal court. ",
            "keyString": "102473s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the architect of North and South Blocks of the central Secretariat in Delhi?",
            "optionA": "  Sir Edward Lutyens ",
            "optionB": "  Herbert Bakers ",
            "optionC": "  Robert Tor Tussell ",
            "optionD": "  Antonin Raymond ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSir Edward Lutyens was an British architect. He designed many buildings in India i.e. India Gate, and he also designed viceroy's house which is known as the Rashtrapati Bhavan.",
            "keyString": "264012s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "India was partitioned as a consequence of the formula contained in",
            "optionA": "  Cabinet Mission Plan ",
            "optionB": "  Attlee's Declaration ",
            "optionC": "  June 3 Plan or Mountbatten Plan ",
            "optionD": "  Both B and C above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia was partitioned as a consequence of the formula contained in June 3 Plan or Mountbatten Plan. ",
            "keyString": "264451s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among of the following was the founder of society called 'Abhinav Bharat'?",
            "optionA": "  Lala Lajpat Rai ",
            "optionB": "  Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "optionC": "  Vinayak Damodar Savarkar ",
            "optionD": "  Bipin Chandra Pal ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAbhinav Bharat Society was founded by Vinayak Damodar Savarkar and his brother Ganesh Damodar Savarkar in 1903. It was initially famous as a name of Mitra Mela. It was inspired by Mazzini's \"Young Italy\".",
            "keyString": "264707s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which year did Bankim Chandra Chattopadhyay wrote Anandmath?",
            "optionA": "  1858 ",
            "optionB": "  1892 ",
            "optionC": "  1882 ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Anandmath was written by Bankim Chandra in 1882. The national song 'Vande Matram' was a part of Anandmath. Sanyasi revolt was also described in this epic. ",
            "keyString": "264919s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "To face the Maratha Army the Rohelas chief entered into a pact with",
            "optionA": "  The Nawab of Awadh ",
            "optionB": "  The French ",
            "optionC": "  The Portuguese ",
            "optionD": "  The Sikhs ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTo face the Maratha Army the Rohelas chief entered into a pact withthe Nawab of Awadh. ",
            "keyString": "266075s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following was not to be ceded by Mir Kasim to the Company as per the treaty signed between Mir Kasim and Calcutta Council?",
            "optionA": "  Burdwan ",
            "optionB": "  Midnapur ",
            "optionC": "  Chittagong ",
            "optionD": "  Monghyr ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMonghyr was not to be ceded by Mir Kasim to the Company as per the treaty signed between Mir Kasim and Calcutta Council. ",
            "keyString": "355505s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "__________ was primarily responsible for making India a secular State",
            "optionA": "  Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  Patel ",
            "optionC": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionD": "  Gokhale ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNehru is known as an architect of Indian secularism. The constitution of India contains his philosophy about the religious neutral state. ",
            "keyString": "355735s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "One of the following was not involved in the Chittagong Armoury Raid, 1934. Who was he?",
            "optionA": "  Kalpana Dutt ",
            "optionB": "  Surya Sen ",
            "optionC": "  Pritialata Woddekar ",
            "optionD": "  Dinesh Gupta ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDinesh Gupta was not involved in the Chittagong Armoury Raid. Armoury raid was done under the leadership of Surya sen. He was also known as Master Da. ",
            "keyString": "355938s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Arrange in chronological order:\n1. Cabinet Mission\n2. Cripps Mission\n3. Montague-Chelmsford Reforms\n4. Minto-Morley Reforms",
            "optionA": "  3, 2, 4, 1 ",
            "optionB": "  1, 2, 3, 4 ",
            "optionC": "  4, 3, 2, 1 ",
            "optionD": "  2, 3, 4, 1 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMinto- Morley reforms(1909), Monatague- Chelmsford reforms(1919), Crips Mission- 1942, Cabinet Mission- 1946. ",
            "keyString": "356126s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Minto Morley reforms was in the year __________",
            "optionA": "  1906 ",
            "optionB": "  1907 ",
            "optionC": "  1909 ",
            "optionD": "  1919 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA 1909 legislative enactment, called the Morley-Minto reforms, conferred some political reforms which encouraged the constitutionalists in the Congress. Indians who could be elected to the legislatures on the basis of the 1861 Indian Councils Act increased numerically. ",
            "keyString": "356615s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Tashkent Agreement was signed between India and __________",
            "optionA": "  Pakistan ",
            "optionB": "  China ",
            "optionC": "  Tibet ",
            "optionD": "  Afghanistan ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Tashkent Declaration was a peace agreement between India and Pakistan signed on 10 January 1966 that resolved the Indo-Pakistani War of 1965. ",
            "keyString": "470426s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The inaugural issue of Bombay Darpan, a Marathi weekly, was published on November 12, 1832 started by a publisher reformer named",
            "optionA": "  Jagannath Shankar ",
            "optionB": "  Vishnu Shastri ",
            "optionC": "  Bal Shastri ",
            "optionD": "  Krishna Shastri ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBalshastri Jambhekar (6 january 1812 \u2013 18 May 1846) is also known as Father of Marathi journalism for his efforts in starting journalism in Marathi language. The inaugural issue of Bombay Darpan, a Marathi weekly, was published on 12 November 1832 started by him. ",
            "keyString": "470644s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "For which community were seats reserved by the Morley-Minto reforms?",
            "optionA": "  Jews ",
            "optionB": "  Muslims ",
            "optionC": "  Christians ",
            "optionD": "  Sikhs ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMorley-Minto reforms also known as India council act 1909, the act introduced separate and discriminatory electorate. This was for the first time that, the seats in the legislative bodies were reserve on the basis of religion for Muslims. ",
            "keyString": "470839s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who, among the following, founded the 'All India Depressed Classes Federation' in 1920?",
            "optionA": "  M. K. Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  Jyotiba Phule ",
            "optionC": "  G. K. Gokhale ",
            "optionD": "  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt was founded to protect and promote the interest of Depressed classes or Untouchable. In later phase, he urge his followers to leave Hindu altogether. ",
            "keyString": "471028s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said: \"Let the pilgrims congregate at the beginning of the Gregorian calendar year. It should be Dhanu 16-17 in Malayalam calendar. Let the pilgrims observe 10 days self-purification according to Sri Buddha's principles of five purities - body, food, mind, word, and deed called as Pancha Dharma\"",
            "optionA": "  S. Sankunni ",
            "optionB": "  P. V. Raghavan ",
            "optionC": "  M. S. Raghavan ",
            "optionD": "  Sree Narayana Guru ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSree Narayana Guru said \"Let the pilgrims congregate at the beginning of the Gregorian calendar year. It should be Dhanu 16-17 in Malayalam calendar. Let the pilgrims observe 10 days self-purification according to Sri Buddha's principles of five purities - body, food, mind, word, and deed called as Pancha Dharma\". ",
            "keyString": "471206s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Narayana Guru was the son of__________",
            "optionA": "  Madan Asan ",
            "optionB": "  Krishnan Vaidyan ",
            "optionC": "  Kummampilli Raman Pillai Asan ",
            "optionD": "  Kumaran ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere are many legends surrounding the life of Narayana Guru but few certain facts until his rise to prominence in 1887. He was born probably in 1854, the son of an Ezhava peasant, Madan Asan and his wife Kuttiyamma, in the village of Chempazhanthy near Thiruvananthapuram. ",
            "keyString": "582653s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "With which of the following was Annie Besant Associated?",
            "optionA": "  Ramakrishna Mission ",
            "optionB": "  Arya Samaj ",
            "optionC": "  ISKCON (International Society for Krishna Consciousness) ",
            "optionD": "  Theosophical Society ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhen Blavatsky died in 1891, Besant was left as one of the leading figures in theosophy and in 1893 she represented it at the Chicago World Fair. The original society, then led by Henry Steel Olcott and Besant, is today based in Chennai, India, and is known as the Theosophical Society Adyar. ",
            "keyString": "582864s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "'Anthology of the Bomb' was written by",
            "optionA": "  Tilak ",
            "optionB": "  Bipin Chandra Pal ",
            "optionC": "  Gokhale ",
            "optionD": "  Annie Besant ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBipin Chandra Pal a powerful orator of the extremist school to which Tilak belonged. Once he wrote an article ' Anthology of the Bomb' for which he was tried, but he apologised. ",
            "keyString": "583044s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Wahabis were __________ fanatics",
            "optionA": "  Hindu ",
            "optionB": "  Muslim ",
            "optionC": "  Christian ",
            "optionD": "  Sikh ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWahhabism is an Islamic doctrine and religious movement founded by Muhammad ibn Abd al-Wahhab. It has been variously described as \"ultraconservative\", \"austere\", \"fundamentalist\", or \"puritan(ical)\"; as an Islamic \"reform movement\" to restore \"pure monotheistic worship\" (tawhid) by devotees; and as a \"deviant sectarian movement\", \"vile sect\" and a distortion of Islam by its opponents. Wahabis were Muslim fanatics. ",
            "keyString": "583220s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The strategy of 'divide and rule' had been actually practised by",
            "optionA": "  Lord Curzon ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Wellesley ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Minto ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Dufferin ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe strategy of 'divide and rule' had been actually practised by Lord Minto. ",
            "keyString": "583393s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Moplahs of Malabar (Kerala) who were largely Muslim leaseholders and cultivators, indulged in a series of rebellions in Kerala between 1836-1919. Which of the following regarding these Moplah uprisings is not true?",
            "optionA": "  They were mainly directed against the upper caste Hindu landlords ",
            "optionB": "  These uprisings were a peculiar form of rural terrorism ",
            "optionC": "  Most of the Moplah martyrs were poor peasants of landless lobourers ",
            "optionD": "  A small band of Moplahs committed collective suicides in the belief of being called Shahids (martyrs) ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA small band of Moplahs committed collective suicides in the belief of being called Shahids (martyrs) is not correct. ",
            "keyString": "844047s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Nanu met Kunjan Pillai, who later came to be known as Chattampi Swamikal. Kunjan Pillai, who discovered and appreciated Nanu's philosophical genius and passion for Yoga, introduced him to__________, a 'Hatha yogi'",
            "optionA": "  Madan Asan ",
            "optionB": "  Thycattu Ayyaavu ",
            "optionC": "  Krishnan Vaidyan ",
            "optionD": "  Kumaran Asan ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNanu met Kunjan Pillai, who later came to be known as Chattampi Swamikal. Kunjan Pillai, who discovered and appreciated Nanu's philosophical genius and passion for Yoga, introduced him to Thycattu Ayyaavu, a 'Hatha yogi'. ",
            "keyString": "847265s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "One of the best known tribal rebellions in Bihar, known as Ulgulan (meaning Great Tumult), was launched by the Mundas under the leadership of",
            "optionA": "  Kanhu ",
            "optionB": "  Sidhu ",
            "optionC": "  Birsa Munda ",
            "optionD": "  Rampa Munda ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOne of the best known tribal rebellions In Bihar, known as Ulgulan (meaning Great Tumult), was launched by the Mundas under the leadership of Birsa Munda. ",
            "keyString": "849813s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "According to __________ the Mutiny was a popular rebellion",
            "optionA": "  V D Sarkar ",
            "optionB": "  V ASmith ",
            "optionC": "  L Mukherjee ",
            "optionD": "  Chabbra ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to V A Smith the mutiny was a popular rebellion. The Sepoy mutiny which started in 1857 threatened the British East India Company's very presence in India. ",
            "keyString": "850430s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The idea of starting a Home Rule League in 1915 was first propounded by",
            "optionA": "  B G Tilak ",
            "optionB": "  Gopal Krishna Gokhale ",
            "optionC": "  Annie Besant ",
            "optionD": "  Both A and B above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe idea of starting a Home Rule League in 1915 was first propounded by Annie Besant. ",
            "keyString": "850971s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who worte \"Sarfaroshi Ki Tamanna Ab Hamaare Dil Mein Hai\"?",
            "optionA": "  Mohammad Iqbal ",
            "optionB": "  Ramprasad Bismil ",
            "optionC": "  Kazi Nazrul Islam ",
            "optionD": "  Firaq Gorakhpuri ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSarfaroshi ki Tamanna is a patriotic poem which was written by Bismil Azimabadi in 1921. Later it was immortalised by Ram Prasad Bismil. ",
            "keyString": "930123s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Viewing the pathetic condition of widows and unfortunate children Jyotirao decided the open an orphanage called __________",
            "optionA": "  Satya Shodhak Samaj ",
            "optionB": "  Arya Samaj ",
            "optionC": "  Brahma Samaj ",
            "optionD": "  Ramakrishna Mission ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tViewing the pathetic condition of widows and unfortunate children Jyotirao decided the open an orphanage called Satya Shodhak Samaj. ",
            "keyString": "930343s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first plans for an Indian railway system was made by",
            "optionA": "  Minto ",
            "optionB": "  Amherst ",
            "optionC": "  Hardinge ",
            "optionD": "  Cornwallis ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first plans for an Indian railway system was made byHardinge. ",
            "keyString": "930565s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who composed the song \"Sare Jahan Se Achha Hindostan Hamara\"?",
            "optionA": "  Mohammed Iqbal ",
            "optionB": "  Josh Malihabadi ",
            "optionC": "  Bhagat Singh ",
            "optionD": "  Chandra Shekhar Azad ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMuhammad Iqbal was a famous poet, politician, philosopher and a remarkable academic. He was also a barrister in British India. He used poetry and songs to spread political awareness amongst the people. Iqbal wrote \u201cSare Jahan se Achha Hindustan Hamara\u201d, the famous song was used as a slogan to rejuvenate the youth with a feeling of patriotism. The abridged version of the song is still sung and is also played frequently as a marching song by the Indian Armed Forces. ",
            "keyString": "930759s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The song 'Jana-Gana-Mana' composed by Rabindra Nath Tagore was first published in January 1912 under the title of",
            "optionA": "  Jay He ",
            "optionB": "  Rashtra Jagriti ",
            "optionC": "  Bharat Vidhata ",
            "optionD": "  Matribhoomi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJana-Gana-Mana composed by Rabindra Nath Tagore in Bengali language. The song Jana Gana Mana was first published under the title \u201cBharat Vidhata\u201d in Tattva Bodhini Patrika in January, 1912. ",
            "keyString": "930929s8m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is called as the 'Prophet of New India'?",
            "optionA": "  Dayanand Saraswati ",
            "optionB": "  Sri Ramkrishna ",
            "optionC": "  Raja Ram Mohan Roy ",
            "optionD": "  Swami Vivekananda ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSri Ram Krishna is called as the \"Prophet of New India\". Honors of Sri Rama Krishna is Paramhansa. ",
            "keyString": "41900s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Chandra Shekhar Azad was __________ of the Hindustan Socialist Republican Army",
            "optionA": "  President ",
            "optionB": "  Secretary ",
            "optionC": "  Commander-in-Chief ",
            "optionD": "  Field Marshal ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChandra Shekhar Azad was Commander-in-Chief of the Hindustan Socialist Republican Army. ",
            "keyString": "42111s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Swami Vivekananda was graduated from __________University",
            "optionA": "  Delhi ",
            "optionB": "  Hyderabad ",
            "optionC": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionD": "  Karachi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSwami Vivekananda was graduated from Calcutta University. ",
            "keyString": "42274s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was advocated of the famous INA Trials?",
            "optionA": "  Bhulabhai Desai ",
            "optionB": "  Asaf Ali ",
            "optionC": "  Subhash Chandra Bose ",
            "optionD": "  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBhulabhai Desai was advocated of INA trial. INA defence committee, the legal defence team for INA formed by the Indian National Congress in 1945.",
            "keyString": "42432s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said about Mahatma Gandhi that he is a \"half naked Fakir\"?",
            "optionA": "  Winston Churchill ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Mountbatten ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Wavell ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Lirrlithgow ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring the second Round table conference Winston Churchill said to Gandhi ji - a half naked fakir and seditious Fakir. A Britisher Frank Morris also titled Gandhiji \"A half naked fakir\". ",
            "keyString": "42913s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "For the annexation of which Indian Kingdom, the \"Doctrine of Lapse\" was not followed?",
            "optionA": "  Satara ",
            "optionB": "  Nagpur ",
            "optionC": "  Jhansi ",
            "optionD": "  Punjab ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDoctrine of Lapse was not applied on Punjab. Punjab was annexed by Lord Dalhousie after second Anglo Sikkh war (1849). And Last Sikh Emperor was sent to London and he died in Paris. ",
            "keyString": "196003s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A Study in Consciousness was written by __________",
            "optionA": "  Annie Besant ",
            "optionB": "  Mrinal Gore ",
            "optionC": "  Prasanna Kumar Tagore ",
            "optionD": "  Rajkamal Sen ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tStudy in Consciousness is a book by Annie Besant that was written in ca. 1904. Besant intended this book to be a contribution to the science of psychology. She writes that the seed of consciousness is the tri-atomic Atma-Buddhi-Manas, the Jivatma. ",
            "keyString": "196224s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among of the following started Marathi fortnightly newspaper 'Bahishkrit Bharat'?",
            "optionA": "  Dr. ",
            "optionB": " R. Ambedkar ",
            "optionC": "  Vir Savarkar ",
            "optionD": "  Vinobha Bhave ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t'Bahishkrit Bharat' was started by Dr.B.R.Ambedkar in 1927, his other newspapers are - Mooknayak (1920), Janata (1930) and Prabuddha Bharat (An awakenned India- 1956) ",
            "keyString": "196390s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mahatma Gandhi was profoundly influenced by the writings of",
            "optionA": "  Bernard Shaw ",
            "optionB": "  Karl Marx ",
            "optionC": "  Lenin ",
            "optionD": "  Leo Tolstoy ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahatma Gandhi was profoundly influenced by the writing of Leo Tolstoy notable works of Tolstoy is War and Peace and The kingdom of God. ",
            "keyString": "196547s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Regulating Act was passed in the year",
            "optionA": "  1793 ",
            "optionB": "  1773 ",
            "optionC": "  1763 ",
            "optionD": "  1783 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRegulating Act, (1773), legislation passed by the British Parliament for the regulation of the British East India Company's Indian territories, mainly in Bengal. ",
            "keyString": "196712s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "As per Cabinet Mission Plan, the strength of the Constituent Assembly would be",
            "optionA": "  389 ",
            "optionB": "  289 ",
            "optionC": "  250 ",
            "optionD": "  350 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per Cabinet Mission Plan, the strength of the Constituent Assembly would be 389. ",
            "keyString": "336618s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "November 26, 1949 is a significant day in our constitutional history because",
            "optionA": "  India took a pledge of complete independence\non this day ",
            "optionB": "  The constitution was adopted on this day ",
            "optionC": "  India became a Republic on this day ",
            "optionD": "  The first amendment of the constitution was\npassed on this day ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 26 Nov 1949, the Constituent Assembly of India adopted the constitution of India and it came into effect from 26 Jan,1950. ",
            "keyString": "338011s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following was not contained in the Cripps Offer?",
            "optionA": "  Dominion Status to India ",
            "optionB": "  Constituent Assembly ",
            "optionC": "  Control of Defence of India by the Indian National Government ",
            "optionD": "  Right to take part in highest Counsels ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tControl of Defence of India by the Indian National Government was not contained in the Cripps Offer. ",
            "keyString": "338618s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement is incorrect about the Act of 1919?",
            "optionA": "  British India must an integral part of the British Empire ",
            "optionB": "  Responsible government would be realised only by progressive stages ",
            "optionC": "  Provincial subjects were classified into reserved subjects & transferred subjects ",
            "optionD": "  The salary of the Secretary of State for India was drawn out of the revenues of Indian government ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter the implementation of the 7th Pay Commission's awards on 1 January 2016, the Cabinet Secretary, who is the top-most bureaucrat in the country, gets Rs. 2.5 lakh per month and a Secretary in the Union government draws Rs. 2.25 lakh per month. ",
            "keyString": "338803s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "According to Gandhi, ahimsa could not be construed to mean",
            "optionA": "  truth ",
            "optionB": "  a positive state of law ",
            "optionC": "  tolerance of the wrong and unjust ",
            "optionD": "  doing good even to the evildoers ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to Gandhi, Ahimsa or Non-Violence has a positive meaning also. In positive sense Non- Violence means 'love'. That means one should not love only human being but every living being in the world. When a person claims to be non-violent, he is expected not to be angry with one who has injured him. ",
            "keyString": "338963s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The quintessence of Gandhian thought is",
            "optionA": "  Satyagraha ",
            "optionB": "  Metaphysics ",
            "optionC": "  Spiritualism ",
            "optionD": "  Moksha ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSatyagraha - the totality or most typical example of Gandhian thought can be regarded as Satyagraha which was the backbone of Gandhian Struggle. ",
            "keyString": "475363s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The day (22 December 1939) the Congress Ministries resigned in the Provinces the Muslim League observed",
            "optionA": "  Deliverance Day ",
            "optionB": "  Direct Action Day ",
            "optionC": "  Victory Day ",
            "optionD": "  Alliance Day ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 22 October 1939, the Congress called upon all its ministries to resign in the wake of the viceroy's declaration. On 2 December that year, League chief Muhammad Ali Jinnah called upon Indian Muslims to celebrate 22 December as 'Deliverance Day' from Congress. ",
            "keyString": "477617s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the Congress President at the time when India become free?",
            "optionA": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionB": "  V. L. Pandit ",
            "optionC": "  Sardar Patel ",
            "optionD": "  J. ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn spite of being ideologically at odds with both the right-wing Vallabhbhai Patel and the left-wing Jawaharlal Nehru \u2013 J B Kripalani was elected Congress President for the crucial years around Indian independence in 1947. ",
            "keyString": "480967s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The historic fast by Gandhi came to an end as a result of the",
            "optionA": "  Poona Pact ",
            "optionB": "  Issue of White Paper ",
            "optionC": "  Gandhi-Irwin Pact ",
            "optionD": "  Arrival of Simon Commission ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe historic fast by Gandhi came to an end as a result of the Poona Pact. ",
            "keyString": "481194s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following was impeached in the UK for his actions in India?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Wavell ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Ripon ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Hastings ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Cornwallis ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEdmund Burke on the impeachment of Warren Hastings (1788) Introduction: Warren Hastings (1732-1818) was the first Governor General of India (1778-1884). He resigned, returned to England, was impeached for his conduct in India and had to face a trial by Parliament. He was acquitted in 1795. ",
            "keyString": "481234s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In Gandhian Socialism",
            "optionA": "  State is required ",
            "optionB": "  State is not required ",
            "optionC": "  State is sometimes required and sometimes\nnot required ",
            "optionD": "  State is neither required ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGandhian socialism generally centres on Hind Swaraj or Indian Home rule. So according to Gandhiji's socialism state is not required. ",
            "keyString": "609287s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "'Amar Shonar Bangla' the national anthem of Bangladesh was composed by whom?",
            "optionA": "  Rabindranath Tagore ",
            "optionB": "  Sarojini Naidu ",
            "optionC": "  Surendranath Banerjee ",
            "optionD": "  Anand Mohan Bose ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRabindranath Tagore was a great Bengali Poet. He played important role in development of modern literature.He is titled as 'Guru dev'. He win noble prizes for \"Gitanjali\" in 1913. He also composed the song \"JAN GAN MAN\" (National Anthem of India) and \"AMAR SONAR BANGLA\" (National Anthem of Bangladesh). ",
            "keyString": "610313s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In the Carnatic, the English supported the claims of",
            "optionA": "  Anwaruddin ",
            "optionB": "  Chanda Sahib ",
            "optionC": "  Nasir Jang ",
            "optionD": "  Muzaffar Jang ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe French wanted to reduce the growing influence of the English in the Carnatic. So they supported Husain Dost Khan (Chanda Sahib) as the rightful Nawab of the Carnatic against Muhammad Anwaruddin, who was supported by the British. ",
            "keyString": "611233s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The two states which had non Congress Ministries in 1937 were",
            "optionA": "  Bengal and Punjab ",
            "optionB": "  Punjab and NWFP ",
            "optionC": "  Madras and Central Provinces ",
            "optionD": "  Bihar and Uttar Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBengal and Punjab were the two states where Non-Congress Ministries established after elections. In Bengal Muslim league and Krishak Praja party made the government and In Punjab, government was made by the Unionist and Muslim league. ",
            "keyString": "611930s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Motilal presided over the Congress Session of 1919 held at",
            "optionA": "  Lahore ",
            "optionB": "  Amritsar ",
            "optionC": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionD": "  Bombay ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMotilal Nehru presided over the Amritsar session of INC in 1919 as well as the Kolkata session of 1928. Motilal Nehru was an eminent lawyer and is the founder patriarch of the Nehru-Gandhi family. ",
            "keyString": "612499s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Assertion (A): Provincial autonomy was introduced in the Government of India Act, 1935.\nReason (R): The Act itself made a clear-cut division of powers between the Centre and the Provinces",
            "optionA": "  Both A and R is true and R is the correct explanation of A ",
            "optionB": "  Both A and R is true but R is not a correct explanation of A ",
            "optionC": "  A is true but R is false ",
            "optionD": "  A is false but R is true ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tsome parts of the GOI Act 1935 came into force for example : the Federal Bank (The Reserve Bank of India) and the Federal Court were established in 1935 and 1937 respectively. The other parts of the Act, particularly provincial Autonomy, came into force on 1st April 1937. ",
            "keyString": "707651s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A resolution declaring 'Purna Swaraj' was passed in the Congress Session held at",
            "optionA": "  Lahore ",
            "optionB": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionC": "  Gaya ",
            "optionD": "  Haripura ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the Lahore session of December 1929, Congress passed the Poorna Swaraj resolution. It was the same session in which Jawaharlal Nehru was elected as president of the Congress. ",
            "keyString": "708281s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following leader made the famous 'Objectives Resolution', in the Constituent Assembly?",
            "optionA": "  Vallabhbhai Patel ",
            "optionB": "  ",
            "optionC": " Rajagopalachari ",
            "optionD": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAn 'Objective Resolution' was moved by Jawaharlal Nehru in the assembly, laying down the underlying principles of the constitution. ",
            "keyString": "708880s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following European Colonisers did not have a settlement on the Eastern Coast of India ?",
            "optionA": "  French ",
            "optionB": "  Portuguese ",
            "optionC": "  Dutch ",
            "optionD": "  Danish ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDanish was the one who had not any settlement on the eastern coast of India whereas French settlement in Pondicherry, Portugese have Goa and Dutch in Kochi. ",
            "keyString": "710449s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "India is in favour of __________ in the economic field",
            "optionA": "  Public Sector ",
            "optionB": "  Private Sector ",
            "optionC": "  Mixed Economy ",
            "optionD": "  Capitalistic Economy ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn a mixed economy, private and public sectors go side by side. The government directs economic activity in some socially important areas of the economy, the rest being left to the price mechanism to operate. Before Independence, Indian economy was a 'laissez faire' economy. ",
            "keyString": "711331s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who had conceived and founded the Ramakrishna Mission?",
            "optionA": "  Swami Muktananda ",
            "optionB": "  Annie Besant ",
            "optionC": "  CR Das ",
            "optionD": "  Swami Vivekananda ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVivekananda went on lecture tours and held private discourses on Hinduism and spirituality. He also founded the first Vedanta Society in the United States at New York. He returned to India in 1897 and founded the Ramakrishna Mission on 1 May 1897. ",
            "keyString": "851468s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "As per Wavell's Plan the external affairs would be under the charge of __________",
            "optionA": "  Viceroy ",
            "optionB": "  Parliament ",
            "optionC": "  An Indian Member of the Executive Council ",
            "optionD": "  Secretary of State ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per Wavell's Plan the external affairs would be under the charge of an Indian member of the Executive Council. ",
            "keyString": "851533s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sati was declared a punishable offence in__________",
            "optionA": "  1727 ",
            "optionB": "  1729 ",
            "optionC": "  1829 ",
            "optionD": "  1834 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBentinck when he passed the Sati Regulation Act in 1829. The practice of Sati was declared illegal and punishable by criminal courts. ",
            "keyString": "851552s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Shimla Conference which was convened as per Wavell's Plan ended in failure because of the stiff opposition of",
            "optionA": "  Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionC": "  Jinnah ",
            "optionD": "  Rajaji ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Shimla Conference which was convened as per Wavell's Plan ended in failure because of the stiff opposition of Jinnah. ",
            "keyString": "851568s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The High Commissioner for India in the United Kingdom must be appointed by __________",
            "optionA": "  Secretary of State for India ",
            "optionB": "  The Government of India ",
            "optionC": "  Parliament of England ",
            "optionD": "  By Indian National Congress ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe High Commissioner for India in the United Kingdom must be appointed by The Government of India. ",
            "keyString": "851583s9m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Siraj-ud-Daulah renamed which city as Alinagar?",
            "optionA": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionB": "  Agra ",
            "optionC": "  Ferozpur ",
            "optionD": "  Fatehpur ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSiraj-ud-Daulah renamed Calcutta as Alinagar, the treaty of Alinagar was signed on 9 feb 1757 between Robert Clive and Siraj-ud-Daulah. ",
            "keyString": "12744s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is also known by the name of 'Tiger of  'Mysore'?",
            "optionA": "  Haidar Ali ",
            "optionB": "  Tipu Sultan ",
            "optionC": "  Yaduraya Wodeyar ",
            "optionD": "  Krishna Devaraya ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTipu Sultan Successor of Hyder Ali (Ruler of Mysore), is known as the \"Tiger of Mysore\" and also known as \"CITIZEN TIPU\". He was a good administrator and launched many reforms related to Revenue andadministration. He founded the \"Jacobian Club\" in Mysore. He died in fourth Anglo Mysore war. ",
            "keyString": "12781s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "On June 14, 1927 __________consecrated a mirror - with the message \"Om shanti\" written on the surface - in a temple in Kalavankode",
            "optionA": "  Rajaram Mohan Roy ",
            "optionB": "  T. K. Madhavan ",
            "optionC": "  Sree Narayana Guru ",
            "optionD": "  Govindan Vaidyar ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn June 14, 1927 Sree Narayana Guru consecrated a mirror - with the message \"Om shanti\" written on the surface - in a temple in Kalavankode. ",
            "keyString": "12795s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The immediate cause of split in the INC at its Surat Session was",
            "optionA": "  election of the President of the INC ",
            "optionB": "  expulsion of Tilak from the INC ",
            "optionC": "  demand of Swaraj as the goal of the INC ",
            "optionD": "  resolutions on Swaraj, Swadeshi, Boycott and National Education ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Congress split in 1907 - The Moderates were opposed to the use of boycott. They felt that it involved the use of force. The immediate cause of split In the INC at its Surat Session was election of the President of the INC. ",
            "keyString": "12807s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following treaty ended the First Carnatic War?",
            "optionA": "  Salbai ",
            "optionB": "  Bassein ",
            "optionC": "  Aix-Ia-Chapelle ",
            "optionD": "  Paris ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFirst Carnatic War 1746-48 was a part of the War of the Austrian Succession that was fought between the Kingdom of Prussia, Spain, France, and Bavaria, Sweden etc. on one side and Habsburg Monarchy, England, Dutch Republic, Russia on the other side. This war finally ended with the Treaty of Aix-la-Chapelle (1748). ",
            "keyString": "12819s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who proclaimed: It is years since I left castes and religions. Yet some people think that I belong to their caste. That is not correct. I do not belong to any particular caste or religion",
            "optionA": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  T. K. Madhavan ",
            "optionC": "  Rajaram Mohan Roy ",
            "optionD": "  Sree Narayana Guru ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSree Narayana Guru proclaimed: It is years since I left castes and religions. Yet some people think that I belong to their caste. That is not correct. I do not belong to any particular caste or religion. ",
            "keyString": "106332s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During the Anglo-French struggle in the Carnatic, the French were finally defeated by the English in the battle of",
            "optionA": "  Trichinopoly ",
            "optionB": "  Arcot ",
            "optionC": "  Wandiwash ",
            "optionD": "  Pondicherry ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBattle of Wandiwash, (Jan. 22, 1760), in the history of India, a confrontation between the French, under the comte de Lally, and the British, under Sir Eyre Coote. It was the decisive battle in the Anglo-French struggle in southern India during the Seven Years War (1756\u201363). During the Anglo-French struggle in the Carnatic, the French were finally defeated by the English in the battle of Wandiwash. ",
            "keyString": "107336s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following provinces the Congress Ministry was not formed in June 1937?",
            "optionA": "  United Provinces ",
            "optionB": "  Central Provinces ",
            "optionC": "  Madras ",
            "optionD": "  Assam ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn Assam provinces the Congress Ministry was not formed in June 1937. ",
            "keyString": "107887s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When the Governor-General was away from Bengal a Vice President appointed by __________ would act for him",
            "optionA": "  Crown ",
            "optionB": "  Parliament ",
            "optionC": "  Board of Control ",
            "optionD": "  Governor-General ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhen the Governor-General was away from Bengal a Vice President appointed by Governor-General would act for him. ",
            "keyString": "108482s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Theosophical Society is an organization formed in __________ to advance the spiritual principles and search for Truth known as Theosophy",
            "optionA": "  1842 ",
            "optionB": "  1843 ",
            "optionC": "  1845 ",
            "optionD": "  1875 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Theosophical Society was an organization formed in 1875 by Helena Blavatsky to advance Theosophy. The original organization, after splits and realignments, currently has several successors. ",
            "keyString": "263992s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Rama Krishna Mission was established by",
            "optionA": "  Vivekananda ",
            "optionB": "  Rama Krishna ",
            "optionC": "  M. G. Ranade ",
            "optionD": "  Keshab Chandra Sen ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Rama Krishna Misson was established by Swami Vivekananda on 1st May 1897 at Belur Math near Kolkata(West Bengal). The Motto of Rama Krishna Mission is \"For one's own Solution, and for the Welfare of the World\". ",
            "keyString": "264529s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Tokyo Conference which passed a resolution to form an Indian National Army or Azad Hind Fauj was a conference of",
            "optionA": "  different associations of Indians living in South-East Asia ",
            "optionB": "  Indians living in Tokyo ",
            "optionC": "  Indian prisoners of war in Japanese custody ",
            "optionD": "  Indian revolutionaries living outside India ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Tokyo Conference which passed a resolution to form an Indian National Army or Azad Hind Fauj was a conference of different associations of Indians living in South-East Asia. ",
            "keyString": "265024s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "M. A. Jinnah, in his early political life",
            "optionA": "  Supported two nation theory ",
            "optionB": "  Initiated Hindu-Muslim unity ",
            "optionC": "  Imagined Pakistan as an independent State ",
            "optionD": "  Was a communalist ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMohammad Ali Jinha in his early life was a symbol of Hindu - Muslim unity and also in favour of Gandhiji's policies for swaraj. ",
            "keyString": "265493s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who He said, \"I accept as Dharma whatever is in full conformity with impartial justice, truthfulness and the like; that which is not opposed to the teachings of God as embodied in the Vedas. Whatever is not free from partiality and is unjust, partaking of untruth and the like, and opposed to the teachings of God as embodied in the Vedas\u2014that I hold as adharma\".He also said \"He, who after careful thinking, is ever ready to accept truth and reject falsehood; who counts the happiness of others as he does that of his own self, him I call just\"",
            "optionA": "  Baba Ram Singh ",
            "optionB": "  Ranjit Singh ",
            "optionC": "  Lal Singh ",
            "optionD": "  Dayananda Saraswathi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDayanand Saraswati was founder of Arya Samaj Social & Religious Reformist (In the second half of Nineteenth Century during British Rule some Social; some Religious; some Political Movements were started in India. It is clear indication something was cooking.These \u2013 in Political it saw formation of Indian National Congress ultimately forced British to LEAVE the country; In Religious \u2013 it saw formation of Brahmo Samaj; Radhasoami; Arya Samaj and a NEW GOD SAIN BABA. It also saw Raja Ram Mohan Roy; Vivekanand; Soami ji Maharaj; Dayanand the social and religious reformists playing an important role \u2013 R.P.Sinha). ",
            "keyString": "266085s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first Swarajist Conference was held at",
            "optionA": "  Ahmedabad ",
            "optionB": "  Allahabad ",
            "optionC": "  Madras ",
            "optionD": "  Bardoli ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first Swarajist Conference was held at Allahabad. ",
            "keyString": "487721s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Swarajist Party was organised by",
            "optionA": "  Motilal Nehru ",
            "optionB": "  Subash Chandra Bose ",
            "optionC": "  Annie Besant ",
            "optionD": "  Gokhale ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSwaraj Party, Indian political party established in late 1922\u2013early 1923 by members of the Indian National Congress (Congress Party), notably Motilal Nehru, one of the most prominent lawyers in northern India (and the father of political leader Jawaharlal Nehru), and Chitta Ranjan Das, a nationalist politician from Bengal.",
            "keyString": "488228s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Deccan Riots of 1874-75 in Maharashtra were directed against",
            "optionA": "  Big landlords ",
            "optionB": "  Moneylenders ",
            "optionC": "  Revenue collectors ",
            "optionD": "  British opium planters ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn May and June 1875, peasants of Maharashtra in some parts of Pune, Satara and Ahmednagar districts revolted against increasing agrarian distress. The Deccan Riots of 1875 targeted conditions of debt peonage (kamiuti) to moneylenders. ",
            "keyString": "488752s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who led the armed raid on the government armoury at Chittagong in 1930?",
            "optionA": "  Chandra Shekhar Azad ",
            "optionB": "  Bhagat Singh ",
            "optionC": "  Surya Sen ",
            "optionD": "  Sukhdev ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChittagong armoury raid held on 18 April,1930 to raid the armoury of police and auxiliary forces form the Chittagong armoury in Bengal which was led by Surya Sen. ",
            "keyString": "489235s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following pairs is not correctly matched?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Dalhousie  -  Doctrine of Lapse ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Minto  -  India Councils Act, 1909 ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Wellesley  -  Subsidiary Alliance ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Curzon   -  Vernacular Press Act, 1878 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVernacular Press Act, 1878 was proposed by Lord Lytton to prevent the Vernacular Press from expressing criticism of British Policies. ",
            "keyString": "489681s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Wahabis operated from",
            "optionA": "  Hindukush ",
            "optionB": "  Khyber Pass ",
            "optionC": "  Western Ghat ",
            "optionD": "  Palghat ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Wahabis operated from Hindukush. ",
            "keyString": "649977s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who of the following attended all the Three Round Table Conferences?",
            "optionA": "  ",
            "optionB": " R. Ambedkar ",
            "optionC": "  M. M. Malavia ",
            "optionD": "  Vallabhbhai Patel ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThree Round table Conferences were held in London in 1930,1931,1932. Dr.B.R Ambedkar attended allthree Round table conference. Gandhi Ji attended second round table Conference. ",
            "keyString": "651281s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who declared \"Swaraj is my birth right and I shall have it\"?",
            "optionA": "  Gopal Krishna Gokhale ",
            "optionB": "  Bal Gangadhara Tilak ",
            "optionC": "  Lala Lajpat Rai ",
            "optionD": "  K.T Telang ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBal Gangadhar Tilak is also known as Lokmanya Tilak. He was against the discriminative attitude of British government. He along with Annie Besant started Home Rule Movement across the country, seeking self government in India.",
            "keyString": "652509s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said \"The Simmon Commission Report should be thrown on a heap of rubbish\"?",
            "optionA": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  Shivaswami Iyer ",
            "optionC": "  Mohammad Ali Jinnah ",
            "optionD": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShivaswami Iyer examined the Simon commission Report and said that this report should be thrown on a heap of rubbish. ",
            "keyString": "654030s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mahatma Gandhi compared Pherozeshah Mehta with the Himalayas, Tilak with the Ocean and Gokhale with",
            "optionA": "  the Sky ",
            "optionB": "  the Ganges ",
            "optionC": "  the Gangotri ",
            "optionD": "  the Mansarovar Lake ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahatma Gandhi compared Pherozeshah Mehta with the Himalayas, Tilak with the Ocean and Gokhale with the Ganges. ",
            "keyString": "655278s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Mohamedan Association was founded in __________in 1856",
            "optionA": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionB": "  Adayar ",
            "optionC": "  Madras ",
            "optionD": "  Maharashtra ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Muslims of Bengal who were largely raiyats and peasants had little interest and connection with this Association. So in order to protect their own interest the Mohamedan Association was founded in Calcutta in 1856. ",
            "keyString": "757825s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first weekly paper published by the INC (in 1889) was",
            "optionA": "  Young India ",
            "optionB": "  India ",
            "optionC": "  Indian People ",
            "optionD": "  Voice India ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1889, the committee started to publish India, a monthly journal summarising Indian affairs and news for the British press and politicians. ",
            "keyString": "758123s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In May__________, S. Ramaswami Mudaliar and P. Anandacharlu established the Madras Mahajana Sabha",
            "optionA": "  1783 ",
            "optionB": "  1784 ",
            "optionC": "  1872 ",
            "optionD": "  1884 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMadras Mahajana Sabha was established by S. Ramaswami Mudaliar and P. Anandacharlu in 1884. Its first conference was held on December 29, 1884. ",
            "keyString": "758330s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Act of 1833 concentrated the legislative powers in the hands of",
            "optionA": "  Parliament ",
            "optionB": "  Governor-General in Council ",
            "optionC": "  Board of Control ",
            "optionD": "  Crown ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tthe act of 1833 concentrated the legislative powers in the hands of Governor-General in Council. ",
            "keyString": "758516s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "After 1893, when complete ban was imposed on all commercial activities of the Company. India was left open to exploitation by",
            "optionA": "  British officers in India ",
            "optionB": "  Planters ",
            "optionC": "  British mercantile industrial capitalist class ",
            "optionD": "  Zamindars and big landlords ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter 1893, when complete ban was imposed on all commercial activities of the Company. India was left open to exploitation by British mercantile industrial capitalist class. ",
            "keyString": "758693s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mahatma Gandhi spent a year of complete silence in 1926 to",
            "optionA": "  consolidate Khadi programme ",
            "optionB": "  work for harijan welfare ",
            "optionC": "  cl do penance for Chauri-Chaura violence ",
            "optionD": "  write his autobiography ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahatma Gandhi spent a year of complete silence in 1926 to work for harijan welfare. ",
            "keyString": "857868s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was the office of District Collector created?",
            "optionA": "  1786 ",
            "optionB": "  1772 ",
            "optionC": "  1771 ",
            "optionD": "  1773 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRevenue Collection system was the major problem for east India company in his initial phase Governor General of Bengal Warren Hastings established the office of District collector in 1772 for collection of revenue. ",
            "keyString": "858089s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who declared as his ultimate aim the wiping of every tear from every eye?",
            "optionA": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionB": "  Gandhiji ",
            "optionC": "  Bal Gangadhar ",
            "optionD": "  Sardar Patel ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJawaharlal Nahru in his speech 'Freedom at midnight\"said that the ambition of the greatest men of our generation has to be to wipe every tear from every eye. ",
            "keyString": "858328s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Directive Principal bears the direct impact of Gandhi's moral philosophy?",
            "optionA": "  Equal pay for equal work ",
            "optionB": "  Provision of free legal aid and advice ",
            "optionC": "  Prohibition of the slaughter of cows ",
            "optionD": "  Protection of the mounments of historical\nimportance ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGandhi's moral Philosophy was of socialism, non-violence and welfare state. The impact of his Philosophy can be seen in various DPSP & including article 48 which prohibits the slaughter of cows. ",
            "keyString": "858503s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following from the first cabinet of indepenent India was responsible of mass religious conversion?",
            "optionA": "  Dr. S. P. Mukherjee ",
            "optionB": "  Dr. John Mathai ",
            "optionC": "  Sardar Baldeve Singh ",
            "optionD": "  Dr. ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDr. B. R. Ambedkar argued that converting into Buddhism was the only way for the untouchables to gain equality. In 1956, he started the Dalit Buddhist Movement. ",
            "keyString": "858670s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "'Dyarchy' was introduced in the Government of India Act of",
            "optionA": "  1909 ",
            "optionB": "  1919 ",
            "optionC": "  1935 ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDyarchy, also spelled diarchy, system of double government introduced by the Government of India Act (1919) for the provinces of British India. ",
            "keyString": "943611s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The problem that exercised and evoked the reformists in the 19th century to the greatest extent related to",
            "optionA": "  Education ",
            "optionB": "  Caste restrictions ",
            "optionC": "  Religious revivalism ",
            "optionD": "  Women's issues ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe problem that exercised and evoked the reformists in the 19th century to the greatest extent related to Women's issues. ",
            "keyString": "944661s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The 'Hero of Plassey' was",
            "optionA": "  Warren Hastings ",
            "optionB": "  Dupleix ",
            "optionC": "  Clive ",
            "optionD": "  Shuja-ud-Daulah ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe 'Hero of Plassey' was Clive. Clive decided that the best way to secure the company's interests in Bengal was to replace Siraj with a new and more pliant nawab. ",
            "keyString": "945119s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The hero of the Kakori 'Dacoity' case was",
            "optionA": "  Ramprasad Bismil ",
            "optionB": "  Bhagat Singh ",
            "optionC": "  Batukeshwar Datta ",
            "optionD": "  Barkatulla ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKakori Dacoity was a train robbery conceived by Ram Prasad Bismil near Lucknow. It was organised under the banner Hindustan Republican Association. ",
            "keyString": "945357s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who preached the idea of Home Rule through his two news papers - the Kesari and the Maratha?",
            "optionA": "  Gokhale ",
            "optionB": "  Annie Besant ",
            "optionC": "  Tilak ",
            "optionD": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKesari is a Marathi newspaper which was founded in 1881 by Lokmanya Bal Gangadhar Tilak. ",
            "keyString": "945577s10m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was given the title of \"The Ambassador of Hindu - Muslim Unity\" for being the architect and mastermind of the historic Lucknow Pact?",
            "optionA": "  Sir Sayyid Ahmad Khan ",
            "optionB": "  Fazl-ul-Haq ",
            "optionC": "  Sayyid Mohammad Sharfuddin Quadri ",
            "optionD": "  Muhammad Ali Jinnah ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMuhammad Ali Jinnah was given the title Ambassador of Hindu Muslim unity. He was the mastermind of historic Lucknow pact (1916). ",
            "keyString": "66596s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main founder (s) of the Swaraj Party was/were",
            "optionA": "  CR Das ",
            "optionB": "  Motilal Nehru ",
            "optionC": "  Madan Mohan Malaviya ",
            "optionD": "  Only A and B above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSwaraj Party, Indian political party established in late 1922\u2013early 1923 by members of the Indian National Congress (Congress Party), notably Motilal Nehru, one of the most prominent lawyers in northern India (and the father of political leader Jawaharlal Nehru), and Chitta Ranjan Das, a nationalist politician from Bengal.",
            "keyString": "66868s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "As per Pitt's India Act the Committee of Secrecy would consist of three members of __________",
            "optionA": "  The Board of Control ",
            "optionB": "  The Court of Directors ",
            "optionC": "  The House of Commons ",
            "optionD": "  The House of Lords ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA committee of secrecy of not more than three members was appointed. The other members of the court of Directors could thus be ignored in important matters. ",
            "keyString": "67069s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who of the following has the distinction of having Authored the National Anthems of two countries of the world?",
            "optionA": "  TS Eliot ",
            "optionB": "  WB Yeats ",
            "optionC": "  Rabindranath Tagore ",
            "optionD": "  Mohammad Iqbal ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRavindranath Tagore had written National anthem of two countries and those are India and Bangladesh. ",
            "keyString": "67232s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who had first sought the legalisation of widow remarriage in India?",
            "optionA": "  Raja Ram Mohan Roy ",
            "optionB": "  Badruddin Tyabji ",
            "optionC": "  Ishwar Chandra Vidayasagar ",
            "optionD": "  Swami Dayanand Saraswati ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIshwar Chandra Vidayasagar ",
            "keyString": "67389s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Marathas were defeated in Panipat because",
            "optionA": "  The Marathas did not fight bravely ",
            "optionB": "  The Marathas were not equal to Afghans in\nstrength ",
            "optionC": "  The Maratha army was short of food supplies ",
            "optionD": "  The Marathas were considered alien by the\nlocal population ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThird battle of Panipat was fought between the Marathas and Ahmad Shah Abdali (The ruler of Afghanistan) on 14th Jan 1761, due to lack of strength as compared to Afghans, Marathas were defeated. ",
            "keyString": "193760s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following was not a common social reform attempted by all the Hindu social reformers of the 19th century",
            "optionA": "  emancipation of women ",
            "optionB": "  monogamy ",
            "optionC": "  female education ",
            "optionD": "  untouchability ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tuntouchability was not a common social reform attempted by all the Hindu social reformers of the 19th century. ",
            "keyString": "194604s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Government of India Act gave separate representation to the Muslims?",
            "optionA": "  Act of 1909 ",
            "optionB": "  Act of 1919 ",
            "optionC": "  Act of 1935 ",
            "optionD": "  Act of 1947 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGovernment of India Act of 1909 gave separate representation to the Muslims. ",
            "keyString": "194791s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Muslim League withdrew its acceptance of the Cabinet  Mission Plan and decided to resort to Direct Action Day on",
            "optionA": "  August 16, 1946 ",
            "optionB": "  September 2, 1946 ",
            "optionC": "  October 15, 1946 ",
            "optionD": "  July 29, 1946 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDirect Action Day (16 August 1946), also known as the Great Calcutta Killings, was a day of widespread communal rioting between Muslims and Hindus in the city of Calcutta (now known as Kolkata) in the Bengal province of British India. The day also marked the start of what is known as The Week of the Long Knives. ",
            "keyString": "195449s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following event compel the Rabindranath Tagore to renounce his knighthood?",
            "optionA": "  To protest against the Jallianwalla Bagh incident ",
            "optionB": "  To protest against lathi charge on Lala Lajpat Rai that caused his death ",
            "optionC": "  To express solidarity with the leaders of Non-Cooperation Movement ",
            "optionD": "  To express solidarity with the protestors against the arrival of Simon Commission ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTagore felt compelled to reenter the political sphere when the government's repression reached an extreme from under the martial law in Punjab. Tagore tried to mobilize political leaders to protest against the atrocities in Punjab on particular the Jallianwala Bagh Massacare. ",
            "keyString": "195665s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Jyotiba Phule, popularly known as Baba Phule, was a social reformer in Maharashtra. Which of the following is not true about him",
            "optionA": "  He was the first to raise his voice against Brahmans in Maharashtra in the 1870s ",
            "optionB": "  Phule through his book Ghulamagiri (1872) and his organization Satyashodhak Mandal, proclaimed the need to save the lower castes from the hypocritical Brahmans and their scriptures ",
            "optionC": "  His Satyashodhak Mandal contained both an elite based conservative trend and a genuine mass-based radicalism ",
            "optionD": "  The urban educated Marathas were his most ardent followers ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJyotirao \u2018Jyotiba\u2019 Govindrao Phule was a prominent social reformer and thinker of the nineteenth century India. He led the movement against the prevailing caste-restrictions in India. He revolted against the domination of the Brahmins and struggled for the rights of peasants and other low-caste people. Mahatma Jyotiba Phule was also a pioneer for women education in India and fought for education of girls throughout his life. He is believed to be the first Hindu to start an orphanage for the unfortunate children. The urban educated Marathas were his most ardent followers is not true ant him. ",
            "keyString": "384364s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Nehru Report of 1928 with proposals for constitutional reforms had been prepared by",
            "optionA": "  Motilal Nehru ",
            "optionB": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionC": "  Kamla Nehru ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Nehru Report of 28-30 August, 1928 was a memorandum outlining a proposed new dominion status constitution for India. It was prepared by a committee of the All Parties Conference chaired by Motilal Nehru with his son Jawaharlal Nehru acting as secretary. ",
            "keyString": "384576s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Annie Besant joined The Theosophical Society on 21 May __________",
            "optionA": "  1867 ",
            "optionB": "  1878 ",
            "optionC": "  1879 ",
            "optionD": "  1889 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnnie Besant joined the Theosophical Society in May 1889 and became Blavatsky's devoted pupil and helper. She became a prominent worker in the Society and was elected President which position she held till her death on 21 September 1933. She first came to India on 16 November 1893. ",
            "keyString": "384759s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1875, Sir Syed founded the Madarsatul Uloom in __________",
            "optionA": "  Delhi ",
            "optionB": "  Aligarh ",
            "optionC": "  Bengal ",
            "optionD": "  Agra ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1875, Sir Syed founded the Madarsatul Uloom in Aligarh and patterned the MAO College after Oxford and Cambridge universities that he went on a trip to London. His objective was to build a college in line with the British education system but without compromising its Islamic values. ",
            "keyString": "384922s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When King George-V and Queen of India visited India, a magnificent Durbar was held at",
            "optionA": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionB": "  Delhi ",
            "optionC": "  Bombay ",
            "optionD": "  Madras ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe 1911 Durbar was the only one that a sovereign, George V, attended. The term was derived from the common Mughal term durbar. On 22 March 1911, a royal proclamation announced that the Durbar would be held in December to commemorate the coronation in Britain a few months earlier of George V and Mary of Teck and allow their proclamation as Emperor and Empress of India.",
            "keyString": "385082s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The __________ were the first Europeans to start a Joint stock company trade with India?",
            "optionA": "  French ",
            "optionB": "  Portuguese ",
            "optionC": "  Danish ",
            "optionD": "  Dutch ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Dutch were the first Europeans to start a Joint stock company trade with India. ",
            "keyString": "471184s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Nanu moved to his hermitage deep inside the hilly forests of__________, where he led an austere life immersed in meditative thought and yoga and subjected himself to extreme sustenance rituals",
            "optionA": "  Silanka ",
            "optionB": "  Maruthwamala ",
            "optionC": "  Karunagapally ",
            "optionD": "  Kayamkulam ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNanu moved to his hermitage deep inside the hilly forests of Maruthwamala, where he led an austere life immersed in meditative thought and yoga and subjected himself to extreme sustenance rituals ",
            "keyString": "471730s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was Jagat Seth's claim to fame in Bengal?",
            "optionA": "  Diwan of Siraj-ud-Daulah ",
            "optionB": "  Leading popular poet ",
            "optionC": "  Biggest banker in Bengal ",
            "optionD": "  Commander of the Nawab's troops ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJagat Seth meaning the \u201cBanker of the World\u201d, was a title conferred on his nephew Fateh Chand, a very rich banker in Bengal in the first half of the 18th century. ",
            "keyString": "471961s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following songs was so dear to Mahatma Gandhi's heart, that he wrote: 'That one song is enough to sustain me, even if I were to forget the 'Bhagavad Gita'",
            "optionA": "  Hare Ram ",
            "optionB": "  Raghupati Raghav Raja Ram ",
            "optionC": "  Vaishnava Jana To Tene Kahiye ",
            "optionD": "  Ishwar Allah Tero Nam ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVaishnava Jana To Tene Kahiye songs was so dear to Mahatma Gandhi's heart, that he wrote: 'That one song is enough to sustain me, even if I were to forget the 'Bhagavad Gita'. ",
            "keyString": "472149s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indians were allowed to frame their Constitution by",
            "optionA": "  The Council Act of 1909 ",
            "optionB": "  Montford Reforms ",
            "optionC": "  August Offer ",
            "optionD": "  The Government of India Act of 1935 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe August Offer was a proposal made by the British government in 1940 promising the expansion of the Executive Council of the Viceroy of India to include more Indians, the establishment of an advisory war council, giving full weight to minority opinion, and the recognition of Indians right to frame their own constitution. ",
            "keyString": "472340s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is one of the causes for the passing of the Act of 1773?",
            "optionA": "  Failure of Double Government ",
            "optionB": "  Success of Double Government ",
            "optionC": "  Agitation in India ",
            "optionD": "  Desire of the Indian Merchants ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Regulating Act 1773 was an Act of the Parliament of Great Britain intended to overhaul the management of the East India Company's rule in India. The Act did not prove to be a long-term solution to concerns over the Company's affairs; Pitt's India Act was therefore subsequently enacted in 1784 as a more radical reform. ",
            "keyString": "547982s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Alipore conspiracy case was launched against the revolutionary activities of",
            "optionA": "  Anusilan Samiti ",
            "optionB": "  Abhinava Bharat ",
            "optionC": "  Abhinava Bharat Society ",
            "optionD": "  Ghadar Party of India ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe revolutionary philosophies and movement made its presence felt during the 1905 Partition of Bengal. Arguably, the initial steps to organise the revolutionaries were taken by Aurobindo Ghosh, his brother Barin Ghosh, Bhupendranath Datta, Lal Bal Pal and Subodh Chandra Mullick when they formed the Jugantar party in April 1906. Jugantar was created as an inner circle of the Anushilan Samiti, which was already present in Bengal mainly as a fitness club. ",
            "keyString": "548202s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The English established their first factory in India at",
            "optionA": "  Bombay ",
            "optionB": "  Surat ",
            "optionC": "  Sutanati ",
            "optionD": "  Madras ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe East India Company arrived first at Surat, India in 1608 in the ship Hector commanded by William Hawkins and within a few years had established a permanent factory there.",
            "keyString": "548405s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is regarded as 'the Mother of the Indian Revolution'?",
            "optionA": "  Rani Lakshmi Bai ",
            "optionB": "  Sarojini Naidu ",
            "optionC": "  Madam Bhikaji Cama ",
            "optionD": "  Priti Lata Waddedar ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBhikaiji Rustom Cama,or Madam Cama was born on 24 September 1861 in Bombay. She was an outstanding lady of great courage, fearlessness, integrity, perseverance and passion for freedom and is considered as the mother of Indian revolution because of her contributions to Indian freedom struggle. ",
            "keyString": "548567s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the first to raise the slogan 'Inquilab zindabad'?",
            "optionA": "  Bhagat Singh ",
            "optionB": "  M Kelappan ",
            "optionC": "  Veer Savarkar ",
            "optionD": "  Shankaran Nair ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe famous slogan Inquilab Zindabad was given by Hasrat Mohani. This famous slogan inspired the activities of the Hindustan Socialist Republican Association particularly Ashfaqulla Khan, Bhagat Singh and Chandrashekhar Azad. ",
            "keyString": "548760s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Atmopadesa Satakam is the work of __________",
            "optionA": "  Dr. Palpu ",
            "optionB": "  Chattambi Swamikal ",
            "optionC": "  ",
            "optionD": " Kesavan ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t\"Atmopadesa Satakam\" is a Malayalam spiritual work by Narayana Guru in the form of a poem. ",
            "keyString": "664883s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Nirvruthi Panchakam was written by __________",
            "optionA": "  ",
            "optionB": "Kesavan ",
            "optionC": "  Chattambi Swamikal ",
            "optionD": "  Brahmananda Sivayogi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNirvruthi Panchakam was written by Sree Narayana Guru. ",
            "keyString": "665178s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Zamindari Association was the political association of modern India",
            "optionA": "  First ",
            "optionB": "  Second ",
            "optionC": "  Third ",
            "optionD": "  Fourth ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Zamindari Association, which was later renamed Landholders' Society, was established in 12 November 1837 by Dwarkanath Tagore, Prasanna Kumar Tagore, Radhakanta Deb, Ramkamal Sen and Bhabani Charan Mitra. It has been described as \u201cthe first organisation of Bengal with distinct political object.\u201d ",
            "keyString": "665433s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the Nawab of Bengal during \"Battle of Plassey\"?",
            "optionA": "  Mir Jafar ",
            "optionB": "  Mir Qasim ",
            "optionC": "  Sirajudduala ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Battle of Plassey was fought in 1757 between the Nawab of Bengal Siraj-ud-daulah and east India company. The Victory of the British forces in this battle paved the way the British rule in India. ",
            "keyString": "665699s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Lokmanya Bal Gangadhar Tilak hailed form",
            "optionA": "  Bengal ",
            "optionB": "  Kashmir ",
            "optionC": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionD": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLokmanya Bal Gangadhar Tilak hailed fromMaharashtra. ",
            "keyString": "665911s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is the founder of the concept \"Sarvodaya\"?",
            "optionA": "  Vinobha Bhave ",
            "optionB": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionC": "  Jai Prakash Narayan ",
            "optionD": "  K. G. Mushroowala ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tM.K Gandhi Translated John Ruskin's work on political economy - \"Unto the Last\" under the title of 'Sarvodaya' which means 'Universal upliftment'. ",
            "keyString": "790965s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following is known as the \"Father of the Indian Renaissance\"?",
            "optionA": "  Raja Ram Mohan Roy ",
            "optionB": "  Rabindra Nath Tagore ",
            "optionC": "  Swami Dayanand Saraswati ",
            "optionD": "  Swami Vivekanand ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRaja Ram Mohan Roy was known as the 'Father of the Indian Renaissance'. ",
            "keyString": "791919s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Battle of Buxar was fought between the combined armies (of the Nawab of Awadh, the Mughal Emperor and Mir Qasim) and the",
            "optionA": "  French ",
            "optionB": "  Dutch ",
            "optionC": "  Portuguese ",
            "optionD": "  English ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Battle of Buxar was fought on 22 October 1764, during the Bengal War was between the forces under the command of the British East India Company, led by Hector Munro, and the combined armies of Mir Qasim, Nawab of Bengal till 1763; the Nawab of Awadh; and the Mughal Emperor Shah Alam II. ",
            "keyString": "792915s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1934 Mahatma Gandhi withdrew from active politics and even resigned his membership of the Congress because",
            "optionA": "  of the failure of the Civil Disobedience Movement ",
            "optionB": "  the political climate of India was unsuitable for any political movement ",
            "optionC": "  he wanted to devote himself fully to constructive programme and Harijan welfare ",
            "optionD": "  of his opposition to the desire of congressmen to enter legislatures under the Government of India Act of 1935 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1934 Mahatma Gandhi withdrew from active politics and even resigned his membership of the Congress because he wanted to devote himself fully to constructive programme and Harijan welfare. ",
            "keyString": "793151s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A new phase began in the Guru's life in 1904. He decided to give up his wandering life and settle down in a place to continue his Sadhana (spiritual practice). He chose__________, twenty miles north of Thiruvananthapuram",
            "optionA": "  Karunagapally ",
            "optionB": "  Sivagiri ",
            "optionC": "  Kayamkulam ",
            "optionD": "  Kannur ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA new phase began in the Guru's life in 1904. He decided to give up his wandering life and settle down in a place to continue his Sadhana (spiritual practice). He chose Sivagiri, twenty miles north of Thiruvananthapuram. Goddess 'Amba' became his deity of worship. ",
            "keyString": "793350s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following leader said that the Act of 1935 provided 'a machine with strong brakes but no engine'?",
            "optionA": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionB": "  Rajendra Prasad ",
            "optionC": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionD": "  Vallabhbhai Patel ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJawaharlal Nehru said that the Act of 1935 provided 'a machine with strong brakes but no engine'. ",
            "keyString": "921473s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following according to Mahatma Gandhi, is the strongest force in the world?",
            "optionA": "  Non-violence of the brave ",
            "optionB": "  Non-violence of the weak ",
            "optionC": "  Non-violence of the coward ",
            "optionD": "  Non-violence of the down-trodden ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahatma Gandhi was extreme supporter of non-violence or \"Ahimsa\". Movements lead by him were based on the principles of \"Satyagrah\". According to him, non-violence of brave is the strongest force in the world. ",
            "keyString": "922238s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was the first train steamed off in India?",
            "optionA": "  1848 ",
            "optionB": "  1853 ",
            "optionC": "  1875 ",
            "optionD": "  1880 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn April 16,1853, the first passengers train steamed between Bori Bunder in Bombay and Thane. ",
            "keyString": "922695s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Of the following, which country's constitution did not influence the fathers of Indian Constitution? ",
            "optionA": "  The USA ",
            "optionB": "  The USSR ",
            "optionC": "  Canada ",
            "optionD": "  Ireland ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Constitution of The USSR did not influence the fathers of Indian Constitution. ",
            "keyString": "923060s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was Lala Lajpat Rai demonstrating against when he succumbed to police brutality?",
            "optionA": "  Rowlatta Act ",
            "optionB": "  Minto-Morley Reforms ",
            "optionC": "  Simon Commission ",
            "optionD": "  Pitts India Act ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSimon commission was appointed to report the working of the existing government, it was a six Members commission under the chairmanship of John Simon and it did not consist a single Indian member. Hence, Congress decided to boycott the commission. Lala ji who led the movement in Lahore was Severely injured by lathi charge. ",
            "keyString": "923384s11m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who founded as Mohammedan Anglo Oriental College (MAOC) at Aligarh in 1875?",
            "optionA": "  Sir Saiyad Ahmed Khan ",
            "optionB": "  Mirza Mohammad ",
            "optionC": "  Maulana Qasim Nanotvi ",
            "optionD": "  Maulana Abdullah Ansari ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMuhammadan Anglo Oriental College was founded in 1875, initially as a primary school, with the intention of taking it to a college level institution, known as Muhammedan Anglo Oriental Collegiate School. Its given Urdu name was Madrasatul Uloom Musalmanan-e-Hind. It started operations on Queen Victoria's 56th birthday, 24 May 1875. Sir Saiyad Ahmed Khan found it. ",
            "keyString": "37596s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who founded the Central Hindu School and College in Banaras (now Varanasi)?",
            "optionA": "  Annie Besant ",
            "optionB": "  Dr. Bhagavan Das ",
            "optionC": "  Govinda Das ",
            "optionD": "  G. N. Chakravarti ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFounded by noted freedom-fighter Annie Besant in July 1898, with Dr. Arthur Richardson, a science graduate from England as the principal, and went on to become the nucleus of Banaras Hindu University, which was established in 1916. Asia's first Educational conference was held in the ground of the CHBS. ",
            "keyString": "37944s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In November 1881, Narendra went to meet __________who was staying at the Kali Temple in Dakshineshwar",
            "optionA": "  Sri Ramakrishna ",
            "optionB": "  Rashik Krishna Mallik ",
            "optionC": "  Dakhinaranjan Mukhopadhyay ",
            "optionD": "  Ramgopal Ghose ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOne day in November 1881, Narendra went to meet Sri Ramakrishna who was staying at the Kali Temple in Dakshineshwar. Apart from removing doubts from the mind of Narendra about the existence of God, Sri Ramakrishna won him over through his pure, unselfish love. ",
            "keyString": "38199s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the name of the English weekly edited by Mahatma Gandhi?",
            "optionA": "  Young India ",
            "optionB": "  Kesari ",
            "optionC": "  Bombay Chronicle ",
            "optionD": "  Resurgent India ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tYoung India was a weekly paper or journal in English published by Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi from 1919 to 1931. ",
            "keyString": "38636s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Rohelas were of __________ origin",
            "optionA": "  Turkish ",
            "optionB": "  Afghan ",
            "optionC": "  British ",
            "optionD": "  Chinese ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThey belonged to an Afghan Ghilzai tribe. It was first Afghan dynasty which ruled large part of the Indian subcontinent between 1290 and 1320. ",
            "keyString": "39228s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Congressmen who wanted to contest the elections under the Act of 1919 and enter the legislature, formed a party (1923) called",
            "optionA": "  Swaraj Party ",
            "optionB": "  Congress Swarajya Party ",
            "optionC": "  Nationalist Party ",
            "optionD": "  Liberal Party ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSwaraj Party, Indian political party established in late 1922\u2013early 1923 by members of the Indian National Congress (Congress Party), notably Motilal Nehru, one of the most prominent lawyers in northern India (and the father of political leader Jawaharlal Nehru), and Chitta Ranjan Das, a nationalist politician from Bengal. The party\u2019s name is taken from the term swaraj, meaning \u201cself-rule,\u201d which was broadly applied to the movement to gain independence from British rule. ",
            "keyString": "198732s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "As a result of the elections held in early 1937 under the Act of 1935 the Congress formed ministries in provinces",
            "optionA": "  7 ",
            "optionB": "  9 ",
            "optionC": "  10 ",
            "optionD": "  8 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs a result of the elections held in early 1937 under the Act of 1935 the Congress formed ministries in 8 provinces. ",
            "keyString": "198936s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Secretary of State for India was given powers by",
            "optionA": "  The Act of 1909 ",
            "optionB": "  The Act of 1919 ",
            "optionC": "  The Act of 1858 ",
            "optionD": "  The Act of 1861 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Secretary of State for India was British cabinet minister and political head of Indian office. This post was created in 1858 by Government of India Act which transferred the power to British crown when East India Company rule in Bengal ended and India( except princely states) was brought under the direct administration of the government in London which marked the beginning of the colonial period under British Empire.",
            "keyString": "202923s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said that the constant 'drain of wealth' from India was responsible for India's economic miseries?",
            "optionA": "  BC Pal ",
            "optionB": "  BP Wadia ",
            "optionC": "  Dadabhai Naoroji ",
            "optionD": "  GS Arundale ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDadabhai Naoroji was the first man to say that internal factors were not the reasons of poverty in India but poverty was caused by the colonial rule that was draining the wealth and prosperity of India. ",
            "keyString": "203162s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "'AI Hilal' was a newspaper launched for propagating nationalism by",
            "optionA": "  Syed Ahmed Khan ",
            "optionB": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionC": "  Abul Kalam Azad ",
            "optionD": "  DE Wacha ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAl-Hilal (newspaper) was a weekly Urdu language newspaper established by the Indian leader Maulana Abul Kalam Azad and used as a medium for criticism of the British Raj in India. The first issue came out on 13 July 1912. ",
            "keyString": "203343s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The song Jana-Gana-Mana composed by Rabindranath Tagore was first published in January 1912 under the title of",
            "optionA": "  Tatva Bodhini ",
            "optionB": "  Morning Song of India ",
            "optionC": "  Bharat Vidhata ",
            "optionD": "  Rashtra Jagrati ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe song Jana-Gana-Mana composed by Rabindranath Tagore was first published in January 1912 under the title of Bharat Vidhata. ",
            "keyString": "353581s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "To whom is the statement \"Cowardice and ahimsa do not go together any more than water and fire\" attributed?",
            "optionA": "  Acharya Narendra Dev ",
            "optionB": "  M K Gandhi ",
            "optionC": "  Swami Vivekananda ",
            "optionD": "  Jayaprakash Narayan ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCowardice and ahimsa do not go together any more than water and fire\" attributed to M K Gandhi. ",
            "keyString": "354246s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the moving spirit behind the oganization of the Ghadar Party?",
            "optionA": "  Lala Hardayal ",
            "optionB": "  V. ",
            "optionC": " Savarkar ",
            "optionD": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLala Hardayal was the moving spirit behind the oganization of the Ghadar Party. ",
            "keyString": "354620s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Of the following who was a poet and political thinker?",
            "optionA": "  Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  Jinnah ",
            "optionC": "  Mohammed Iqbal ",
            "optionD": "  Patel ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSir Muhammad Iqbal widely known as Allama Iqbal, was a poet, philosopher and politician, as well as an academic, barrister and scholar in British India who is widely regarded as having inspired the Pakistan Movement.",
            "keyString": "355008s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who had scrapped the partition of Bengal?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Hardinge ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Mountbatten ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Lytton ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Wellesley ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Hardinge had scrapped the partition of Bengal. ",
            "keyString": "355195s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "__________edited the journal of Poona Sarvajanik Sabha",
            "optionA": "  Gokhale ",
            "optionB": "  W. ",
            "optionC": " Banerjee ",
            "optionD": "  Ranade ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter graduation in 1884, Gokhale joined the Deccan educational Society founded by Ranade. He served the society for twenty years in various capacities as a school master, a professor and principal of Fergusson College, Poona. He also edited the quarterly journal of the Poona Sarvajanik Sabha. ",
            "keyString": "477809s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following event was probe by the Hunter Commission?",
            "optionA": "  Chauri Chaura incident ",
            "optionB": "  Demolition of Kanpur mosque ",
            "optionC": "  Jalianwalla Bagh massacre ",
            "optionD": "  Kakori train dacoity incident ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Jallianwala Bagh massacre, also known as the Amritsar massacre, took place on 13 April 1919 when troops of the British Indian Army under the command of Colonel Reginald Dyer fired rifles into a crowd of Punjabis, who had gathered in Jallianwala Bagh, Amritsar, Punjab. ",
            "keyString": "478192s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indirect election was introduced in India by the Act of",
            "optionA": "  1853 ",
            "optionB": "  1858 ",
            "optionC": "  1892 ",
            "optionD": "  1833 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe act of 1892 can be said to be a first step towards the beginning of the representative government in India. However such representation was via only indirect elections and there was nothing for a common Indian. The system of indirect election prevented direct contact between the public and the representatives. ",
            "keyString": "478422s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the founder of Banaras Hindu University?",
            "optionA": "  Sukumar Dutt ",
            "optionB": "  Madan Mohan Malviya ",
            "optionC": "  Dr. Rajendra Prasad ",
            "optionD": "  Motilal Nehru ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMadan Mohan Malviya strived to promote modern education among hindus and eventually founded Banaras Hindu University (BHU) at Varanasi in 1916, which was created under the B.H.U. Act, 1915. The largest residential university in Asia and one of the largest in the world, having over 40,000 students across arts, sciences, engineering, medical, agriculture, performing arts, law and technology from all over the world. He was Vice Chancellor of Banaras Hindu University from 1919\u20131938. ",
            "keyString": "480126s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the correct chronological order of in modern Indian history?",
            "optionA": "  Morley-Minto Reforms, Gandhi-Irwin Pact, August Offer, Jallianwala Bagh Massacre ",
            "optionB": "  August Offer, Morley-Minto Reforms, Jallianwala Bagh Massacre, Gandhi-Irwin Pact ",
            "optionC": "  Morley-Minto Reforms, Jallianwala Bagh Massacre, Gandhi-Irwin Pact, August Offer ",
            "optionD": "  Jallianwala Bagh Massacre, Gandhi-Irwin Pact, August Offer, Morley-Minto Reforms ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMorley-Minto Reforms- 1909, Jallianwala Bagh Massacre- 1919, Gandhi-Irwin Pact- 1931, August Offer- 1940. ",
            "keyString": "480343s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "India Home Rule Society, founded in London in February 1905, was one of the earliest revolutionary societies set up outside India. This society was founded by",
            "optionA": "  Lala Har Dayal ",
            "optionB": "  VD Savarkar ",
            "optionC": "  Shyamji Krishnavarma ",
            "optionD": "  Madan Lal Dhingra ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt first housed an organisation called the Indian Home Rule Society (IHRS).This was founded in February 1905 by Shyamji Krishna Varma along with other notable expatriate Indians such as Bhikaji Cama, S.R. Rana and Lala Lajpat Rai to serve as a rival organisation to the British Committee of Congress. ",
            "keyString": "601027s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following leader is correctly matched with their association/party/ books/ newspaper?",
            "optionA": "  Devendranath Tagore: Young India ",
            "optionB": "  Rabindranath Tagore: Patrika ",
            "optionC": "  M. K. Gandhi: Gitanjali ",
            "optionD": "  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBal Gangadhar Tilak born as Keshav Gangadhar Tilak, was an Indian nationalist, teacher, lawyer and an independence activist. He was the first leader of the Indian Independence Movement. ",
            "keyString": "601961s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Singh Sabha intended to restore Sikhism to its past purity by publishing historical religious books, magazines and journals, to propagate knowledge using Punjabi, to return Sikh apostates to their original faith, and to involve highly placed __________in the educational programme of the Sikhs",
            "optionA": "  Portuguese ",
            "optionB": "  Frenchmen ",
            "optionC": "  Dutch ",
            "optionD": "  Englishmen ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Singh Sabha intended to restore Sikhism to its past purity by publishing historical religious books, magazines and journals, to propagate knowledge using Punjabi, to return Sikh apostates to their original faith, and to involve highly placed Englishmen in the educational programme of the Sikhs. ",
            "keyString": "602522s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following literary personalities made the greatest contribution in arousing patriotism in the 19th century?",
            "optionA": "  Dinbandhu Mitra's exposure of Indigo planters in Nil Darpana ",
            "optionB": "  Bankim Chandra with his historical novels culminating with Ananda Math (1882) ",
            "optionC": "  Vishnu Krishna Chiplunkar's Journal Nibandhamaka (1874-81) ",
            "optionD": "  Bharatendu Harishchandra (1850-85) through his plays, poems and journals advocating use of Swadeshi articles and use of Hindi in courts ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBankim Chandra with his historical novels culminating with Ananda Math (1882) made the greatest contribution in arousing patriotism in the 19th century. ",
            "keyString": "602702s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Of the following who are not given reserved seats in the Indian legislature?",
            "optionA": "  Scheduled Caste ",
            "optionB": "  Scheduled Tribes ",
            "optionC": "  Anglo-Indian ",
            "optionD": "  Landed Gentry ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLanded Gentry are not given reserved seats in the Indian legislature. ",
            "keyString": "602877s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following did not attend the First Round Table Conference?",
            "optionA": "  MK Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  Sir Tej Bahadur Sapru ",
            "optionC": "  Dr Ambedkar ",
            "optionD": "  C V Chintamani ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first Round Table Conference convened from 12 November 1930 to 19 January 1931. Prior to the Conference, M. K. Gandhi had initiated the Civil Disobedience Movement on behalf of the Indian National Congress. ",
            "keyString": "709295s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indian tricolour was unfurled for the first time by Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "optionA": "  At the ramparts of the red ford in 1947 ",
            "optionB": "  On the bank of Ravi at Lahore in 1929 ",
            "optionC": "  When India became a democratic republic in 1950 ",
            "optionD": "  When The Government of India Act was\npassed in 1935 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indian Tricolour was unfurled for the first time by Jawaharlal Nehru on the banks of Ravi at Lahore in 1929, in this session. The demand of Purna Swaraj was raised. ",
            "keyString": "711443s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1939 Subhash Chandra Bose was elected as President of the Congress Party defeating",
            "optionA": "  Pattabhi Sitharamayy ",
            "optionB": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionC": "  Maulana Abul Kalam Azad ",
            "optionD": "  VB Patel ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the Tripuri Session of 1939 of INC a deadlock was created due to the ideological differences between M.K. Gandhi and Subhash Chandra Bose and election was held for the post of chairman in which Bose defeated Pattabhi Setharamayya (supported by M.K Gandhi). ",
            "keyString": "712905s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The President of the Constituent Assembly was",
            "optionA": "  Dr. BR Ambedkar ",
            "optionB": "  Dr. Rajendra Prasad ",
            "optionC": "  Jawahar Lal Nehru ",
            "optionD": "  Vallabhbhai Patel ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDr. Sachchidananda Sinha was the first chairman (temporary) of Constituent Assembly. Later Dr. Rajendra Prasad was elected as the president and its vice-president was Harendra Coomar Mookerjee, a Christian from Bengal and former vice-chancellor of Calcutta University. ",
            "keyString": "713289s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who ruled that pilgrims could wear yellow clothes - the colour of the garments Sri Buddha wore",
            "optionA": "  P. K. Kesavan ",
            "optionB": "  Govindan Vaidyar ",
            "optionC": "  P. K. Divakara Panicker ",
            "optionD": "  Sree Narayana Guru ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSree Narayana Guru ruled that pilgrims could wear yellow clothes - the colour of the garments Sri Buddha wore ",
            "keyString": "713602s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following was not of the achievements of the Exteremist Group in the Congress?",
            "optionA": "  The partition of Bengal was annulled in 1911 ",
            "optionB": "  The Calcutta Corporation Act and the Indian Universities Act were taken off the statute book ",
            "optionC": "  Nationalism took root among the progressive sections of society ",
            "optionD": "  The Extremists taught people self-confidence and selfreliance and prepared the social base of the nationalist movement ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Calcutta Corporation Act and the Indian Universities Act were taken off the statute book was not of the achievements of the Exteremist Group in the Congress. ",
            "keyString": "793692s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Motilal Nehru and Chittaranjan Das were the founder members of the",
            "optionA": "  Communist Party of India ",
            "optionB": "  Forward Block ",
            "optionC": "  Socialist-Swarajist Party ",
            "optionD": "  Swarajya Party ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSwarajya Party was established in 1923, by Moti Lal Nehru and Chittaranjan das in Allahabad. ",
            "keyString": "793966s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who introduced the permanent settlement in Bengal?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Cornwallis ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Dalhousie ",
            "optionC": "  William Bentinck ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Curzon ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Cornwallis introduced permanent settlement in Bengal. Under this fix revenue system was introduced. ",
            "keyString": "794169s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following Governor-General repealed the Vernacular Press Act of Lytton?",
            "optionA": "  Northbrook ",
            "optionB": "  Dufferin ",
            "optionC": "  Elgin-II ",
            "optionD": "  Ripon ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGovernor-General Ripon repealed the Vernacular Press Act of Lytton. ",
            "keyString": "794513s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "To avenge the brutal lathi charge on Lala Lajpat Rai (October 30, 1928), which was believed to have caused his death subsequently, who murdered Saunders, the Assistant Superintendent of Police, Lahore?",
            "optionA": "  Batukeshwar Dutt ",
            "optionB": "  Bhagat Singh ",
            "optionC": "  Chandra Shekhar Azad ",
            "optionD": "  Sachindra Sanyal ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTo avenge the brutal lathi charge on Lala Lajpat Rai (October 30, 1928), which was believed to have caused his death subsequently, Bhagat Singh murdered Saunders, the Assistant Superintendent of Police, Lahore. ",
            "keyString": "794697s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Baba Ram Singh, born at Bhaini, in __________district in 1816",
            "optionA": "  Haryana ",
            "optionB": "  Jodhpur ",
            "optionC": "  Kashmir ",
            "optionD": "  Ludhiana ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRam Singh was born at Bhaini in Ludhiana district of Punjab in 1816. He joined as a soldier in the Sikh army and there he came under the influence of Bhai Balak Singh. ",
            "keyString": "843946s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Ryotwari System of Land Tenure to a situation where",
            "optionA": "  The Ryot is the owner of the land held by him/\nher and directly pays the revenue assessed\non the land to the State ",
            "optionB": "  The Ryot is an occupancy tenant of his/her land\nand pays the land revenue to the Zamindar ",
            "optionC": "  The person cultivates the land leased from a\nlandlord and inreturn pays rent to the landlord ",
            "optionD": "  The land is collectively owned and cultivated\non a cooperative basis ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Ryotwari system was a land tenure system in British India, introduced by Sir Thomas Munro in 1820 based on system administered by Captain Alexander Read in the Baramahal district. It allowed the government to deal directly with the peasant (ryot) for revenue collection, and gave the peasant freedom to give up or acquire new land for cultivation. ",
            "keyString": "844165s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following reason that compel the Congress leader not to attend the Round Table Conference?",
            "optionA": "  The British government was not in favour of M. K. Gandhi's participation in it ",
            "optionB": "  The British government wanted to give representation to communal organisations ",
            "optionC": "  The British government did not give any\u00a0assurance to the effect that the discussions\u00a0would proceed on the basis of granting\u00a0Poorna Swaraj ",
            "optionD": "  Fazl-i-Hussain who was suspected of dislike towards the Muslims with leanings towards the Congress was to guide the British government in the choice of Muslim delegates to the conference ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe British government did not give any assurance to the effect that the discussions would proceed on the basis of granting Poorna Swaraj was the reason that compel the Congress leader not to attend the Round Table Conference. ",
            "keyString": "844365s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mahabandula was killed at __________",
            "optionA": "  Rangoon ",
            "optionB": "  Tenesserin ",
            "optionC": "  Danubyu ",
            "optionD": "  Prome ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn December 1824, Maha Bandula opened a broad offensive against the British positions in the area of Rangoon but was defeated and retreated to Danubyu. He defended Danubyu successfully beginning on March 5 but was killed during an artillery bombardment. ",
            "keyString": "844554s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Narayana Guru was born on August 22, 1856, in the village of __________ near Thiruvananthapuram",
            "optionA": "  Chempazhanthi ",
            "optionB": "  Karunagapally ",
            "optionC": "  Kayamkulam ",
            "optionD": "  Kannur ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSree Narayana Guru was born on August 22, 1856 (1032 Chingam in Malayalam calendar) in a humble cottage in the pretty hamlet of Chempazhanthi near Thiruvananthapuram. His father was Madan Asan, a farmer, and mother Kutti Amma and he had three sisters. He was named by his father as Narayanan; he affectionately called him Nanu, a short name for Narayanan. ",
            "keyString": "844760s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1913, the Guru founded an Ashram at __________ called the Advaita Ashram",
            "optionA": "  Vaikom ",
            "optionB": "  Palluruthi ",
            "optionC": "  Aluva ",
            "optionD": "  Trichur ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1913, the Guru founded an Ashram at Aluva called the Advaita Ashram. ",
            "keyString": "930041s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Of the following who died as political prisoner in Lahore prison?",
            "optionA": "  Bhagat Singh ",
            "optionB": "  Batukeshwar Dutt ",
            "optionC": "  Jatin Das ",
            "optionD": "  Sukh Dev ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJatindra Nath Das (27 October 1904 \u2013 13 September 1929), also known as Jatin Das, was an Indian independence activist and revolutionary. He died in Lahore jail after a 63-day hunger strike. ",
            "keyString": "930521s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under whose leadership was the Congress Socialist Party founded in 1934?",
            "optionA": "  Jawaharlal Nehru and Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  Acharya Narendra Bose and P. ",
            "optionC": " Joshi ",
            "optionD": "  Subhas Chandra Bose and P. ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder the leadership of Acharya Narendra Bose and P. C. Joshi Narayan Congress Socialist Party was founded in 1934 and Acharya Narendra Dev was the president of Party. ",
            "keyString": "930942s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following introduced Ryotwari system in madras?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Hastings ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Wellesley ",
            "optionC": "  Sir Thomas Munro ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Cannemara ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSir Thomas Munro introduced Ryotwari system in Madras in 1820. Under Ryotwari System the ryots (peasnts) were given thc direct ownership and British government collected taxes directly from peasant. This system was introduced in Madras, Bombay, part of Assam. ",
            "keyString": "931354s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Second Round Table Conference failed over the question of",
            "optionA": "  communal representation ",
            "optionB": "  suspension of Civil Disobedience Movement ",
            "optionC": "  grant of dominion status ",
            "optionD": "  date of transfer of power ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Second Round Table Conference failed over the question of communal representation. The conference was deadlocked on the minorities issue for separate electorate was now being demanded by the Muslims, Dalits, Christians, Anglo Indians, and Europeans etc. ",
            "keyString": "931765s12m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Har Bilas Sarda was instrumental in the passage of the famous Sarda Act of 1930, which provided for",
            "optionA": "  enforcing monogamy ",
            "optionB": "  removal of restrictions on intercaste marriages ",
            "optionC": "  penalisation of parties to a marriage in which the girl was below 14 or the boy was below 18 years of age ",
            "optionD": "  civil marriages ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHar Bilas Sarda was Instrumental in the passage of the famous Sarda Act of 1930, which provided for penalisation of parties to a marriage in which the girl was below 14 or the boy was below 18 years of age. ",
            "keyString": "20594s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the first propounder of the doctrine of Passive Resistance ?",
            "optionA": "  ",
            "optionB": " G Tilak ",
            "optionC": "  Aurobindo Ghosh ",
            "optionD": "  Lajpat Rai ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDoctrine of Passive Resistance was propounded by Aurobindo Ghosh, it was based on a series of articles published by Aurobindo Ghosh. ",
            "keyString": "21234s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Act(s) was/were passed in 1856?",
            "optionA": "  The Religious Disabilities Act ",
            "optionB": "  The Hindu Widow Remarriage Act ",
            "optionC": "  Both the above ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBoth The Religious Disabilities Act and The Hindu Widow Remarriage Act were passed in 1856. ",
            "keyString": "21722s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who established the Indian Civil Liberties Union in 1936?",
            "optionA": "  Subhash Chandra Bose ",
            "optionB": "  Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "optionC": "  Jawahar Lal Nehru ",
            "optionD": "  Rajendra Prasad ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJawahar Lal Nehru established the Indian CivilLiberties union in 1936. This is the origin of Human right movement in India. ",
            "keyString": "22189s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The term of office of member of the Council of India as per the act of 1919 was",
            "optionA": "  5 years ",
            "optionB": "  4 years ",
            "optionC": "  2 years ",
            "optionD": "  6 years ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe term of office of member of the Council of India as per the act of 1919 was 5 years. ",
            "keyString": "22682s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Tilak called him the 'Diamond of India, the jewel of Maharashtra and the Prince of Workers'. Who is referred in these words",
            "optionA": "  Lajpat Rai ",
            "optionB": "  Shivaji ",
            "optionC": "  Gokhale ",
            "optionD": "  Madhava Rao ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTilak called Gokhale the 'Diamond of India, the jewel of Maharashtra and the Prince of Workers'. ",
            "keyString": "143017s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Identify the revolutionary among the following who was not active in London?",
            "optionA": "  Shyamji Krishna Varma ",
            "optionB": "  Ashfaqullah ",
            "optionC": "  Lala Hardayal ",
            "optionD": "  V D Savarkar ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe revolutionary Ashfaqullah was not active in London. ",
            "keyString": "143241s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who were called \"Kukas\"?",
            "optionA": "  Namdhari ",
            "optionB": "  Nirankari ",
            "optionC": "  Tilak ",
            "optionD": "  Sri Aurobindo ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Namdharis were also known as \u201cKukas\u201d because of their trademark style of reciting the \u201cGurbani\u201d (Sayings/Teachings of the Guru). This style was in a high-pitched voice called \u201cKook\u201d in Punjabi. Thus, the Namdharis were also called \u201cKukas\u201d. ",
            "keyString": "143429s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Theosophical Society was officially formed in . . . . ., United States, in November 1875 by Helena Blavatsky, Henry Steel Olcott, William Quan Judge and others",
            "optionA": "  Madras ",
            "optionB": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionC": "  Bombay ",
            "optionD": "  New York City ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Theosophical Society was officially formed in New York City, United States, on 17 November 1875 by Helena Petrovna Blavatsky, Colonel Henry Steel Olcott, William Quan Judge, and others. Olcott was its first president, and remained president until his demise in 1907. ",
            "keyString": "143650s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mrs Annie Besant became the first woman President of the INC in",
            "optionA": "  1916 ",
            "optionB": "  1917 ",
            "optionC": "  1918 ",
            "optionD": "  1920 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShe launched the Home Rule League in 1916, modelling the Indian plight on that of Ireland. She was a member of the Fabian Society, owing to her close relationship with George Bernard Shaw. In 1917 she became the first woman president of the Indian National Congress at a session in Calcutta. ",
            "keyString": "144022s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1937 , an educational conference endorsing Gandhi's proposals for 'basic education' through the vernacular medium was held at",
            "optionA": "  Surat ",
            "optionB": "  Bombay ",
            "optionC": "  Ahmedabad ",
            "optionD": "  Wardha ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe educational conference endorsing Gandhi's proposals for 'basic education' through the Vernacular medium was held in October 1937 at Wardha. ",
            "keyString": "277237s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who had paned the Vernacular Press Act into law?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Mayo ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Hardinge ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Dalhousie ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Lytton ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tProposed by Lord Lytton, then viceroy of India (governed 1876\u201380), the act was intended to prevent the vernacular press from expressing criticism of British policies\u2014notably, the opposition that had grown with the outset of the Second Anglo-Afghan War (1878\u201380). The act excluded English-language publications. ",
            "keyString": "277277s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following provision is a part of the Government of India Act of 1919?",
            "optionA": "  Transfer of power to the Indians ",
            "optionB": "  The enlargement of the Viceroy's Executive Council ",
            "optionC": "  Remodelling of the Central legislature ",
            "optionD": "  Doing away with the distinction between the regulation and non-regulation provinces ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTransfer of power to the Indians is a part of the Government of India Act of 1919. ",
            "keyString": "277296s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The famine in Bihar and Bengal in 1873-74 was averted by the timely action of",
            "optionA": "  Minto ",
            "optionB": "  Morley ",
            "optionC": "  Northbrook ",
            "optionD": "  Hastings ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe famine in Bihar and Bengal in 1873-74 was averted by the timely action of Northbrook. ",
            "keyString": "277312s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "'There are no politics devoid of religion' is stated by",
            "optionA": "  Nehru ",
            "optionB": "  Gandhi ",
            "optionC": "  Vinoba Bhave ",
            "optionD": "  Jaya Prakash Narayan ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGandhiji said \"there is no politics devoid of religion\" and \"Politics bereft of religion death trap\". ",
            "keyString": "277327s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The __________ was run by Tarachand Chakravarty",
            "optionA": "  Quill ",
            "optionB": "  Hesperus ",
            "optionC": "  Enquirer ",
            "optionD": "  Bengal Spectator ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Quill was run by Tarachand Chakravarty. Tarachand's own paper, Quill, was the mouthpiece of the modernist reform school that he headed. ",
            "keyString": "401442s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Tilak was sentenced and transported to",
            "optionA": "  Mandal ",
            "optionB": "  Mandalay ",
            "optionC": "  Australia ",
            "optionD": "  Andaman ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTilak was sent to prison for six years (he spent most of it in a prison in Mandalay, Burma). ",
            "keyString": "401505s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In a message to the Sree Narayana Dharma Paripalana Yogam in 1926 __________ declared, no community can make progress except through organization",
            "optionA": "  Chattambi Swamikal ",
            "optionB": "  Dr. Palpu ",
            "optionC": "  Narayana Guru ",
            "optionD": "  Rajaram Mohan Roy ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn a message to the Sree Narayana Dharma Paripalana Yogam in 1926 Narayana Guru declared, No community can make progress except through organization. ",
            "keyString": "401520s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "'Confessions of Thug' was written by",
            "optionA": "  Burke ",
            "optionB": "  Meadows Taylor ",
            "optionC": "  Havell ",
            "optionD": "  Moreland ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tConfessions of a Thug is an English novel written by Philip Meadows Taylor in 1839 based on the Thuggee cult in British India. ",
            "keyString": "401533s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said, The Congress is tottering to its fall and one of\nmy greatest ambitions while in India is to assist it to a\npeaceful demise?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Dufferin ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Curzon ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Lansdowne ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Elgin ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Curzon said, The Congress is tottering to its fall and one of my greatest ambition while in India is to assist it to a peaceful demise. ",
            "keyString": "401544s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Hindu College was started in 1817 at",
            "optionA": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionB": "  Bombay ",
            "optionC": "  Madras ",
            "optionD": "  Pondicherry ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHindu College was established in 1817 by Raja Ram Mohan Roy, Radhakanta Deb, David Hare, Sir Edward Hyde East, Baidyanath Mukhopadhya and Rasamay Dutt. ",
            "keyString": "637479s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the French Governor of Pondicherry who tried to make the French Company as a powerful company?",
            "optionA": "  Thomas Arthur, Comte de Lally ",
            "optionB": "  Godeheu ",
            "optionC": "  La Bourdonnais ",
            "optionD": "  Joseph Francois Dupleix ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJoseph Francois Dupleix was the French Governor General(1742-57) of Pondicherry. He was the rival of Robert Clive. ",
            "keyString": "637671s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Jinnah gave his opposition to Wavell's Plan in the Conference held at __________",
            "optionA": "  Delhi ",
            "optionB": "  Shimla ",
            "optionC": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionD": "  Madras ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJinnah gave his opposition to Wavell's Plan in the Conference held at Shimla. ",
            "keyString": "637831s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1937, the Congress formed Ministries in",
            "optionA": "  7 states ",
            "optionB": "  9 states ",
            "optionC": "  5 states ",
            "optionD": "  4 states ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1937 , Congress had clean majority in five provinces i.e.- United provincesU.P., Madras, Bihar, Central provinces (C. P.), Orissa and formed its own government in 5 provinces. ",
            "keyString": "637989s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the Chairman of the Union Powers Committee of the Constituent Assembly of India?",
            "optionA": "  Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel ",
            "optionB": "  Dr. ",
            "optionC": " R. Ambedkar ",
            "optionD": "  Sir Alladi Krishnaswami Ayyar ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPt. Jawaharlal Nehru was the chairman of the Union Power Committee of the constituent assembly. ",
            "keyString": "638143s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The author of the \"The Peri plus of the Erythraean Sea\" was a",
            "optionA": "  Historian ",
            "optionB": "  Poet ",
            "optionC": "  Sailor ",
            "optionD": "  Musician ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe author of the \"The Peri plus of the Erythraean Sea\" was a sailor. ",
            "keyString": "742436s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Why was the Simon Commission boycotted by the Indians?",
            "optionA": "  It did not include any Indian as a member ",
            "optionB": "  It did not have any woman member ",
            "optionC": "  It was appointed before the stipulated time ",
            "optionD": "  If refused to meet prominent Indian leaders ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Simon Commission was established by the British government, to future administrative reforms in India. This commission was boycotted by the Indians because it did not include any Indian member. ",
            "keyString": "742740s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Muslim League demanded creation of Pakistan (Pakistan Resolution) in its session held on March 24, 1940 at",
            "optionA": "  Karachi ",
            "optionB": "  Lahore ",
            "optionC": "  Islamabad ",
            "optionD": "  Aligarh ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe resolution for the establishment of a separate homeland for the Muslims of British India passed in the annual session of the All India Muslim League held in Lahore on 22\u201324 March 1940 is a landmark document of Pakistan's history. ",
            "keyString": "742951s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following pair of Congress Session is not correctly matched?",
            "optionA": "  Nagpur Session 1920: Changes in the Constitution of the Congress ",
            "optionB": "  Madras Session 1927: Independence Resolution passed for the first time at the instance of Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionC": "  Calcutta Session 1928: Return of Gandhi to active politics after six years ",
            "optionD": "  Lahore Session 1929:\u00a0Resolution on Fundamental Rights and National Economic Policy ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLahore Session 1929. When the Nehru Report came before the annual session of the Congress in Calcutta in December 1928, the left lashed it out on the fact that it did not want the complete Independence and wanted only a dominion status. ",
            "keyString": "743137s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Cripps Mission visited India in the year",
            "optionA": "  1940 ",
            "optionB": "  1942 ",
            "optionC": "  1945 ",
            "optionD": "  1946 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Cripps Mission was a failed attempt in late March 1942 by the British government to secure full Indian cooperation and support for their efforts in World War II. The mission was headed by a senior minister Sir Stafford Cripps, Lord Privy Seal and leader of the House of Commons. ",
            "keyString": "743316s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "My strongest bulwark is gone lamented Mahatma Gandhi on the death of",
            "optionA": "  Gopalakrishna Gokhale ",
            "optionB": "  Motilal Nehru ",
            "optionC": "  Pheroze Shah Mehta ",
            "optionD": "  Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMy strongest bulwark is gone lamented Mahatma Gandhi on the death of Bal Gangadhar Tilak. ",
            "keyString": "853334s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following influenced the makers of Indian Constitution?",
            "optionA": "  The Constitution of China ",
            "optionB": "  The Constitution of USSR ",
            "optionC": "  The Constitution of USA ",
            "optionD": "  The Constitution of Japan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Constitution of USA influenced the makers of Indian Constitution. ",
            "keyString": "854171s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "As per the Cabinet Mission Plan, the power would be first transferred to __________",
            "optionA": "  The Indian National Congress ",
            "optionB": "  The Interim Government ",
            "optionC": "  The Viceroy ",
            "optionD": "  The Princes of the States ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Cabinet Mission of 1946 came to India aimed to discuss the transfer of power from the British government to the Indian leadership, with the aim of preserving India's unity and granting it independence. As per the Cabinet Mission Plan, the power would be first transferred to The Interim Government. ",
            "keyString": "986925s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first Indian to enter the Indian Civil Service was",
            "optionA": "  Gokhale ",
            "optionB": "  Satyendra Nath Tagore ",
            "optionC": "  Ramanuja ",
            "optionD": "  Rabindranath Tagore ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSatyendranath was selected for the Indian Civil Service in June, 1863. He completed his probationary training and returned to India in November 1864. ",
            "keyString": "987337s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "__________ made a whirlwind tour of the country in 1916 and in his speeches he said, \"Swaraj is my birthright and I will have it.\"",
            "optionA": "  Tilak ",
            "optionB": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionC": "  Gokhale ",
            "optionD": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTilak made a whirlwind tour of the country in 1916 and in his speeches he said, \"Swaraj is my birthright and I will have it.\" ",
            "keyString": "987505s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first President of the Ghadar Party - founded in 1913 in USA was",
            "optionA": "  Lata Hardayal ",
            "optionB": "  Sohan Singh Bhakna ",
            "optionC": "  Bhai Parmanand ",
            "optionD": "  Sardar Ajit Singh ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1913, Pacific Coast Hindustan Association was founded by Lala Hardayal with Sohan Singh Bhakna as its president, which was called Ghadar Party. ",
            "keyString": "987680s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first statue of the Guru was conceived by __________",
            "optionA": "  Moorkoth Kumaran ",
            "optionB": "  Tavaroli ",
            "optionC": "  Bodhananda Swamikal ",
            "optionD": "  Gokahale ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMoorkoth Kumaran was a disciple of Narayana Guru and wrote the first biography of Guru. This biography contains the essence of Guru's message. He has initiated to install first statue of Narayana Guru in Kerala when he was alive. ",
            "keyString": "987848s13m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following was famous for framing the education minute?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Elgin ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Macaulay ",
            "optionC": "  Sadler ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Macaulay was famous for framing education minute, he brought English language as a medium of subject. ",
            "keyString": "57208s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mahatma Gandhi returned to India from__________  in January 1915",
            "optionA": "  South Africa ",
            "optionB": "  England ",
            "optionC": "  USA ",
            "optionD": "  Russia ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahatma Gandhi returned to India from South Africa in January 9, 1915. The political Guru of Gandhi was Gopal Krishna Gokhle. ",
            "keyString": "57466s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bicameral Legislature was first provided to India by the",
            "optionA": "  Pitt's India Act ",
            "optionB": "  Government of India Act of 1935 ",
            "optionC": "  Government of India Act of 1919 ",
            "optionD": "  Council Act of 1861 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBicameral Legislature was first provided to India by the Government of India Act of 1919. ",
            "keyString": "57572s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who opened the First Round Table Conference?",
            "optionA": "  King George V ",
            "optionB": "  MK Gandhi ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Irwin ",
            "optionD": "  Ramsay McDonald ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFirst Round Table Conference was held between November 1930 and January 1931. It was officially inaugurated on November 12, 1930 at House of Lords at London by the British King (George V) and was chaired by then British Prime Minister, Ramsay MacDonald. ",
            "keyString": "57681s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following leaders did not attended the First Round Table Conference?",
            "optionA": "  M. K. Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  Sir Tej Bahadur Sapru ",
            "optionC": "  Dr. Ambedkar ",
            "optionD": "  Y. Chintamani ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first Round Table Conference convened from 12 November 1930 to 19 January 1931. Prior to the Conference, M. K. Gandhi had initiated the Civil Disobedience Movement on behalf of the Indian National Congress. ",
            "keyString": "57803s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Mountbatten plan did not envisage the inclusion of the __________ province in the Indian dominion",
            "optionA": "  Bihar ",
            "optionB": "  Sind ",
            "optionC": "  Madras ",
            "optionD": "  Bombay ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Mountbatten plan did not envisage the inclusion of the Sind province in the Indian dominion. ",
            "keyString": "177869s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indian Civil Service Examination was thrown open to all by the Act of",
            "optionA": "  1853 ",
            "optionB": "  1858 ",
            "optionC": "  1813 ",
            "optionD": "  1784 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFrom 1858, after the demise of the East India Company's rule in India, the British civil service took on its administrative responsibilities. The change in governance came about due to the Indian Rebellion of 1857, which came close to toppling British rule in the country. ",
            "keyString": "178780s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "__________'s Darsana Mala is written in Sanskrit",
            "optionA": "  Sree Narayana Guru ",
            "optionB": "  Chattambi Swamikal ",
            "optionC": "  ",
            "optionD": " Kesavan ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Darsana Mala, or Garland of Visions, was one of the last major works of All Saint Brahmasree Guru Narayana, dictated about 1916. ",
            "keyString": "179019s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In the Cabinet Mission Plan, provision was made for the Commissioner's Provinces to represent by __________ members in the Constituent Assembly",
            "optionA": "  14 ",
            "optionB": "  10 ",
            "optionC": "  8 ",
            "optionD": "  4 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the Cabinet Mission Plan, provision was made for the Commissioner's Provinces to represent by 4 members in the Constituent Assembly. ",
            "keyString": "180723s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "As per Cabinet Mission Plan, the Princely States would be represented by __________ members in the Constituent Assembly",
            "optionA": "  90 ",
            "optionB": "  93 ",
            "optionC": "  103 ",
            "optionD": "  100 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per cabinet mission plan the princely states would be represent by 93 members in the constituent assembly. ",
            "keyString": "183214s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In the Interim Government formed in 1946, the Minister for Education was",
            "optionA": "  Patel ",
            "optionB": "  Rajaji ",
            "optionC": "  Maulana Abul Kalam Azad ",
            "optionD": "  Annie Besant ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the Interim Government formed in 1946, the Minister for Education was Maulana Abul Kalam Azad.",
            "keyString": "289990s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who had founded the Indian Home Rule Society?",
            "optionA": "  Madan Lal Dhingra ",
            "optionB": "  V D Savarkar ",
            "optionC": "  Lala Hardayal ",
            "optionD": "  Shyamji Krishna Varma ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe organisation was founded by Shyamji Krishna Varma, with support from a number of prominent Indian nationalists in Britain at the time, including Bhikaji Cama, Dadabhai Naoroji and S.R. The society was founded amongst efforts and movements that arose to reverse the flow of authority and power from Britain to India. ",
            "keyString": "290474s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "From 1885 to 1905 (the moderate phase of the INC) the object before the INC was",
            "optionA": "  wider employment of Indians in higher public services ",
            "optionB": "  establishment of representative institutions ",
            "optionC": "  self-government to India ",
            "optionD": "  Only A and B above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFrom 1885 to 1905 (the moderate phase of the INC) the object before the INC was wider employment of Indians in higher public services and establishment of representative institutions. ",
            "keyString": "290958s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main exponent of the theory of Drain of Wealth was",
            "optionA": "  RC Dutt ",
            "optionB": "  Dadabhai Naoroji ",
            "optionC": "  DR Gadoil ",
            "optionD": "  Karl Mane ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDadabhai Naoroji's work focused on the drain of wealth from India to England during colonial rule of British in India. One of the reasons that the Drain theory is attributed to Naoroji is his decision to estimate the net national profit of India, and by extension, the effect that colonisation has on the country. ",
            "keyString": "291377s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Gandhi-lrwin Pact (1931) was vehemently criticised and opposed by the people on the ground that",
            "optionA": "  the Civil Disobedience Movement was suspended ",
            "optionB": "  the sufferings of thousands of people in the Civil Disobedience Movement were wasted ",
            "optionC": "  It was contrary to the pledge of the Congress for Poorna Swaraj ",
            "optionD": "  Gandhi did nothing to save the lives of Bhagat Singh, Sukh Dev and Raj Guru who had been awarded the death sentence ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Gandhi-lrwin Pact (1931) was vehemently criticised and opposed by the people on the ground that Gandhi did nothing to save the lives of Bhagat Singh, Sukh Dev and Raj Guru who had been awarded the death sentence. ",
            "keyString": "291785s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which great war was fought between the years 1914 and 1918?",
            "optionA": "  The Battle of Tarain ",
            "optionB": "  The First World War ",
            "optionC": "  The Battle of Plassey ",
            "optionD": "  The Second World War ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWorld War I began in 1914, after the assassination of Archduke Franz Ferdinand, and lasted until 1918. During the conflict, Germany, Austria-Hungary, Bulgaria and the Ottoman Empire (the Central Powers) fought against Great Britain, France, Russia, Italy, Romania, Japan and the United States (the Allied Powers). ",
            "keyString": "400535s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the first woman President of Congress?",
            "optionA": "  Mrs. Annie Besant ",
            "optionB": "  Mrs. Sarojini Naidu ",
            "optionC": "  Mrs. Nelline Sengupta ",
            "optionD": "  Aruna Asaf Ali ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMrs. Annie Beasant was the first women President of Congress (1917, Calcutta session), she was also the founder of Home rule League.",
            "keyString": "401400s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who had rounded the first women's university in India?",
            "optionA": "  Rani Ahilya Devi ",
            "optionB": "  Ishwar Chandra Vidayasagar ",
            "optionC": "  Rani of Thomi ",
            "optionD": "  Dhondo Keshav Karve ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShreemati Nathibai Damodar Thackersey (SNDT) University, the first women's university in India. It was founded in 1916 by Dr. Dhondo Keshav Karve, with the objective of educating more women. ",
            "keyString": "401814s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Hardayal, an intellectual giant, was associated with",
            "optionA": "  Home Rule Movement ",
            "optionB": "  Ghadar Movement ",
            "optionC": "  Swadeshi Movement ",
            "optionD": "  Non-Cooperation Movement ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLala Hardayal was a revolutionary attached with Gadar Movement in San Francisco. He inspired many Indians living in US and Canada to fight against British imperialism. He turned down a career in Indian Civil services to participate in National Movement. ",
            "keyString": "402212s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "After a few years Olcott and Blavatsky moved to India and established the International Headquarters at Adyar, in__________",
            "optionA": "  New Zealand ",
            "optionB": "  Canada ",
            "optionC": "  Australia ",
            "optionD": "  Madras ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOlcott was its first president, and remained president until his demise in 1907. After a few years Olcott and Blavatsky moved to India and established the International Headquarters at Adyar, in Madras (now Chennai). ",
            "keyString": "402672s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Wavell Plan was announced in the year",
            "optionA": "  1945 ",
            "optionB": "  1942 ",
            "optionC": "  1946 ",
            "optionD": "  1940 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 14 June 1945 Lord Wavell announced a plan for a new Executive Council in which all members except the Viceroy and the Commander in Chief would be Indians. This executive council was to be a temporary measure until a new permanent constitution could be agreed upon and come into force. ",
            "keyString": "471013s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Constitution drawn by the Constituent Assembly (provided in the Cabinet Mission Plan) would be implemented by",
            "optionA": "  Parliament ",
            "optionB": "  The British Government ",
            "optionC": "  Viceroy ",
            "optionD": "  Indian National Congress ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Constitution drawn by the Constituent Assembly (provided in the Cabinet Mission Plan) would be implemented by The British Government. ",
            "keyString": "471340s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The 'Doctrine of Lapse' was first applied to the princely State of",
            "optionA": "  Satara ",
            "optionB": "  Jhansi ",
            "optionC": "  Avadh ",
            "optionD": "  Jaunpur ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSatara was the first princely state where Doctrine of lapse applied. The Doctrine of lapse theory was introduced by Lord Dalhousie.",
            "keyString": "472171s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Why did Mahatma Gandhi ultimately lend his support to the resolution passed by the Congress Working Committee agreeing to the partition of India in spite of his personal, lifelong outspoken disapproval of Pakistan?",
            "optionA": "  There was no other go after he was presented with a fait accompli ",
            "optionB": "  Jawaharlal Nehru convinced him about the justification in favour of it ",
            "optionC": "  To prevent the loss of prestige of the Congress Ministers who had agreed to the partition ",
            "optionD": "  The problem at home were far too pressing to carp about a minor concession being conceded to the Muslim League ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahatma Gandhi ultimately lend his support to the resolution passed by the Congress Working Committee agreeing to the partition of India in spite of his personal, lifelong outspoken disapproval of Pakistan to prevent the loss of prestige of the Congress Ministers who had agreed to the partition. ",
            "keyString": "472716s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Hindu Pioneer started in __________",
            "optionA": "  1827 ",
            "optionB": "  1831 ",
            "optionC": "  1834 ",
            "optionD": "  1838 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Hindu Pioneer was started in 1838. ",
            "keyString": "473676s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Dandi March started on __________ 1930",
            "optionA": "  12th March ",
            "optionB": "  12th April ",
            "optionC": "  12th February ",
            "optionD": "  12th May ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe historic march to protest against the salt law began on March 12, 1930 and gained momentum throughout India. ",
            "keyString": "605907s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the ruler of Delhi when Ahmad Shah Abdali defeated the Marathas in the third Battle of Panipat in 1761?",
            "optionA": "  Alamgir-I ",
            "optionB": "  Muhammad Shah ",
            "optionC": "  Jahadar Shah ",
            "optionD": "  Shah Alam-II ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAhmad Shah Abdali the military General of Nadir shah invaded india during the reign of Shah Alam-II (supported by the Marathas) which lead to Third battle of Panipat in 1761 in which Marathas were defeated by the Abdali. ",
            "keyString": "606436s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "At Jallianwala Bagh meeting __________ ordered the troops to open fire",
            "optionA": "  Benn ",
            "optionB": "  Irwin ",
            "optionC": "  Dyer ",
            "optionD": "  Montagu ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOne of the most horrific massacres of Indians was carried out by soldiers of the British Raj led by General Reginald Dyer, who opened fire on a gathering of unarmed men, women and children at Jallianwala Bagh in Amritsar. ",
            "keyString": "606845s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statements is not correct? According to Pitt's India Act the Board of Control would consist of",
            "optionA": "  The Chancellor of the Exchequer ",
            "optionB": "  Secretary of State for India ",
            "optionC": "  Four Privy Councillors ",
            "optionD": "  The Governor-General ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFor the purpose of Joint Government, a Board of Commissioners for the Affairs of India called Board of Control was created. This board was made of six people viz. the Chancellor of the Exchequer, the Secretary of State, and four Privy Councillors nominated by the King. The Secretary of the State was entitled as the President of the Board of Control. ",
            "keyString": "607200s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "After reading Thomas Paine's famous book __________Jyotirao was greatly influenced by his ideas",
            "optionA": "  The Rights of Man ",
            "optionB": "  Prince ",
            "optionC": "  Utopia ",
            "optionD": "  Advaitha Deepika ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1848, aged 23, Phule visited the first girls' school in Ahmadnagar, run by Christian missionaries. It was also in 1848 that he read Thomas Paine's book Rights of Man and developed a keen sense of social justice. He realised that lower castes and women were at a disadvantage in Indian society, and also that education of these sections was vital to their emancipation. ",
            "keyString": "607704s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who played Socrates to the first generation of the English educated young men of Bengal",
            "optionA": "  Swami Vivekananda ",
            "optionB": "  Rai Narain Bose ",
            "optionC": "  Henry Vivian Derozio ",
            "optionD": "  Drinkwater Bethun ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHenry Louis Vivian Derozio (18 April 1809 \u2013 26 December 1831) was an Indian poet and assistant headmaster of Hindu College, Kolkata, a radical thinker and one of the first Indian educators to disseminate western learning and science among the young men of Bengal. He played Socrates to the first generation of the English educated young men of Bengal.",
            "keyString": "709459s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bal Gangadhar Tilak was given the epithet of Lokmanya during",
            "optionA": "  His imprisonment in 1908 ",
            "optionB": "  Home Rule Movement ",
            "optionC": "  Revolutionary Movement ",
            "optionD": "  Swadeshi Movement ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe name of Tilak became household names during Home rule movement and this let him earn the epithet Lokmanya. Home Rule League was set up in April 1916 by Bal Gangadhar Tilak. ",
            "keyString": "709959s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bal Gangadhar Tilak earned the epithet of Lokmanya during",
            "optionA": "  his trial in 1907-08 ",
            "optionB": "  the Lucknow pact of 1916 ",
            "optionC": "  the Home Rule Movement ",
            "optionD": "  the Congress Session in 1917 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBal Gangadhar Tilak earned the epithet of Lokmanya during the Home Rule Movement. ",
            "keyString": "710386s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the founder of Swatantra Party?",
            "optionA": "  ",
            "optionB": " G. Tilak ",
            "optionC": "  Dadabhai Naoroji ",
            "optionD": "  Gopal Krishna Gokhale ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter parting away from Congress in 1957, C.Rajagopalachari founded Swatantra Party (Classical Liberal Political Party in 1959). ",
            "keyString": "710798s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the first Indian civil servant?",
            "optionA": "  Motilal Nehru ",
            "optionB": "  S N Banerjee ",
            "optionC": "  C R Das ",
            "optionD": "  Bhagat Singh ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSir Surendranath Banerjee (10 November 1848 \u2013 6 August 1925) was one of the earliest Indian political leaders during the British Raj. He founded the Indian National Association, through which he led two sessions of the Indian National Conference in 1883 and 1885, along with Anandamohan Bose. He was the first Indian civil servant. ",
            "keyString": "711213s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Governor-General was given power to issue ordinances by the act of",
            "optionA": "  1858 ",
            "optionB": "  1861 ",
            "optionC": "  1860 ",
            "optionD": "  1871 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Governor-General was given power to issue ordinances by the act of 1861. ",
            "keyString": "797775s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where was the Royal Durbar Held on November 1st, 1858 to issue to Queen's proclamation?",
            "optionA": "  Lucknow ",
            "optionB": "  Ahmadabad ",
            "optionC": "  Delhi ",
            "optionD": "  Allahabad ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn November 1, 1858, a grand Darbar was held at Allahabad. Here Lord Canning sent forth the royal proclamation which announced that the queen had assumed the government of India. This proclamation declared the future policy of the British Rule in India.",
            "keyString": "798036s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Pakistan panacea was sponsored by",
            "optionA": "  Azad Kalam ",
            "optionB": "  Jinnah ",
            "optionC": "  Md Iqbal ",
            "optionD": "  Liyakat All Khan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Pakistan panacea was sponsored by Md Iqbal. ",
            "keyString": "798292s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Krishnamohan started the __________ in 1831",
            "optionA": "  Enquirer ",
            "optionB": "  Hindu Pioneer ",
            "optionC": "  Quill ",
            "optionD": "  Bengal Spectator ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKrishnamohan Banerjee joined the newly founded Hindu College with a scholarship. In 1831, the religious-reformer-and-litterateur started publishing The Inquirer. ",
            "keyString": "798482s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "According to the provisions of the Regulating Act the Supreme Court in Bengal consisted of the Chief Justice and",
            "optionA": "  Five Judges ",
            "optionB": "  Two Judges ",
            "optionC": "  Six Judges ",
            "optionD": "  Three Judges ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to the provisions of the regulating act the supreme court in Bengal consisted of the chief justice and Three Judges. ",
            "keyString": "804827s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who started the journal 'New India'?",
            "optionA": "  ",
            "optionB": " W. Leadbeater ",
            "optionC": "  Annie Besant ",
            "optionD": "  Ram Mohun Roy ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNew India was a newspaper founded as a means to spread news related to the Indian freedom struggle, and as a means to vocalize the views of its founder, the freedom fighter Dr. Annie Besant, through her editorials. ",
            "keyString": "893127s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Ghadar Party took the name Ghadar from",
            "optionA": "  the Revolt of 1857 ",
            "optionB": "  its objective to wage another revolt ",
            "optionC": "  a weekly paper Ghadar published in commemoration of the Revolt of 1857 ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Ghadar party took the name ghadar froma weekly paper Ghadar published in commemoration of the Revolt of 1857. ",
            "keyString": "893193s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who of the following was associated with the publication of a large number of weeklies and dailies such as Hindustan, Indian Union, Leader, Maryada, Kissan, Abhudaya etc.?",
            "optionA": "  Motilal Nehru ",
            "optionB": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionC": "  Madan Mohan Malaviya ",
            "optionD": "  Ganesh Shankar Vidyarthi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGanesh Shankar Vidyarthi was associated with the publication of a large number of weeklies and dailies such as Hindustan, Indian Union, Leader, Maryada, Kissan, Abhudaya etc. ",
            "keyString": "894283s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first truly revolutionary organisation in Bengal was",
            "optionA": "  Anusilan Samiti ",
            "optionB": "  Yugantar ",
            "optionC": "  Abhinava Bharata ",
            "optionD": "  Abhinava Bharat Society ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnushilan Samiti was a Bengali Indian organisation that existed in the first quarter of the twentieth century, and propounded revolutionary violence as the means for ending British rule in India. ",
            "keyString": "894381s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Brahmavidya Panchakam is a Sanskrit work of __________",
            "optionA": "  Sree Narayana Guru ",
            "optionB": "  Chattambi Swamikal ",
            "optionC": "  K. Madhvan Nair ",
            "optionD": "  Dr. Palpu ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBrahmavidya Panchakam is a Sanskrit work of Sree Narayana Guru. ",
            "keyString": "894734s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Shuja-ud-Daulah was the Nawab of",
            "optionA": "  Rampur ",
            "optionB": "  Arcot ",
            "optionC": "  Awadh ",
            "optionD": "  Surat ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShuja-ud-Daulah was the Subedar Nawab of Oudh from 5 October 1754 to 26 January 1775. ",
            "keyString": "965964s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following had observed, upon Gandhi's assassination. \"None will believe that a man like this body and soul ever walked on this earth\"?",
            "optionA": "  Bertrand Russel ",
            "optionB": "  Nelson Mandela ",
            "optionC": "  Albert Einstein ",
            "optionD": "  Leo Tolstoy ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAlbert Einstein had observed, upon Gandhi's assassination. \"None will believe that a man like this body and soul ever walked on this earth\". ",
            "keyString": "967280s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the Governor-General when Pindaris had created havoc in Central India by indulging in large-scale looting?",
            "optionA": "  Lord William Bentinck ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Hastings ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Cornwallis ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Wellesley ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Hastings was determined to suppress the Pindaris. For this, he gathered a large army of 113,000 men and 300 guns and attacked the Pindaris from four sides. He himself took the command of the force from North side while Sir Thomas Hislop commanded the force from the South. By 1818, the Pindaris were completely suppressed and all their bands were disintegrated. By 1824, the menace of Pindaris came to an end. ",
            "keyString": "968368s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Maulana Abul Kalam Azad was a scholar in",
            "optionA": "  Persian ",
            "optionB": "  Arabic ",
            "optionC": "  Sanskrit ",
            "optionD": "  French ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMaulana Sayyid Abul Kalam Ghulam Muhiyuddin Ahmed bin Khairuddin Al-Hussaini (11 November 1888 \u2013 22 February 1958) was an Indian scholar, activist and a senior leader of the Indian National Congress during the Indian independence movement. ",
            "keyString": "969174s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who founded the Ramakrishna Mission?",
            "optionA": "  Derozio ",
            "optionB": "  Satkari Datta ",
            "optionC": "  Swami Vivekananda ",
            "optionD": "  Sri Ramakrishna Parama Hamsar ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t\"For one's own salvation and for the welfare of the world\" This is the motto of the Ramakrishna Mission which was founded by Swami Vivekananda.",
            "keyString": "969865s14m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the oldest trade Union organisation in India?",
            "optionA": "  Indian National Trade Union Cogress (INTUC) ",
            "optionB": "  Centre of Indian Trade Unions (CITU) ",
            "optionC": "  All India Trade Union Congress (AITUC) ",
            "optionD": "  Bharatiya Mazdoor Sangh (BMS) ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll India Trade Union Congress (AITUC) is the oldest trade union federation in India and one of the five largest. It was founded on 31st october 1920 in Bombay by Lala Lajpat Rai, Joseph Baptista, First president- Lala Lajpat Rai. First General Secretary- Diwan Chaman Lal. ",
            "keyString": "57188s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In the famous Kakori Conspiracy Case (August 1925) which of the following revolutionaries was not hanged?",
            "optionA": "  Ram Prasad Bismil ",
            "optionB": "  Asafaqulla Khan ",
            "optionC": "  Snehlata ",
            "optionD": "  Suhasini Sarkar ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Kakori Conspiracy (or Kakori train robbery or Kakori Case) was a train robbery that took place between Kakori and, near Lucknow, on 9 August 1925 during the Indian Independence Movement against the British Indian Government. The robbery was organised by Hindustan Republican Association. The robbery was conceived by Ram Prasad Bismil and Ashfaqullah Khan who belonged to the HRA, which later became the Hindustan Socialist Republican Association. Snehlata was not hanged. ",
            "keyString": "58135s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Infanticide was completely banned by the",
            "optionA": "  Bengal Regulation Act XVII of 1829 ",
            "optionB": "  Sharda Act, 1930 ",
            "optionC": "  Bengal Regulation Act XXI of 1795 ",
            "optionD": "  Minto-Morley reforms ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBengal Regulation Act XXI of 1795 completely banned infanticide in India. The Anglicist-Orientalist controversy was related to the education system in India. ",
            "keyString": "59473s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The revolutionary who died of a 64 days hunger strike was",
            "optionA": "  Sukh Dev ",
            "optionB": "  Batukeshwar Dutt ",
            "optionC": "  Jatin Das ",
            "optionD": "  Raj Guru ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJatindra Nath Das, also known as Jatin Das, was a revolutionary and Independence activist. He embraced death in Lahore jail after fasting for 63 days on this day, September 13, in the year 1929, aged 24 years. ",
            "keyString": "60345s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first Congress and nationalist leader to face repeated imprisonment was",
            "optionA": "  Pheroze Shah Mehta ",
            "optionB": "  Gopal Krishna Gokhale ",
            "optionC": "  Dadabhai Naoroji ",
            "optionD": "  BG Tilak ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first Congress and nationalist leader to face repeated imprisonment was BG Tilak. ",
            "keyString": "61114s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Hevarappathinkangal is a Tamil work of __________",
            "optionA": "  Chattambi Swamikal ",
            "optionB": "  Sree Narayana Guru ",
            "optionC": "  K. Ayyappan ",
            "optionD": "  K. madhvan Nair ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHevarappathinkangal is a Tamil work of Sree Narayana Guru. ",
            "keyString": "204080s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sati was prohibited by",
            "optionA": "  Warren Hastings ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Wellesley ",
            "optionC": "  Lord William Bentinck ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Dalhousie ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGovernor General Lord William Bentinck passed the Bengal Sati Regalation Act, 1829, which declared the Practice of Sati as punishable offence. ",
            "keyString": "205130s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who shot dead John Saunders on 17th December 1928?",
            "optionA": "  Bhagat Singh ",
            "optionB": "  Mangal Pandey ",
            "optionC": "  Sukhdev ",
            "optionD": "  Bipin Chandra Pal ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLala Lajpat Rai was lathi charged and died when he was opposing the Simmon commission in Lahore. Bhagat Singh and other shot the Police superintendent John Saunders who was responsible for lathi charge. ",
            "keyString": "206362s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who represented Indian women in The Second Round Table Conference?",
            "optionA": "  Aruna Asaf Ali ",
            "optionB": "  Sucheta Kripalani ",
            "optionC": "  Sarojini Naidu ",
            "optionD": "  Kalpana Joshi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe second Round Table conference started onSeptember 7, 1931. M.K.Gandhi represented Indian national Congress and Sarojini Naidu represented Indian women. ",
            "keyString": "206950s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When did M. K. Gandhi participated in the Second Round Table Conference?",
            "optionA": "  Signing the Gandhi-Irwin Pact of March, 1931 ",
            "optionB": "  Getting assurance from the Muslim League that it would not oppose his claim to represent the whole of India ",
            "optionC": "  Fruitful talks with Sapru ",
            "optionD": "  Receiving assurances that independence was fast coming ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn August 29, 1931, Gandhi sailed for England in theSS Rajputana to attend the Second Round Table Conference, He went as the solerepresentative of the Indian National Congress. ",
            "keyString": "207472s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Identify the body among the following that was not founded by Dr. B. R. Ambedkar?",
            "optionA": "  Samaj Samato Sangh ",
            "optionB": "  People's Education Society ",
            "optionC": "  Deccan Education Society ",
            "optionD": "  Depressed Classes Institute ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1880 Vishnushastri Chiplunkar and Lokmanya Bal Gangadhar Tilak established the New English School, one of the first native-run schools offering Western education in Pune. In 1884 they created the Deccan Education Society with Gopal Ganesh Agarkar, Mahadev Ballal Namjoshi, V. S. Apte. ",
            "keyString": "350170s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first Indian national leader who began building, organizing and promoting the freedom struggle was",
            "optionA": "  Dadabhai Naoroji ",
            "optionB": "  Lala Lajpat Rai ",
            "optionC": "  Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "optionD": "  Gopal Krishna Gokhale ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDadabhai Naoroji was belonged to the Moderates of the Indian National Congress. He was a very strong influence for the other freedom fighters of the Indian independence movement and mentored leaders like Gopal Krishna Gokhale and Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi among the many. ",
            "keyString": "350243s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Of the following who did not find a place in the Legislative Council as per the Act of 1853?",
            "optionA": "  The Governor-General ",
            "optionB": "  Additional Members ",
            "optionC": "  The Commander-in-Chief ",
            "optionD": "  The Lieutenant Governor ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Charter act of 1853 provided for appointment of a separate Governor for the Presidency of Bengal, distinct from the Governor General. However, the court of Directors and the Board of Control were authorized to appoint a lieutenant governor, till the appointment of a Governor was made. Please note that the Lieutenant governor was appointed in 1854, but no Governor was appointed for Bengal till 1912. ",
            "keyString": "350263s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Author of 'Culture ideology Hegemony Intellectual and Social consciousness in Colonial India' is",
            "optionA": "  K. N. Ganesh ",
            "optionB": "  K. N. Panikkar ",
            "optionC": "  R. ",
            "optionD": " Majumdar ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tK. N. Panikkar is Vice-Chancellor of Sree Sankaracharya University of Sanskrit, Kerala. He is the author of 'Culture ideology Hegemony Intellectual and Social consciousness in Colonial India'. ",
            "keyString": "350279s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following was not one of the recommendations of the Cabinet Minion (1946) about the Constitution of India?",
            "optionA": "  There should be a Union of India embracing both British India and the States ",
            "optionB": "  The Muslim majority provinces should be separately constituted into a Union of Pakistan ",
            "optionC": "  The provinces should enjoy autonomy for all subjects and should be free to form groups ",
            "optionD": "  Three basic Groups proposed by the Mission were Group A (Hindumajority Provinces) Group B (Muslim-majority Provinces) and Group C (Bengal and Assam) ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Muslim majority provinces should be separately constituted into a Union of Pakistan was not one of the recommendations of the Cabinet Minion (1946) about the Constitution of India. ",
            "keyString": "350294s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following has been given honorary status among the seven wonders of the modern world?",
            "optionA": "  Taj Mahal ",
            "optionB": "  Great Pyramid of Giza ",
            "optionC": "  Petra ",
            "optionD": "  Colosseum ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGreat Pyramid of Giza has been given honorary status. Seven wonders of the modern world are Chicken Itza- Mexico, Christ Redeemer- Brazil,The Great Wall- China, Machu Picchu- Peru, Petra- Jordan, The Roman Colosseum- Italy, The Taj Mahal- India. ",
            "keyString": "497158s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Whose speeches at the World's Parliament of Religions held in September 1893 made him famous as an 'orator by divine right' and as a 'Messenger of Indian wisdom to the Western world'",
            "optionA": "  Swami Vivekananda  ",
            "optionB": "  Sri Ramakrishna  ",
            "optionC": "  Chandra Sekhar Deb  ",
            "optionD": "  Shyama Charan Sen ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSwami Vivekananda, one of the greatest sons of India is always remembered all over the world for his address at the World\u2019s Parliament of Religions held at Chicago in 1893, which made the western intelligentsia to turnaround to recognise the great culture and tradition India had since time immemorial. His speeches at the World\u2019s Parliament of Religions made him famous as an \u2018orator by divine right\u2019 and as a \u2018Messenger of Indian wisdom to the Western world\u2019. After the Parliament, he spent nearly three and a half years, spreading Vedanta philosophy as taught and practised by Sri Ramakrishna Paramhans, mostly in the eastern parts of USA and London. ",
            "keyString": "497720s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Muslim League advocated a separate Muslim State",
            "optionA": "  At its birth in 1906 ",
            "optionB": "  During the Khilafat Movement ",
            "optionC": "  In 1930, when it opposed the Civil Disobedience\nMovement ",
            "optionD": "  At the Lahore Session of 1940 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAt the Lahore Session of 1940 Muslim League advocated a separate Muslim State, Pakistan. The word Pakistan was given by Chaudhary Rehmat Ali. (A student of Cambridge University). ",
            "keyString": "497997s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Congress ministries gave up office in October 1939 over the issue of",
            "optionA": "  constant interference by Governors in day-to-day administration ",
            "optionB": "  propaganda of the Muslim League against the Congress ",
            "optionC": "  India having been unwillingly dragged into the Second World War ",
            "optionD": "  failure of the British to define their war aims ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Congress ministries gave up office in October 1939 over the issue of failure of the British to define their war aims. ",
            "keyString": "498221s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What had the Sir Charles Wood Despatch of 1854 primarily dealt with?",
            "optionA": "  Social reforms ",
            "optionB": "  Administrative reforms ",
            "optionC": "  Educational reforms ",
            "optionD": "  Political consolidation ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCharles Wood was a British Liberal politician and Member of Parliament. He served as Chancellor of the Exchequer from 1846 to 1852. Later he became the President of the Board of Control of the East India Company. In 1854 he sent the \u201cWood's despatch\u201d to the Governor General Lord Dalhousie. ",
            "keyString": "498427s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following leaders was one of the founding member of the Muslim League?",
            "optionA": "  Muhammad Ali Jinnah ",
            "optionB": "  Shaukat Ali ",
            "optionC": "  Nawab Salimullah ",
            "optionD": "  Aga Khan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNawab Sir Khwaja Salimullah Bahadur GCIE KCSI (1871\u20131915) was the fourth Nawab of Dhaka and one of the leading Muslim politicians during the British Raj. In 1906, the Muslim League was officially founded at the educational conference held in Dhaka. The convention was held at Ahsan Manzil, the official residence of the Dhaka Nawab Family.",
            "keyString": "618715s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Gandhi-Irwin Pact was signed on 5th March __________",
            "optionA": "  1928 ",
            "optionB": "  1930 ",
            "optionC": "  1931 ",
            "optionD": "  1935 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Gandhi-Irwin Pact was a political agreement signed by Mahatma Gandhi and Lord Irwin, the then Viceroy of India, on 5 March 1931 before the second Round Table Conference in London. ",
            "keyString": "618919s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The 19th Century reawakening in India was confined to the",
            "optionA": "  Priestly class ",
            "optionB": "  Upper middle class ",
            "optionC": "  Rich peasantry ",
            "optionD": "  Urban Landlords ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe 19th Century reawakening in India was confined to the Upper middle class. ",
            "keyString": "619138s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following reformer associated with the passing of the Widow Remarriage Act?",
            "optionA": "  Swami Vivekananda ",
            "optionB": "  Raja Rammohan Roy ",
            "optionC": "  Ishwar Chandra Vidyasagar ",
            "optionD": "  Ramakrishna Paramahansa ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBecause of Ishwar Chandra Vidyasagar's contribution, the Widow Remarriage Act was passed in 1856 making the marriage of widows legal. Ishwar Chandra Vidyasagar worked towards providing education to women. He opened and ran many schools for girls at his own expense. ",
            "keyString": "619316s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who declared that he would talk of religion only when he succeeded in removing poverty and misery from the country, for religion could not appease hunger?",
            "optionA": "  Swami Vivekananda ",
            "optionB": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionC": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionD": "  Dadabhai Naoroji ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSwami Vivekananda declared that he would talk of religion only when he succeeded in removing poverty and misery from the country, for religion could not appease hunger. ",
            "keyString": "619492s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the first to use the term 'Adivasi' to refer to the tribal people?",
            "optionA": "  Jyotiba Phule ",
            "optionB": "  Thakkar Bappa ",
            "optionC": "  M N Srinivas ",
            "optionD": "  B R Ambedkar ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThakkar Bappa was the first to use the term 'Adivasi' to refer to the tribal people. ",
            "keyString": "868443s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Writing Social History is the book of __________",
            "optionA": "  Ania Loomba ",
            "optionB": "  Sumit Sarkar ",
            "optionC": "  Cohn Bernard ",
            "optionD": "  Ranajith Guha ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWriting Social History is the book of Sumit Sarkar. ",
            "keyString": "868686s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following books were written by Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru?\nI. Discovery of India\nII. Outline of History\nIII. Glimpses of World History\nIV. A Study of History",
            "optionA": "  I & IV ",
            "optionB": "  II & IV ",
            "optionC": "  I & III ",
            "optionD": "  I, II, III & IV ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Discovery of India and Glimpses of World History were written by Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru. ",
            "keyString": "868960s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Montagu who toured in India in 1918 was a",
            "optionA": "  Member of Privy Council ",
            "optionB": "  Member of Viceroy's Council ",
            "optionC": "  Secretary of State for India ",
            "optionD": "  Viceroy of India ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMontagu who toured in India in 1918 was a Secretary of State for India. ",
            "keyString": "869132s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Go back to Vedas\" This call  is given by",
            "optionA": "  Ramakrishna Paramhansa ",
            "optionB": "  Vivekananda ",
            "optionC": "  Jyotiba Phule ",
            "optionD": "  Dayanand Saraswati ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSwami Dayanand Saraswati gave the slogan 'Go back to Vedas'. He was the founder of Arya Samaj, a Hindu reform movements of the vedic tradition. ",
            "keyString": "869292s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The battle of Plassey was fought between",
            "optionA": "  East India Company and Ahmad Shah ",
            "optionB": "  East India Company and Tipu Sultan ",
            "optionC": "  East India Company and Sirajuddaulla ",
            "optionD": "  East India Company and Anwaruddin ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe battle of Plassey was fought between East India Company and Nawab of Bengal (Sirajud Daulla) on 23rd june 1757. Nawab of Bengal was defeated by Robert Clive (Commander cum Govemor of EIC). ",
            "keyString": "944037s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Jyotiba Phule was one of the prominent __________ of the 19th century India",
            "optionA": "  Scientists ",
            "optionB": "  Politicians ",
            "optionC": "  Economists ",
            "optionD": "  Social reformers ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJyotirao 'Jyotiba' Govindrao Phule was a prominent social reformer and thinker of the nineteenth century India. He led the movement against the prevailing caste-restrictions in India. He revolted against the domination of the Brahmins and struggled for the rights of peasants and other low-caste people. ",
            "keyString": "944228s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the National leader who wrote History of India on the walls of the Andaman Cellular Jail?",
            "optionA": "  Nandalal Bose ",
            "optionB": "  Ambedkar ",
            "optionC": "  Vir Savarkar ",
            "optionD": "  Jyotiba Phule ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVir Savarkar was great national leader, he wrote history of Indian on walls of Andaman Cellular jail.",
            "keyString": "944390s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who designated the administrative head of the district as Collector?",
            "optionA": "  Warren Hastings ",
            "optionB": "  Cornwallis ",
            "optionC": "  MacPherson ",
            "optionD": "  Clive ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMacPherson designated the administrative head of the district as Collector. ",
            "keyString": "944714s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who had set up the Anti-Untouchability League for the eradication of the evil of untouchability?",
            "optionA": "  Jagjivan Ram ",
            "optionB": "  Dr. ",
            "optionC": " R. Ambedkar ",
            "optionD": "  Acharya Kripalani ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe scrapping of separate electorates was only the beginning of the end of untouchability. Under Gandhi\u2019s inspiration, while he was still in prison, a new organization, Harijan Sevak Sangh was founded to combat untouchability and a new weekly paper, the Harijan, was started. Harijan means \"children of God\"; it was Gandhi\u2019s name for the \"untouchables\". ",
            "keyString": "944932s15m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The decline of Indian Handicrafts industry in the 19th century was attributed to",
            "optionA": "  Competition from British manufacturing\nindustries only ",
            "optionB": "  Disappearance of Indian Princely Courts only ",
            "optionC": "  Establishment of alien rule only ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above are responsible for the decline of Indian Handicraf Industry in 19th century. ",
            "keyString": "81316s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who attended the Imperial Durbar of 1877 dressed in hand-spun Khadi?",
            "optionA": "  M.K. Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "optionC": "  Bipin Chandra Pal ",
            "optionD": "  Ganesh Vasudev Joshi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tImperial Durbar of 1877 which was first among the three Delhi Darbars, was organised during the Viceroyalty of Lord Lytton. Queen Victoria was conferred with the title of \"Kesar-e-hind\" in this darbar. It was Ganesh Vasudev Joshi who attended this Darbar dressed in hand-Spun Khadi. ",
            "keyString": "81826s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Government of India Act of 1935 borrowed its preamble from",
            "optionA": "  The Constitution of the USA ",
            "optionB": "  The Constitution of Australia ",
            "optionC": "  From the Government of India Act of 1919 ",
            "optionD": "  From Pitt's India Act ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Government of India Act of 1935 borrowed its preamble from the Government of India Act of 1919. ",
            "keyString": "82639s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statements about the Government of India Act of 1935 is not correct?",
            "optionA": "  Diarchy was established in the provinces ",
            "optionB": "  The Viceroy was given special powers ",
            "optionC": "  The federal executive was to consist of the Viceroy, councillors and the ministers ",
            "optionD": "  The federal legislature was to be bicameral ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDyarchy was introduced as a constitutional reform by Edwin Samuel Montagu (secretary of state for India, 1917\u201322) and Lord Chelmsford (viceroy of India, 1916\u201321). ",
            "keyString": "83000s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statements is not correct? The materials for the Government of India Act of 1935 were drawn from",
            "optionA": "  The Simon Commission Report ",
            "optionB": "  The Nehru Committee Report ",
            "optionC": "  The White Paper issued by the British Government ",
            "optionD": "  Morley-Minto Reforms ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indian Councils Act 1909, commonly known as the Morley-Minto Reforms, was an Act of the Parliament of the United Kingdom that brought about a limited increase in the involvement of Indians in the governance of British India. ",
            "keyString": "83233s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where did the so-called 'Black Hole Tragedy' take place ?",
            "optionA": "  Daccan ",
            "optionB": "  Monghyr ",
            "optionC": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionD": "  Murshidabad ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Black Hole tragedy took place at Fort William in Calcutta in the year 1756. The Background: The Nawab of Bengal gave The East India Company certain special rights as traders in Calcutta and allowed them to build a small fort (the Company named it Fort William) and maintain a small army. ",
            "keyString": "214251s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mahatma Gandhi began his political activities in India first from",
            "optionA": "  Dandi ",
            "optionB": "  Kheda ",
            "optionC": "  Sabarmati ",
            "optionD": "  Champaran ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1917 on the invitation of Raj Kumar Shukla, Gandhi ji visited champaran village in Bihar, were 'Tinkathiya' system was prevalent. In this system farmers were forced to grow Indigo on the 3/20th part of land. Gandhiji organized Champaran Satyagraha to protest against this system. ",
            "keyString": "214440s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "According to Dadabhai Naoroji 'Swaraj' means",
            "optionA": "  Complete independence ",
            "optionB": "  Self government ",
            "optionC": "  Economic independence ",
            "optionD": "  Political independence ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDadabhai Naoroji, known as Grand old Man of India, was a prominent leader of Indian National Congress. The demand for Swaraj was first raised by Dadabhai Naoroji in Calcutta Session of India National Congress in 1906. According to him 'Swaraj' means self Govemment or 'self rule'. ",
            "keyString": "214600s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Rohelas helped the Afghan invaders in 1761 in the Battle of",
            "optionA": "  Bauxar ",
            "optionB": "  Plassey ",
            "optionC": "  Arcot ",
            "optionD": "  Panipat ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Third Battle of Panipat took place on 14 January 1761 at Panipat, about 60 miles (97 km) north of Delhi, between a northern expeditionary force of the Maratha Empire and invading forces of the King of Afghanistan, Ahmad Shah Abdali, supported by two Indian allies\u2014the Rohillas Najib-ud-daulah, Afghans of the Doab region and Shuja-ud-Daula-the Nawab of Awadh. ",
            "keyString": "214757s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The landmarks or Dalhousie's administration did not include",
            "optionA": "  Indian Railways ",
            "optionB": "  English as the medium of instruction ",
            "optionC": "  Public works department ",
            "optionD": "  Telegraph ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe landmarks of Dalhousie's administration did not include English as the medium of instruction. ",
            "keyString": "214909s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first elected Indian President of the Legislative Assembly was",
            "optionA": "  Motilal Nehru ",
            "optionB": "  Rangachariar ",
            "optionC": "  CR Das ",
            "optionD": "  VJ Patel ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVithalbhai Patel was elected to the Central Legislative Assembly as one of the candidates of the Congress Swarajya Dal and in 1925 as the first Indian President of the House where he created history. ",
            "keyString": "312621s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "__________ is remembered as the 'Grand old man of India'",
            "optionA": "  Ranade ",
            "optionB": "  Dadabhai Naoroji ",
            "optionC": "  Pulinbehari Sarkar ",
            "optionD": "  Amaresh Chakravarty ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDadabhai Naoroji (4 September 1825 \u2013 30 June 1917), known as the Grand Old Man of India, was a Parsi intellectual, educator, cotton trader, and an early Indian political and social leader. ",
            "keyString": "446453s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "One Caste One Religion, One God for Man is the teaching of __________",
            "optionA": "  Rajaram Mohan Roy ",
            "optionB": "  Chattambi Swamikal ",
            "optionC": "  ",
            "optionD": " Kesavan ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSri Narayana Guru preached the doctrine of 'One caste, One religion, One God.' Its worth note that one of his athiest disciples, Sahadaran Ayyapan, changed into 'no religion, no caste and no God for mankind. ",
            "keyString": "446524s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The passage of the Rowlatt Act had been almost immediately followed by the",
            "optionA": "  Minto-Morley Reforms ",
            "optionB": "  Khilafat Movement ",
            "optionC": "  Jallianwala Bagh Massacre ",
            "optionD": "  Chauri-Chaura Incident ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Rowlatt Act came into effect in March 1919. The army was called into Punjab, and on 13 April people from neighbouring villages gathered for Baisakhi Day celebrations and to protest against deportion of two important Indian leaders in Amritsar, which led to the infamous Jallianwala Bagh massacre of 1919. ",
            "keyString": "446540s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1904 the then Maharaja  of . . . . . . exempted Narayana Guru from personal appearances in court, an honour recognizing the Guru as a distinguished living personality",
            "optionA": "  Kannur ",
            "optionB": "  Thalassery ",
            "optionC": "  Travancore ",
            "optionD": "  Cochi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1904 the then Maharajah of Travancore exempted Narayana Guru from personal appearances in court, an honour recognizing the Guru as a distinguished living personality. ",
            "keyString": "446553s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "All are of one Self-fraternity such being the dictum to avow, in such a light how can we take life and devoid of least pity go on to eat. Who said this?",
            "optionA": "  Tilak ",
            "optionB": "  Chattambi Swamikal ",
            "optionC": "  Rajaram Mohan Roy ",
            "optionD": "  Sree Narayana Guru ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll are of one Self-fraternity such being the dictum to avow, In such a light how can we take life And devoid of least pity go on to eat was said by Sree Narayana Guru. ",
            "keyString": "446568s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following had been a high court judge, an economist, a social reformer, among the founders or the INC, besides being regarded by A O Hume as his political guru?",
            "optionA": "  Surendranath Banerjee ",
            "optionB": "  Pheroze Shah Mehta ",
            "optionC": "  Mahadev Gobind Ranade ",
            "optionD": "  Dadabhai Naoroji ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahadev Gobind Ranade had been a high court judge, an economist, a social reformer, among the founders or the INC, besides being regarded by A O Hume as his political guru. ",
            "keyString": "546543s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "__________co-edited 'the National Reformer' with Charles Bradlaugh and wrote many political and free-thought books and pamphlets from 1874-88",
            "optionA": "  W. T. Stead ",
            "optionB": "  S. N. Banerjee ",
            "optionC": "  H. P. Blavatsky ",
            "optionD": "  Annie Besant ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnnie Besant co-edited 'the National Reformer' with Charles Bradlaugh and wrote many political and free-thought books and pamphlets from 1874-88. ",
            "keyString": "546578s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following is correctly matched?",
            "optionA": "  Non-Cooperation Movement  -  Surendra Nath\nBanerjee ",
            "optionB": "  Swadeshi Movement  -  Rabindra Nath Tagore ",
            "optionC": "  Indian National Army  - Subhash Chandra Bose ",
            "optionD": "  Swaraj Party  -  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian National Army - Subhash Chandra Bose is correctly matched. ",
            "keyString": "546592s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is correctly matched?",
            "optionA": "  Third Battle of Panipat: 1764 ",
            "optionB": "  Regulating Act: 1773 ",
            "optionC": "  Pitt's India Act: 1761 ",
            "optionD": "  Treaty of Allahabad: 1784 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Regulating Act 1773 was an Act of the Parliament of Great Britain intended to overhaul the management of the East India Company's rule in India. ",
            "keyString": "546605s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Home Rule League was started by",
            "optionA": "  M. K. Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  ",
            "optionC": " G. Tilak ",
            "optionD": "  Ranade ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHome Rule movement was a movement in British India on the lines of Irish Home rule movement. It started in India under the leadership of Annie besant and B.G Tilak. Firstly Home Rule established in India by B.G Tilak at Belgam (Karnataka) and later by Annie Besant at Adyar in 1916. ",
            "keyString": "546616s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Objective of Non-alignment of India's foreign policy means",
            "optionA": "  To stand in isolation from world affairs ",
            "optionB": "  To judge every international issue on its own merit ",
            "optionC": "  To interfere in the internal matters of a country ",
            "optionD": "  Not to help any country ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Objective of Non-alignment of India's foreign policy means to judge every international issue on its own merit. ",
            "keyString": "661810s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Servants of India Society was founded in",
            "optionA": "  England ",
            "optionB": "  India ",
            "optionC": "  America ",
            "optionD": "  Burma ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Servants of India Society was formed in Pune, Maharashtra, India on June 12, 1905 by Gopal Krishna Gokhale, who left the Deccan Education Society to form this association. ",
            "keyString": "661843s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Communist Party of India was founded in 1921 by",
            "optionA": "  Hiren Mukherjee ",
            "optionB": "  SM Joshi ",
            "optionC": "  MN Roy ",
            "optionD": "  RC Dutt ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Communist Party of India was founded in 1921 by MN Roy. ",
            "keyString": "661857s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement relates the Dadabhai Naoroji's definition of 'Drain of Wealth'?",
            "optionA": "  Those resources of the country were being utilized in the interest of Britain ",
            "optionB": "  That a part of India's national wealth or total annual product was being exported to Britain for which India got no material return ",
            "optionC": "  That the British industrialists were being given an opportunity to invest in India under the protection of the imperial power ",
            "optionD": "  That the British goods were being imported into the country making it poorer day by day ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDadabhai Naoroji's definition of 'Drain of Wealth means that a part of India's national wealth or total annual product was being exported to Britain for which India got no material return. ",
            "keyString": "661869s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1848, an incident took place in his life that later sparked off the dalit-revolution in the Indian society. Jyotirao was invited to attend a wedding of one of his __________friends",
            "optionA": "  Brahmin ",
            "optionB": "  Christian ",
            "optionC": "  Pulaya ",
            "optionD": "  Nayar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1848, an incident took place in his life that later sparked off the dalit-revolution in the Indian society. Jyotirao was invited to attend a wedding of one of his Brahmin friends. ",
            "keyString": "661881s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Simon Commission was boycotted by Indians because",
            "optionA": "  It sought to curb civil liberties of the Indians ",
            "optionB": "  It proposed to partition India ",
            "optionC": "  It was an all-white commission without Indian\nrepresentation ",
            "optionD": "  It proposed measures to contain nationalism ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSimon Commission was boycotted because it was an all - White Commission without Indian representation. All the members of commission were Britishers. The Simon Commission was opposed primarily because it did not have any Indian representation in the assemblage. The government of Britain had appointed this Commission in 1927. The goal of the Simon Commission was to give an account of how the Indian constitution was working. ",
            "keyString": "783726s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Through which principle/device did Mahatma Gandhi strive to bridge economic inequalities?",
            "optionA": "  Abolition of machinery ",
            "optionB": "  Establishment of village industries ",
            "optionC": "  Adoption of non-violence ",
            "optionD": "  Trusteeship theory ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTrusteeship is a socio-economic philosophy that was propounded by Mahatma Gandhi. It provides a means by which the wealthy people would be the trustees of trusts that looked after the welfare of the people in general. This concept was condemned by socialists as being in favor of the landlords, feudal princes and the capitalists, opposed to socialist theories. ",
            "keyString": "783944s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Through which principle or device did Ghandhiji strive to bridge economics inequalities?",
            "optionA": "  Abolition of machinery ",
            "optionB": "  Establishment of village industries ",
            "optionC": "  Trusteeship theory ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGhandhiji postulated the 'Trusteeship theory'. It was a social economic theory based on the principle of \"Transforming the present capitalist order of society into egalitarian one\". ",
            "keyString": "784127s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who had observed that \"Good government was never a good substitute for self-government\"?",
            "optionA": "  Swami Vivekananda ",
            "optionB": "  Ramakrishna Paramahansa ",
            "optionC": "  Swami Dayananda ",
            "optionD": "  Aurobindo Ghose ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSwami Dayananda observed that \"Good government was never a good substitute for self-government\". ",
            "keyString": "784298s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sivagiri pilgrimage was conceived by __________ and T. K. Kittan Writer. It was duly approved by Gurudevan on January, 1928",
            "optionA": "  Vallabhasseri Govindan Vaidyar ",
            "optionB": "  T. K. Madhavan ",
            "optionC": "  Rajaram Mohan Roy ",
            "optionD": "  Govindan Vaidyar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSivagiri pilgrimage was conceived by Vallabhasseri Govindan Vaidyar and T. K. Kittan Writer. It was duly approved by Gurudevan on January, 1928. ",
            "keyString": "784462s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the only Indian to be elected as President of the United Nations General Assembly?",
            "optionA": "  Vijayalakshmi Pandit ",
            "optionB": "  V. K. Krishna Menon ",
            "optionC": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionD": "  Rajeswar Dayal ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVijayalakshmi Pandit was the first woman and only Indian till date to become president of United Nations General Assembly. She was also the member of Constituent Assembly and the first Indian woman to hold a cabinet post in pre-independent India. ",
            "keyString": "866624s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Gandhi wanted to realise 'truth' through",
            "optionA": "  Ahimsa (Non-violence) ",
            "optionB": "  Dharma (Religion) ",
            "optionC": "  Karma (Service) ",
            "optionD": "  Dhyana (Meditation) ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGandhiji always followed the philosphy of non-violence and truth in his movements. ",
            "keyString": "866859s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following leader was associated with the Home Rule League?",
            "optionA": "  ",
            "optionB": " G. Tilak ",
            "optionC": "  G. K. Gokhale ",
            "optionD": "  M. G. Ranade ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBal Gangadhar Tilak founded the first home rule league at the Bombay provincial congress at Belgaum in April,1916. ",
            "keyString": "867053s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1921, Mahatma Gandhi resolved to wear only a loin cloth to propagate home spun cotton to signify",
            "optionA": "  the poverty of the Indian people ",
            "optionB": "  the ruin of India's handloom textiles ",
            "optionC": "  his identification with the Indian people ",
            "optionD": "  his resolve to wear tailored clothes only when India became independent ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1921, Mahatma Gandhi resolved to wear only a loin cloth to propagate home spun cotton to signify his identification with the Indian people. ",
            "keyString": "867232s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following reason compel the leaders of Muslim League to enter in the Interim Government?",
            "optionA": "  The Congress accepted their demand that it would not nominate a non-Muslim League Muslim to the Interim Government ",
            "optionB": "  The Viceroy accepted its stand that it would not join the Constituent Assembly ",
            "optionC": "  The Viceroy had accepted its stand that it would not take steps to rescind the League Council's resolution of July 29 ",
            "optionD": "  The Muslim League wanted to get a foothold to fight for the cherished goal of Pakistan ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Muslim League wanted to get a foothold to fight for the cherished goal of Pakistan was the reason compelled the leaders of Muslim League to enter in the Interim Government. ",
            "keyString": "867417s16m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first national leader to decry the salt tax in the Indian legislature was",
            "optionA": "  G. K. Gokhale ",
            "optionB": "  M. K. Gandhi ",
            "optionC": "  J. L. Nehru ",
            "optionD": "  Netaji S C Bose ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first national leader to decry the salt tax in the Indian legislature was G K Gokhale. ",
            "keyString": "1901s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Communal Representation was for the first time given in the interest of Muslims by",
            "optionA": "  The Indian Council Act of 1909 ",
            "optionB": "  The Government of India Act of 1919 ",
            "optionC": "  The Government of India Act of 1935 ",
            "optionD": "  The Act of 1858 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe principle of communal election was accepted only in the case of Muslims and was implemented by the Regulations made under the 1909 Act. This was the outcome of unswerving and steadfast demands by Muslims who expressed serious concerns that a first past the post electoral system, like that of Britain, would leave them permanently subject to Hindu majority rule. The Act of 1909 stipulated, as demanded by the Muslim leadership that only Muslims should vote for candidates for the Muslim seats (\u2018separate electorates\u2019). ",
            "keyString": "2155s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indian National Army (Azad Hind Fauj) fought in the Second World War against",
            "optionA": "  Germany ",
            "optionB": "  Japan ",
            "optionC": "  Italy ",
            "optionD": "  Great Britain ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian National Army in 1942 - 45 fought against GreatBritain along with Japanese during second world war-II. ",
            "keyString": "6356s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Portuguese built their first fort on India soil in the territory of the Raja of",
            "optionA": "  Calicut ",
            "optionB": "  Cochin ",
            "optionC": "  Daman ",
            "optionD": "  Bijapur ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Raja of Cochin even permitted them to build factory and allowed Portugues to stay in Cochin. ",
            "keyString": "6782s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Permanent Revenue settlement of Bengal was introduced by",
            "optionA": "  Clive ",
            "optionB": "  Hastings ",
            "optionC": "  Wellesley ",
            "optionD": "  Cornwallis ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Permanent Settlement (Permanent Settlement of Bengal) was introduced by Lord Cornwallis in 1793. According to this settlement Landlords agreed to have perpetual and hereditary rights over the land, as long as they pay fixed revenue to the British Government. ",
            "keyString": "7008s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Act of __________ had introduced the system of separate electorates",
            "optionA": "  1874 ",
            "optionB": "  1893 ",
            "optionC": "  1909 ",
            "optionD": "  1926 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian Councils Act of 1909, also called Morley-Minto Reforms, series of reform measures enacted in 1909 by the British Parliament, the main component of which directly introduced the elective principle to membership in the imperial and local legislative councils in India. ",
            "keyString": "163478s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following ruler was the first Indian native ruler to accept the system of Subsidiary Alliance?",
            "optionA": "  Scindia of Gwalior ",
            "optionB": "  Nizam of Hyderabad ",
            "optionC": "  Dalip Singh of Punjab ",
            "optionD": "  Gaikwad of Baroda ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe nizam of Hyderabad was the first to enter into such an alliance. Tipu Sultan of Mysore refused to do so, but after the British victory in the Fourth Anglo-Mysore War, Mysore was forced to become a subsidiary state. The Nawab of Awadh was the next to accept the Subsidiary Alliance, in 1801. ",
            "keyString": "163823s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under whose leadership was the Chittagong Armoury Raid organised?",
            "optionA": "  Sukhdev ",
            "optionB": "  Bhagat Singh ",
            "optionC": "  Surya Sen ",
            "optionD": "  Rajguru ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChittagong armoury raid was organized by Surya sen (popularly known as Master da) along with Kalpana Dutt. It was aimed at dacoiting the British Armoury at Chittagong (then in Bengal, now in present day Bangladesh). ",
            "keyString": "164041s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the name of the Sabha started by Debendranath Tagore?",
            "optionA": "  Arya Samaj ",
            "optionB": "  Dharma Sabha ",
            "optionC": "  Tattvabodhini Sabha ",
            "optionD": "  Tattvabodhini Samaj ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 6 October 1839 Debendranath Tagore established Tattvaranjini Sabha which was shortly thereafter renamed the Tattwabodhini (Truth-seekers) Sabha. Initially confined to immediate members of the Tagore family, in 2 years it mustered over 500 members. ",
            "keyString": "164232s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Dandi March started from __________ in 1930",
            "optionA": "  Surat ",
            "optionB": "  Sabarmati Ashram ",
            "optionC": "  Delhi Durbar Hall ",
            "optionD": "  Vedaranyan ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 12 March 1930, Gandhi and 80 satyagrahis, many of whom were from scheduled castes, set out on foot for the coastal village of Dandi, Gujarat, over 390 kilometres (240 mi) from their starting point at Sabarmati Ashram. ",
            "keyString": "164411s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Commissioners for the Affairs of India were known as",
            "optionA": "  Court of Directors ",
            "optionB": "  Board of Directors ",
            "optionC": "  Board of Control ",
            "optionD": "  Board of Merchants ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Right Honourable Board of Commissioners for the Affairs of India (commonly known as the India Board or the Board of Control) was an arm of the Government of the United Kingdom responsible for managing the Government's interest in British India and the East India Company between 1784 and 1858. ",
            "keyString": "299365s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following was not a French settlement in India?",
            "optionA": "  Puducherry ",
            "optionB": "  Mahe ",
            "optionC": "  Goa ",
            "optionD": "  Chandannagar ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGoa is a former Portuguese colony, the Portuguese overseas territory of Portuguese India existed for about 450 years until it was annexed by India in 1961. In 1510, the Portuguese defeated the ruling Bijapur kings with the help of a local ally, Timayya, leading to the establishment of a permanent settlement in Velha Goa (or Old Goa).",
            "keyString": "299442s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who contemptuously referred to Mahatma Gandhi as a halfnaked fakir?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Wavell ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Irwin ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Willingdon ",
            "optionD": "  Winston Churchill ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBritish Prime Minister Winston Churchill once called Mahatma Gandhi \"a seditious Middle Temple lawyer, now posing as a fakir... striding half-naked up the steps of the Viceregal Palace.\" ",
            "keyString": "299463s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who called Sree Narayana Guru as 'The Second Buddha'?",
            "optionA": "  G. Sankara Kurup ",
            "optionB": "  Swami Vivekananda ",
            "optionC": "  Bodhananda Swamikal ",
            "optionD": "  Moorkoth Kumaran ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tG.Sankara Kurup called Shri Narayana Guru as Second Buddha. ",
            "keyString": "299479s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "AI Hilal was a",
            "optionA": "  Mosque ",
            "optionB": "  Journal ",
            "optionC": "  Madrasah ",
            "optionD": "  Garden ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Al-Hilal was a weekly Urdu language newspaper established by the Indian leader Maulana Abul Kalam Azad and used as a medium for criticism of the British Raj in India. The first issue came out on 13 July 1912. ",
            "keyString": "299494s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The most Important feature of the Government of India Act of 1919 was",
            "optionA": "  enlargement of Indian Councils ",
            "optionB": "  provision for direct election ",
            "optionC": "  dyarchy in the Provinces ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe most Important feature of the Government of India Act of 1919 was enlargement of Indian Councils, provision for direct election and dyarchy in the Provinces. ",
            "keyString": "406721s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Muslim communalism was lent an impetus by the activities of",
            "optionA": "  Ashfaqullah ",
            "optionB": "  Liaqat Hussain ",
            "optionC": "  Maulana Abul Kalam Azad ",
            "optionD": "  Sayyid Ahmad Khan ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMuslim communalism was lent an impetus by the activities of Sayyid Ahmad Khan. ",
            "keyString": "407128s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who threw two bombs on the Door of the Central Assembly in New Delhi on April 8, 1929?",
            "optionA": "  Bhagat Singh ",
            "optionB": "  Batukeshwar Dutt ",
            "optionC": "  Raj Guru ",
            "optionD": "  Both A and B above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBhagat Singh also disapproved that the two should be escorted after the bombing by the rest of the party. On 8 April 1929, Singh and Dutt threw a bomb onto the corridors of the assembly and shouted \u201cInquilab Zindabad!\u201d (\u201cLong Live the Revolution!\u201d). This was followed by a shower of leaflets stating that it takes a loud voice to make the deaf hear. ",
            "keyString": "407510s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Noakhali is situated in",
            "optionA": "  West Bengal ",
            "optionB": "  Bangladesh ",
            "optionC": "  Tripura ",
            "optionD": "  Bihar ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNoakhali is a district in South East Bangladesh 16th August, 1946 was declared the 'Direct Action Day'(also known as Calcutta killings Great) by Muslim League putting forward the demand of separate Nation and the riots broke out at Noakhali. ",
            "keyString": "407553s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During the first Carnatic War, the French Governor-General of Pondicherry was",
            "optionA": "  La Bourdonnais ",
            "optionB": "  Captain Paradise ",
            "optionC": "  Dupleix ",
            "optionD": "  Count-de-Lally ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGeneral Joseph Fran\u00e7ois Dupleix was the French Governor-General of Pondicherry during the first Carnatic War. ",
            "keyString": "407874s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many volunteers had accompanied Gandhi on the famous Dandi March of March 12, 1930?",
            "optionA": "  13 ",
            "optionB": "  44 ",
            "optionC": "  78 ",
            "optionD": "  108 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe 24-day march lasted from 12 March 1930 to 6 April 1930 as a direct action campaign of tax resistance and nonviolent protest against the British salt monopoly. It gained worldwide attention which gave impetus to the Indian independence movement and started the nationwide Civil Disobedience Movement. 78 volunteers had accompanied Gandhi on the famous Dandi March of 12 March 1930. ",
            "keyString": "528843s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who established the 'Sharda Sadan', a school for Indian Widows in colonial India?",
            "optionA": "  Mahadev Govind Ranade ",
            "optionB": "  Sarojini Naidu ",
            "optionC": "  Dayanand Saraswati ",
            "optionD": "  Pandita Ramabai ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPandita Ramabai started 'Sharda sadan' (House of Learning) at Bombay in 1889. It was the school of Indian Widows in colonial India. ",
            "keyString": "529037s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which session of Congress the demand of \"Purna\nSwaraj\" was accepted as the aim of the congress ?",
            "optionA": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionB": "  Madras ",
            "optionC": "  Nagpur ",
            "optionD": "  Lahore ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1928, Gandhi ji demanded Swaraj in the coming one year, from the British Government. In Lahore Session of 1929 of INC which took place on the bank of river Ravi under the presidentship of Pt. Jawahar Lal Nehru, the JNC declared 'Purna Swaraj' as its ultimate goal. ",
            "keyString": "529198s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The immediate cause for the Mutiny was",
            "optionA": "  Doctrine of Lapse ",
            "optionB": "  The Social Legislation of 1856 ",
            "optionC": "  The Episode of the Greased Cartridges ",
            "optionD": "  The fear of me Indians that they would be converted to Christianity ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe immediate cause of the revolt was the introduction of the new Enfield rifle and the greased cartridge. In loading the rifle the sepoy before inserting the cartridge had to bite off its top. It was believed that the grease was made out of the fats of cows and pigs. ",
            "keyString": "529356s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which religious reformer of Western India was known as 'Lokhitwadi'?",
            "optionA": "  Gopal Hari Deshmukh ",
            "optionB": "  R. G. Bhandarkar ",
            "optionC": "  Mahadev Govind Ranade ",
            "optionD": "  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGopal Hari Deshmukh was an Indian activist, thinker social and religious reformer who belonged to Maharashtra. He is also known 'Lokhitwadi'. ",
            "keyString": "529511s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Constituent Assembly was formed on the recommendations of the",
            "optionA": "  Government of India Act, 1935 ",
            "optionB": "  Cabinet Mission Plan ",
            "optionC": "  Cripps' Mission ",
            "optionD": "  Mountbatten Plan ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Constitution of India was drafted by the Constituent Assembly, and it was implemented under the Cabinet Mission Plan on 16 May 1946. The members of the Constituent Assembly were elected by the provincial assemblies by a single, transferable-vote system of proportional representation. ",
            "keyString": "591206s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statements is not correct? As per the Act of 1935, the Federal Court would have jurisdiction to decide disputes between",
            "optionA": "  The Federating Units ",
            "optionB": "  The Federating Units and the Federal Government ",
            "optionC": "  The Federal Government and a Federating Units ",
            "optionD": "  The Secretary of State and the Viceroy's Council ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Federal Court had exclusive original jurisdiction in any dispute between the Central Government and the Provinces. Initially, it was empowered to hear appeals from the High Courts of the provinces in the cases which involved the interpretation of any Section of the Government of India Act, 1935. ",
            "keyString": "591400s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said \"Give me Blood, I will give you Freedom\"?",
            "optionA": "  Subhash Chandra Bose ",
            "optionB": "  Lala Lajpat Rai ",
            "optionC": "  Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "optionD": "  Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSubhash Chandra Bose was an Indian Nationalist. He was a member national Planning commission under the leadership of Nehru. He said the famous slogan \"Give me blood, I will give you freedom\" during the commandership of INA. ",
            "keyString": "591562s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "__________in his book 'Economic history of India' wrote 'If India is poor today it is through the operation of economic causes'",
            "optionA": "  Dadhabai Naoroji ",
            "optionB": "  R. ",
            "optionC": " Dutt ",
            "optionD": "  Ranade ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFrom the Rise of the British Power in 1757 to the Accession of Queen Victoria in 1837. R.C. Dutt in his book 'Economic history of India' wrote 'If India is poor today it is through the operation of economic causes'. ",
            "keyString": "591718s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The All India Muslim League was founded in 1906 primarily to promote among Indian Muslims",
            "optionA": "  mutual unity and goodwill ",
            "optionB": "  political consciousness ",
            "optionC": "  feeling of loyalty to the British Government ",
            "optionD": "  hatred for the Congress ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMuslim League, original name All India Muslim League, political group that led the movement calling for a separate Muslim nation to be created at the time of the partition of British India (1947). The Muslim League was founded in 1906 to safeguard the rights of Indian Muslims. ",
            "keyString": "591872s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "As per the Regulating Act, a Governor-General and four Councillors were appointed for",
            "optionA": "  Bengal ",
            "optionB": "  Bombay ",
            "optionC": "  Madras ",
            "optionD": "  Surat ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Act designed its chief as Governor- General of Bengal and a council of four members were appointed. The first Governor General (Warren Hestings) and Councilors (Philip Francis, Clavering, Monson, and Barwell) were named in the Act. ",
            "keyString": "722021s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indian handicrafts rapidly declined due to",
            "optionA": "  lack of patronage ",
            "optionB": "  growing craze for imported goods ",
            "optionC": "  stiff competition from the machine-made goods of England ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian handicrafts rapidly declined due to lack of patronage, growing craze for imported goods, stiff competition from the machine-made goods of England. ",
            "keyString": "722217s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When Gandhi-Irwin Pact was signed, the Secretary of State for India was",
            "optionA": "  Salisbury ",
            "optionB": "  Curzon ",
            "optionC": "  Wedgwood Benn ",
            "optionD": "  Montagu ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhen Gandhi-Irwin Pact was signed, the Secretary of State for India was Wedgwood Benn. ",
            "keyString": "722380s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Cripps Mission came to India",
            "optionA": "  1946 ",
            "optionB": "  1945 ",
            "optionC": "  1942 ",
            "optionD": "  1940 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn March 1942, a delegation headed by Stafford Cripps a left wing labourite came to India to seek India's Support in war and offered constitutional proposal in return. Gandhiji referred it as a post dated cheque. ",
            "keyString": "722544s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statements is correct about Pt. Jawaharlal Nehru?",
            "optionA": "  Nehru did not believe in the doctrine of non-violence ",
            "optionB": "  Nehru was not in favour of socialism ",
            "optionC": "  Nehru had his higher education in India only ",
            "optionD": "  Nehru stressed the importance of national planning ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNehru stressed the importance of national planning. ",
            "keyString": "722699s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mahatma Gandhi broke his epic fast unto death on September 26, 1932 after the Poona Pact, which provided for",
            "optionA": "  common electorate for all Hindus ",
            "optionB": "  reservation of 48 seats for the depressed classes in different provincial legislatures ",
            "optionC": "  reservation of 18 per cent of the seats in the Central Legislature ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahatma Gandhi broke his epic fast unto death on September 26, 1932 after the Poona Pact, which provided for common electorate for all Hindus, reservation of 48 seats for the depressed classes in different provincial legislatures and reservation of 18 per cent of the seats in the Central Legislature. ",
            "keyString": "806194s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "As per the Regulating Act a Supreme Court was established in",
            "optionA": "  Bengal ",
            "optionB": "  Bombay ",
            "optionC": "  Delhi ",
            "optionD": "  Madras ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Supreme Court of Judicature at Fort William, Calcutta (Kolkata) was founded by an Act of Parliament in 1774. It replaced the Mayor's Court of Calcutta and was British India's highest court from 1774 until 1862, when the High Court of Calcutta was established. ",
            "keyString": "806382s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Swami Vivekananda, known in his pre-monastic life as__________",
            "optionA": "  Narendra Nath Datta ",
            "optionB": "  Vishwanath Datta ",
            "optionC": "  Upendranath Datta ",
            "optionD": "  Vasava Datta ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSwami Vivekananda, known in his pre-monastic life as Narendranath Datta, was born in Kolkata on 12 January 1863. Born with a yogic temperament, he used to practise meditation even from his boyhood, and was associated with Brahmo Movement for some time. ",
            "keyString": "806546s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When the August Offer 1940 was offered to India the Prime Minister of England was",
            "optionA": "  Chamberlain ",
            "optionB": "  Baldwin ",
            "optionC": "  Churchill ",
            "optionD": "  Asquith ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhen the August Offer 1940 was offered to India the Prime Minister of England was Winston Churchill. ",
            "keyString": "806702s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who had strongly advocated the policy of abolishing princely states in free India?",
            "optionA": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionC": "  C Rajagopalachari ",
            "optionD": "  Vallabhbhai Patel ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tC Rajagopalachari had strongly advocated the policy of abolishing princely states in free India. ",
            "keyString": "806857s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the charge against Bal Gangadhar Tilak, for which he was sentenced to six years transportation in July 1908?",
            "optionA": "  for being the chief exponent of the cult of extremism ",
            "optionB": "  for insiting violence during the Surat session of the INC ",
            "optionC": "  for seditious writings in his paper Kesari ",
            "optionD": "  for being instrumental in the murder of the British Plaque commissioner in Poona. ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFor seditious writings in his paper Kesari, Bal Gangadhar Tilak was sentenced to six years transportation in July 1908. ",
            "keyString": "938798s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "I. It favoured Dominion Status.\nII. It favoured a federal system.\nIII. It rejected the system of Communal Electorate.\nIV. It was against the setting up of a Supreme Court.\nWhich of the above statement(s) is/are correct related to the Nehru Report?",
            "optionA": "  I & IV ",
            "optionB": "  I & III ",
            "optionC": "  II, III & IV ",
            "optionD": "  I, II & III ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt favoured dominion status, it favoured a federal system and it rejected the system of communal electorate are correct related to the Nehru Report. ",
            "keyString": "938835s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Pitt's India Bill was introduced by __________ in 1784",
            "optionA": "  Prime Minister Pitt ",
            "optionB": "  Governor-General of India ",
            "optionC": "  Senior Merchants ",
            "optionD": "  East India Company ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPitt's India Act 1784 or the East India Company Act 1784 was passed in the British Parliament to rectify the defects of the Regulating Act 1773. ",
            "keyString": "938855s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was the First Round Table Conference held?",
            "optionA": "  1933 ",
            "optionB": "  1931 ",
            "optionC": "  1930 ",
            "optionD": "  1903 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFirst Round Table Conference (November 1930 \u2013 January 1931) officially inaugurated by George V on November 12, 1930 in Royal Gallery House of Lords at London and chaired by the Prime Minister. ",
            "keyString": "938868s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Swami Vivekananda's father, __________, was a successful attorney with interests in a wide range of subjects",
            "optionA": "  Vishwanath Datta ",
            "optionB": "  Narendra Nath Datta ",
            "optionC": "  Sri Ramakrishna ",
            "optionD": "  Rashik Krishna Mallik ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSwami Vivekananda, known in his pre-monastic life as Narendranath Datta, was born in an affluent family in Kolkata on 12 January 1863. His father, Vishwanath Datta, was a successful attorney with interests in a wide range of subjects, and his mother, Bhuvaneshwari Devi, was endowed with deep devotion, strong character and other qualities. ",
            "keyString": "938880s17m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said this message, the name Ezhava does not denote a caste or a religion and he made temple rights to everyone. Therefore people can be admitted to this organization without paying heed to differences of caste",
            "optionA": "  Chattambi Swamikal ",
            "optionB": "  T. K. Madhavan ",
            "optionC": "  Narayana Guru ",
            "optionD": "  Rajaram Mohan Roy ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNarayana Guru said that name Ezhava does not denote a caste or a religion and he made temple rights to everyone. Therefore people can be admitted to this organization without paying heed to differences of caste. ",
            "keyString": "186556s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "__________ is the acknowledged high priest of the drain theory",
            "optionA": "  Dadabhai Naoroji ",
            "optionB": "  S. N. Bose ",
            "optionC": "  J. N. Ghosh ",
            "optionD": "  J. N. Mukherjee ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe acknowledged high priest of the drain theory was Dadabhai Naoroji. It was in may 1867 that Dadabhai Naoroji put forward the idea that Britain was draining India. From then on for nearly half a century he launched a raging campaign against the drain, hammering at the theme through every possible form of public communication. ",
            "keyString": "187042s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The name of the periodical published by Gandhi during his stay in South Africa was",
            "optionA": "  Navjivan ",
            "optionB": "  India Gazette ",
            "optionC": "  Afrikaner ",
            "optionD": "  Indian Opinion ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe name of the periodical published by Gandhi during his stay in South Africa was Indian Opinion. ",
            "keyString": "187493s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The majority of the moderate leaders of India's freedom struggle may be traced to hail from",
            "optionA": "  Bengal ",
            "optionB": "  Rural areas ",
            "optionC": "  Urban areas ",
            "optionD": "  Both rurals as well as urban parts ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe majority of the moderate leaders of India's freedom struggle may be traced to hail from Urban areas. ",
            "keyString": "187986s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following was the first English ship that came to India?",
            "optionA": "  Elizabeth ",
            "optionB": "  Bengal ",
            "optionC": "  Red Dragon ",
            "optionD": "  Mayflower ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEast India Company, Second Voyage (1604\u20131605) The Second Voyage of the East India Company to the East Indies was made by the same four ships that had made the previous voyage, with Red Dragon now under the command of Sir Henry Middleton. ",
            "keyString": "188452s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first Indian selected for Indian Civil Service was",
            "optionA": "  Satyendra Nath Tagore ",
            "optionB": "  Sarojini Naidu ",
            "optionC": "  Lala Lajpat Rai ",
            "optionD": "  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSatyendra Nath Tagore was the first Indian to join the Indian Civil Service. He was elected in ICS in June 1863. He was the elder brother of Gurudev Rabindra nath Tagore. ",
            "keyString": "286356s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who founded India House in London and guided other revolutionaries",
            "optionA": "  Sri Aurobindo ",
            "optionB": "  Lokmanya Tilak ",
            "optionC": "  Shyamji Krishna Varma ",
            "optionD": "  Bhagat Singh ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShyamji Krishna Varma (4 October 1857 \u2013 30 March 1930) was an Indian revolutionary fighter, an Indian patriot, lawyer and journalist who founded the Indian Home Rule Society, India House and The Indian Sociologist in London. ",
            "keyString": "287024s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mohan Das Karamchand Gandhi was called as 'Mahatma' by",
            "optionA": "  Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "optionB": "  Motilal Nehru ",
            "optionC": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionD": "  Rabindra Nath Tagore ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRabindra Nath Tagore gave title Mahatma to Mohan Das Karamchand Gandhi after Champaran Satyagraha. ",
            "keyString": "288014s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The famous revolutionary song 'Sarfaroshi ki tamanna ab hamare dil mei hai ' was composed by",
            "optionA": "  Bhagat Singh ",
            "optionB": "  Khudiram Bose ",
            "optionC": "  Chandrasekhar Azad ",
            "optionD": "  Ramprasad Bismil ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRamprasad Bismil composed the song \"Sarfarosi ki Tamanna Ab Hamare Dil mei hai\" during British Period but it was written by Bismil Azimabadi of patna in 1921. ",
            "keyString": "288702s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "After the 1935 elections, the only two provinces out of eleven which had non-Congress ministries were",
            "optionA": "  Bengal and Punjab ",
            "optionB": "  Assam and Kerala ",
            "optionC": "  Bengal and Assam ",
            "optionD": "  Punjab and Kerala ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tProvincial elections were held in British India in the winter of 1936-37 as mandated by the Government of India Act 1935. Elections were held in eleven provinces - Madras, Central Provinces, Bihar, Orissa, United Provinces, Bombay Presidency, Assam, NWFP, Bengal, Punjab and Sindh. After the 1935 elections, the only two provinces out of eleven which had non-Congress ministries were Bengal and Punjab. ",
            "keyString": "289276s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Subhash Bose established the Provisional Government of Free India at",
            "optionA": "  Berlin ",
            "optionB": "  Bangkok ",
            "optionC": "  Singapore ",
            "optionD": "  Tokyo ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Provisional Government of Free India, or, more simply, Free India (Azad Hind), was an Indian provisional government established in occupied Singapore in 1943 and supported by the Empire of Japan, Nazi Germany, Italian Social Republic, and their allies. ",
            "keyString": "415405s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Permanent settlement introduced by Cornwallis is in Bengal is known as",
            "optionA": "  Roytwari System ",
            "optionB": "  Mahalwari System ",
            "optionC": "  Zamindari System ",
            "optionD": "  Iqtadari System ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tZamindari System was introduced by Cornwallis in 1793 through Permanent Settlement Act. It was introduced in provinces of Bengal, Bihar, Orissa and Varanasi. Zamindars were recognized as owner of the lands. Zamindars were given the rights to collect the rent from the peasants. ",
            "keyString": "415449s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The office of Governor-General of India was created by the",
            "optionA": "  Government of India Act, 1833 ",
            "optionB": "  Government of India Act, 1858 ",
            "optionC": "  Charter Act, 1833 ",
            "optionD": "  Charter Act, 1813 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe office of Governor-General of India was created by theCharter Act, 1833. ",
            "keyString": "415468s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the first Governor General of the new Indian Dominion?",
            "optionA": "  Rajendra Prasad ",
            "optionB": "  Vallabhbhai Patel ",
            "optionC": "  Rajagopalachari ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Mountbatten ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first Governor-General of British India was Lord William Bentinck, and the first Governor-General of independent India was Lord Mountbatten. ",
            "keyString": "415484s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following controlled maximum trade in the western coastal region during 17th century?",
            "optionA": "  Portuguese ",
            "optionB": "  Dutch ",
            "optionC": "  The house of Jagat Seth ",
            "optionD": "  Mulla Abdul Gaffar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPortuguese controlled maximum trade in western coastal region during 17th century. ",
            "keyString": "415499s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which amidst the following sites/monuments in India is on the UNESCO's list of World Cultural Heritages?",
            "optionA": "  Ellora Caves ",
            "optionB": "  Kashi Viswanath Temple ",
            "optionC": "  Qutab Minar ",
            "optionD": "  Manas Wildlife -  Sancturary ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKashi Vishvanath Temple is one of the most famous Hindu temples dedicated to Lord Shiva. It is located in Varanasi, Uttar Pradesh, India. The temple stands on the western bank of the holy river Ganga, and is one of the twelve Jyotirlingas, the holiest of Shiva temples. It is not on the UNESCO's list of World Cultural Heritages. ",
            "keyString": "577753s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following leaders died as a result of injuries sustained during a protest demonstration against Simon Commission?",
            "optionA": "  Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "optionB": "  Dadabhai Naoroji ",
            "optionC": "  Goplakrishna Gokhale ",
            "optionD": "  LaIa Lajpat Rai ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tProminent Indian nationalist Lala Lajpat Rai led a protest in Lahore. He suffered a police beating during the protest, and died of his injuries on 17th November,1928. ",
            "keyString": "578009s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "'Education is the manifestation of the perfection already in man'.Who said this?",
            "optionA": "  Swami Vivekananda ",
            "optionB": "  Sri Ramakrishna ",
            "optionC": "  Chandra Sekhar Deb ",
            "optionD": "  Sri Narayana Guru ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVivekananda believed education is the manifestation of perfection already in men. He thought it a pity that the existing system of education did not enable a person to stand on his own feet, nor did it teach him self-confidence and self-respect. To him education was an assimilation of noble ideas. ",
            "keyString": "578183s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following periods is considered as the revolutionary era in Indian history?",
            "optionA": "  1857-60 ",
            "optionB": "  1857-1947 ",
            "optionC": "  1857-90 ",
            "optionD": "  1845-1947 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t1857-90 is considered as the revolutionary era in Indian history. ",
            "keyString": "578348s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following events inspired for the formation of the Home Rule Leagues?",
            "optionA": "  First World War ",
            "optionB": "  Just before the First World War ",
            "optionC": "  After the First World War ",
            "optionD": "  After the passing of the Act of 1909 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnnie Besant gave new hope to the country. \u201cThe moment of England\u2019s difficulty is the moment of India\u2019s opportunity.\u201dShe started the Home Rule League Movement to be later supported fully by Tilak. It aimed at self-government for India within the British Commonwealth. She was more Indian than most Indians, a woman of profound courage and determination. The movement soon made a great impact upon the people. ",
            "keyString": "578583s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mahabandula was the great General of the",
            "optionA": "  Marathas ",
            "optionB": "  Sikhs ",
            "optionC": "  Nepalese ",
            "optionD": "  Burmese ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGeneral Maha Bandula was commander-in-chief of the Royal Burmese Armed Forces from 1821 until his death in 1825 in the First Anglo-Burmese War. ",
            "keyString": "711770s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was the All India Women's Conference founded?",
            "optionA": "  1924 ",
            "optionB": "  1925 ",
            "optionC": "  1926 ",
            "optionD": "  1927 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll India Women's conference was founded in 1927 and registered in 1930,under the societies registration act XXI of 1850, It is an organization dedicated to the upliftment and betterment of women. It was founded by Margaret Cousins. ",
            "keyString": "712095s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Jathi Nirnayam is the work of __________",
            "optionA": "  Sree Narayana Guru ",
            "optionB": "  ",
            "optionC": " Kesavan ",
            "optionD": "  Nataraja Guru ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA Critique on Jati (Casteism) by Sree Narayana Guru Translated by Muni Narayana Prasad written in 1914, this work deals with concept of Jati (Casteism). ",
            "keyString": "712260s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "From which of the following Upanishads the words 'Satyameva Jayate' inscribed in Devanagari Script below the abacus of the state Emblem are?",
            "optionA": "  Prashna ",
            "optionB": "  Yajurveda ",
            "optionC": "  Mundaka ",
            "optionD": "  Ishavasya ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t'Satyameva Jayate' is inscribed in devanagari script from Mundaka Upanishad.",
            "keyString": "712514s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ram Prasad Bismil had been associated with the case?",
            "optionA": "  Alipore bomb ",
            "optionB": "  Kanpur conspiracy ",
            "optionC": "  Kokori bomb ",
            "optionD": "  Meerut conspiracy ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Kakori Conspiracy (or Kakori train robbery or Kakori Case) was a train robbery that took place between Kakori and, near Lucknow, on 9 August 1925 during the Indian Independence Movement against the British Indian Government. The robbery was organised by Hindustan Republican Association (HRA). The robbery was conceived by Ram Prasad Bismil and Ashfaqullah Khan who belonged to the HRA, which later became the Hindustan Socialist Republican Association. ",
            "keyString": "714409s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following leader draws his inspiration from M.K Gandhi?",
            "optionA": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionB": "  Jayaprakash Narayan ",
            "optionC": "  Abdul Ghaffar Khan ",
            "optionD": "  Subhas Chandra Bose ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKhan Abdul Ghaffar Khan, also known as the 'Frontier Gandhi', was a political and spiritual leader known for his belief in non-violence and the methods of opposition to the British adopted by Mahatma Gandhi. ",
            "keyString": "829442s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following organised the \"All India Depressed Classes Association\" in colonial India?",
            "optionA": "  M. K. Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  Jyotiba Phule ",
            "optionC": "  Pandita Ramabai ",
            "optionD": "  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t\"All India Depressed class Association\" was organized by Dr. B. R. Ambedkar at Nagpur on August 8, 1930. ",
            "keyString": "829630s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In __________ , Jyotiba Phule formed the Satya Shodhak Samaj (Society of Seekers of Truth)",
            "optionA": "  1773 ",
            "optionB": "  1853 ",
            "optionC": "  1873 ",
            "optionD": "  1889 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSatyashodhak Samaj (Truth-seekers' Society) is a social reform society founded by Jyotiba Phule in Pune, India, on 24 September 1873. Its purpose was to liberate the less privileged in the then prevailing society such as women, Shudra, and Dalit from exploitation and oppression. ",
            "keyString": "829792s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Servants of India Society was founded in 1905 by",
            "optionA": "  BG Tilak ",
            "optionB": "  Lala Lajpat Rai ",
            "optionC": "  Gopal Krishna Gokhale ",
            "optionD": "  Aurobindo Ghosh ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Servants of India Society was formed in Pune, Maharashtra, on June 12, 1905 by Gopal Krishna Gokhale, who left the Deccan Education Society to form this association. ",
            "keyString": "829953s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Acts had provision of Indian Civil Services recruitment on the basis of competitive examination?",
            "optionA": "  Charter Act of 1813 ",
            "optionB": "  Government of India Act, 1858 ",
            "optionC": "  Charter Act of 1853 ",
            "optionD": "  Charter Act of 1833 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCharter Act of 1853 had provision of Indian Civil Services recruitment on the basis of competitive examination. ",
            "keyString": "830111s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "First Indian Commander-in-Chief was",
            "optionA": "  Gen. K. S. Thimayya ",
            "optionB": "  Gen. K. M. Kariappa ",
            "optionC": "  S. H. F. J. Manekshaw ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tField Marshal K. M. Cariappa or Kodandera \"Kipper\" Madappa Cariappa OBE (28 January 1899 \u2013 15 May 1993) was the first Indian commander-in-chief (C-in-C) of the Indian Army. He led Indian forces on the Western Front during the Indo-Pakistani War of 1947. ",
            "keyString": "897500s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1901 the State Census Manual of __________recorded Sree Narayana as a revered \"Guru\" and an erudite Sanskrit scholar",
            "optionA": "  Travancore ",
            "optionB": "  Malabar ",
            "optionC": "  Cochi ",
            "optionD": "  Kottayam ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1901 the State Census Manual of Travancore recorded Sree N\u0101r\u0101yana as a revered \" Guru\" and an erudite Sanskrit scholar. ",
            "keyString": "897719s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who instituted Scientific Society in 1863 to create a scientific temperament among the Muslims and to make the Western knowledge available to Indians in their own language?",
            "optionA": "  Mohammad Iqbal ",
            "optionB": "  Sir Syed Ahmed Khan ",
            "optionC": "  Karim Ali ",
            "optionD": "  Inayat Ali ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSir Syed Ahmed Khan instituted Scientific Society in 1863 to create a scientific temperament among the Muslims and to make the Western knowledge available to Indians in their own language. ",
            "keyString": "897885s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Government of India Act of 1935 had divided India into __________ provinces",
            "optionA": "  5 ",
            "optionB": "  8 ",
            "optionC": "  11 ",
            "optionD": "  14 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Government of India Act of 1935 had divided India into 11 provinces. ",
            "keyString": "898048s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who played an important role in bringing all the states in the independent India into the country's unity?",
            "optionA": "  Sardar Patel ",
            "optionB": "  Hume ",
            "optionC": "  Subhash Chandra Bose ",
            "optionD": "  Dr. Rajendra Prasad ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVallabhbhai Patel is the single most important reason that we have inherited the India that we have today \u2013 the political and geographic landmass we call India, without which there can be no 'idea of India'. Sardar Patel played an important role in bringing all the states in the independent India into the country's unity. ",
            "keyString": "898210s18m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first to come and last to leave India were",
            "optionA": "  The Portuguese ",
            "optionB": "  The French ",
            "optionC": "  The English ",
            "optionD": "  The Dutch ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPortuguese was the first voyage to India was by Vasco de Gama in 1498. The Portuguese Settlement in India is supposed to have lasted between 1505 and 1962. The most famous governor among the Portuguese was Alfonso de Albuquerque.",
            "keyString": "5465s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Dyarchy which was introduced on 1921 in province was in force till the year",
            "optionA": "  1927 ",
            "optionB": "  1935 ",
            "optionC": "  1937 ",
            "optionD": "  1947 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Dyarchy which was introduced on 1921 in province was in force till the year 1937. ",
            "keyString": "5697s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who gave the concept of Total Revolution?",
            "optionA": "  Jayaprakash Narayan ",
            "optionB": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionC": "  Karl Marx ",
            "optionD": "  Lenin ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJayaprakash Narayan was an Indian Independece activist. He gave the concept of Total Revolution which is political, social, economic, cultural, ideological, educational and motivational revolution.",
            "keyString": "5864s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mahatma Gandhi had been present at the Round Table Conference(s) held in London",
            "optionA": "  Third ",
            "optionB": "  Second ",
            "optionC": "  First ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe second Round Table Conference was held in London from 7 September 1931 to 1 December 1931 with the participation of Gandhi and the Indian National Congress. ",
            "keyString": "6021s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "I. Nasir Jang\nII. Muzaffar Jang\nIII. Anwaruddin\nIV. Chanda Sahib\nWhich of the above ruler(s) is/are associated with the French during the course of the Carnatic wars?",
            "optionA": "  I & II ",
            "optionB": "  III & IV ",
            "optionC": "  II & III ",
            "optionD": "  II & IV ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMuzaffar Jang and Chanda Sahib are associated with the French during the course of the Carnatic wars. ",
            "keyString": "6176s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The idea of incorporating, safeguards in the Indian Constitution was inspired by the",
            "optionA": "  Third Round Table Conference ",
            "optionB": "  Gandhi-Irwin Pact ",
            "optionC": "  Visit of Simon Commission ",
            "optionD": "  Poona Pact ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe idea of incorporating, safeguards in the Indian Constitution was inspired by the Visit of Simon Commission. ",
            "keyString": "72247s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sir Saiyad breathed his last on Sunday, 27th March__________",
            "optionA": "  1878 ",
            "optionB": "  1898 ",
            "optionC": "  1901 ",
            "optionD": "  1906 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSir Syed breathed his last on March 27, 1898 and was buried in the premises of the university mosque in the Sir Syed Hall, AMU. ",
            "keyString": "72444s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following regulations made English as a medium of education compulsory in government aided schools and colleges?",
            "optionA": "  Pitts India Act, 1784 ",
            "optionB": "  Educational Despatch, 1854 ",
            "optionC": "  Macaulay Minute, 1835 ",
            "optionD": "  Regulating Act, 1773 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMacaulay minute reform which was introduced in 1835 made English as a medium of education which was compulsory in upper primary level education. ",
            "keyString": "72607s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The 'Mohammadan Anglo-Oriental College' later became the",
            "optionA": "  Osmania University ",
            "optionB": "  JamiaMilia Muslim University ",
            "optionC": "  Baraktullah University ",
            "optionD": "  Aligarh Muslim University ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAligarh Muslim University established by Sir Sayyed Ahmad Khan as Mohammadan Anglo-Oriental College in 1875. ",
            "keyString": "72778s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1905 __________ laid the foundation of the 'servants of India society', with a view to the training of national missionaries for the service of India, and to promote by all constitutional means, the true interest of the Indian people",
            "optionA": "  Gokhale ",
            "optionB": "  Dadabai Naoroji ",
            "optionC": "  R. ",
            "optionD": " Dutt ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1905 Gokhale laid the foundation of the Servants of India Society with a view to \u201cthe training of national missionaries for the service of India, and to promote, by all constitutional means, the true interests of the Indian people.\u201d ",
            "keyString": "72935s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "High courts were established in Calcutta, Bombay and Madras in",
            "optionA": "  1935 ",
            "optionB": "  1919 ",
            "optionC": "  1862 ",
            "optionD": "  1861 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Calcutta, Bombay and Madras high court were established in 1862 by the Indian High court act of 1861, which was authorized by the Parliament ofUnited Kingdom. ",
            "keyString": "137683s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Prior to the Indian Association Sisir Kumar Ghosh along with Sambhu Charan Mukherjee founded __________in Calcutta on 25 September 1875",
            "optionA": "  The India League ",
            "optionB": "  Indian National Congress ",
            "optionC": "  Madras Mahajana Sabha ",
            "optionD": "  Bombay Presidency Association ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPrior to the Indian Association Sisir Kumar Ghosh along with Sambhu Charan Mukherjee founded 'The India League' in Calcutta on 25 September 1875. ",
            "keyString": "137872s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Special Congress Session held in 1920 at Calcutta was presided over by",
            "optionA": "  Nehru ",
            "optionB": "  LaIa Lajpat Rai ",
            "optionC": "  Bose ",
            "optionD": "  Gandhi ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 4 September 1920, Congress met at Calcutta in a special session. This special session was presided by Lala Lajpat Rai. ",
            "keyString": "138035s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following had during his reign introduced a new calendar, a new system of coinage, and new scales of weights and measures?",
            "optionA": "  Tipu Sultan ",
            "optionB": "  Murshid Quli Khan ",
            "optionC": "  Raghunath Rao ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Cornwallis ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTipu Sultan's desire to change with the times was symbolized in the Introduction of a new calendar, a new system of coinage, and new scales of weights and measures. ",
            "keyString": "138193s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Lahore was Ranjeet Singh's political capital. Which city was called his religious capital?",
            "optionA": "  Amritsar ",
            "optionB": "  Anandpur Sahib ",
            "optionC": "  Gujranwala ",
            "optionD": "  Peshawar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRanjeet Singh was famous Sikh ruler of Punjab, Amritsar was his religious capital. Lahore was the political capital. ",
            "keyString": "138347s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The communal electorate was introduced for the first time in India in",
            "optionA": "  1919 ",
            "optionB": "  1935 ",
            "optionC": "  1906 ",
            "optionD": "  1909 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Communal electorate (for Muslim) was introduced for the first time by Morley Reforms in 1909. ",
            "keyString": "220454s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The reformer from Maharashtra popularly known as 'Lokhitavadi' (For the well of others) was",
            "optionA": "  MG Ranade ",
            "optionB": "  Gopal Hari Deshmukh ",
            "optionC": "  Pt Ramabai ",
            "optionD": "  GK Gokhale ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGopal Hari Deshmukh (18 February 1823 \u2013 9 October 1892) was an Indian activist, thinker, social reformer and writer from Maharashtra. His original surname was Shidhaye. Because of 'Vatan' (right of Tax collection) that the family had received,the family was later called Deshmukh. ",
            "keyString": "221079s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bhulabhai Desai's most memorable achievement was his defence of the India National Army (I.N.A.) personnel at the Red fort Trial towards the end of",
            "optionA": "  1943 ",
            "optionB": "  1944 ",
            "optionC": "  1945 ",
            "optionD": "  1946 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTowards the end of 1945, during the Red Fort trials Bhulabhai Desai defended the three Indian National Army soldiers named Sardar Guru Baksh Singh, Shri Prem Sehgal, Shah Nawaz. These soldiers were charged of treasury during world war-II. ",
            "keyString": "221479s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Bombay Association, the first political association in Bombay presidency was founded by __________ in 1852",
            "optionA": "  Dadabhai Naoroji ",
            "optionB": "  Pulinbehari Sarkar ",
            "optionC": "  Amaresh Chakravarty ",
            "optionD": "  Prankrishna Parija ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first political association in Bombay presidency was founded by Dadabhai Naoroji in 1852, to express public grievances to the British. ",
            "keyString": "221833s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the founder of the, Ghadar Party?",
            "optionA": "  Basant Kumar Biswas ",
            "optionB": "  Sohan Singh Bhakna ",
            "optionC": "  Ram Prasad Bismil ",
            "optionD": "  Bhagat Singh ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGhadar Party was founded by the Lala Hardyal in United States and Canada in 1913. Sohan Singh Bhakna was the president of Ghadar Party. ",
            "keyString": "222195s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "On September 20, 1932 Mahatma Gandhi began a fast unto death in Yervada jail against",
            "optionA": "  British repression of the Satyagrahis ",
            "optionB": "  Violation of the Gandhi - Irwin Pact ",
            "optionC": "  Communal award of Ramsay MacDonald ",
            "optionD": "  Communal Roits in Calcutta ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 20 September 1932, M. K. Gandhi began a fast in Yerveda Jail (near Bombay) in protest of the British Government's decision of separate electorates. It ended by the Poona pact 26 September 1932. ",
            "keyString": "322768s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Kasturba Gandhi died in detention (in 1944) at",
            "optionA": "  Yeravada Jail ",
            "optionB": "  Ahmedabad Prison ",
            "optionC": "  Aga Khan Palace ",
            "optionD": "  Ahmednagar Fort ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKasturba Gandhi died in detention (in 1944) at Aga Khan Palace. ",
            "keyString": "322982s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Jyotiba Phule died On 28 November,__________",
            "optionA": "  1850 ",
            "optionB": "  1859 ",
            "optionC": "  1870 ",
            "optionD": "  1890 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJyotiba Phule died On 28 November,1890. ",
            "keyString": "323162s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who founded the Naujawan Bharat Sabha?",
            "optionA": "  ",
            "optionB": " ",
            "optionC": " Pal ",
            "optionD": "  G. Subramania lyer ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Naujawan Bharat Sabha was founded by Sardar Bhagat Singh. ",
            "keyString": "323324s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first Defence Minister of India was",
            "optionA": "  K. M. Cariappa ",
            "optionB": "  Gopalaswami Aiyangar ",
            "optionC": "  Baldev Singh ",
            "optionD": "  Sardar Patel ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 15 August 1947, India became an independent nation and Baldev Singh became India's first Minister of Defence, under the first Prime Minister of India, Jawaharlal Nehru. ",
            "keyString": "323484s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The system of civil services had been introduced into India by",
            "optionA": "  Lord Ripon ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Dalhousie ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Bentick ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Hastings ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGovernor-General Lord William Bentick paid attention to new administrative reforms and introduced some changes in the sphere of administration. He started the practice of appointing Indians in Company's service. ",
            "keyString": "536108s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The upliftment of the backward classes had been the prime concern of the",
            "optionA": "  Arya Samaj ",
            "optionB": "  Prarthana Samaj ",
            "optionC": "  Satyashodhak Samaj ",
            "optionD": "  Ramakrishna Mission ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe upliftment of the backward classes had been the prime concern of the Satyashodhak Samaj. ",
            "keyString": "536153s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "On Cabinet Mission, __________ observed, the proposals\npreserve the essential unity of India which la threatened by\nthe dispute between two major communities",
            "optionA": "  Lord Wavell ",
            "optionB": "  Nehru ",
            "optionC": "  Patel ",
            "optionD": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Cabinet Mission of 1946 came to India aimed to discuss the transfer of power from the British government to the Indian leadership, with the aim of preserving India's unity and granting it independence. On Cabinet Mission, Lord Wavell observed, the proposals preserve the essential unity of India which la threatened by the dispute between two major communities. ",
            "keyString": "536176s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the author of the book My Experiment with Truth?",
            "optionA": "  Aurobindo ",
            "optionB": "  Tilak ",
            "optionC": "  Gandhi ",
            "optionD": "  Vinobha ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMohan Das Karam Chand Gandhi was the author of book 'My Experient with Truth'. ",
            "keyString": "536194s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following pair of author & book is incorrectly matched?",
            "optionA": "  Rabindra Nath Tagore: Gora ",
            "optionB": "  Dadabhai Naoroji: Poverty and the Un-British rule in India ",
            "optionC": "  Dinabandhu Mitra: Nil Darpan ",
            "optionD": "  R. ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRomesh Chunder Dutt CIE was an Indian civil servant, economic historian, writer, and translator of Ramayana and Mahabharata. ",
            "keyString": "536285s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Narayana Guru's later literary and philosophical masterpiece Atmopadesa Satakam was written in__________",
            "optionA": "  Tamil ",
            "optionB": "  Malayalam ",
            "optionC": "  Sanskrit ",
            "optionD": "  Hindi ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNarayana Guru's later literary and philosophical masterpiece Atmopadesa Satakam was written in Malayalam. ",
            "keyString": "590962s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Hindu of Madras started in 1868 as a weekly, became a Daily in",
            "optionA": "  1889 ",
            "optionB": "  1899 ",
            "optionC": "  1890 ",
            "optionD": "  1855 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn Madras, the Hindu was started as a weekly in 1868 which became tri-weekly in 1883 and a daily from 1889.",
            "keyString": "590996s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which year was Burma separated from India?",
            "optionA": "  1863 ",
            "optionB": "  1902 ",
            "optionC": "  1937 ",
            "optionD": "  1947 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe British separated Burma Province from British India in 1937 and granted the colony a new constitution calling for a fully elected assembly, with many powers given to the Burmese, but this proved to be a divisive issue as some Burmese felt that this was a ploy to exclude them from any further Indian reforms. ",
            "keyString": "591012s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The film Mangal Pandey released in August 2005 deals with",
            "optionA": "  Jallianwala Bagh tragedy ",
            "optionB": "  Netaji Subash Bose's fight against British\noccupation of India ",
            "optionC": "  The first war of Indian Independence in 1857 ",
            "optionD": "  The partition of India and Pakistan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMangal Pandey: The Rising (internationally known as The Rising: Ballad of Mangal Pandey) is a 2005 Indian historical biographical drama film based on the life of Mangal Pandey, an Indian soldier known for helping to spark the Indian rebellion of 1857 (also known as The First War of Indian Independence). ",
            "keyString": "591024s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "As per the Act of 1853 the Governor-General's Council was enlarged for the purpose of",
            "optionA": "  Defence ",
            "optionB": "  Legislation ",
            "optionC": "  Finance ",
            "optionD": "  Security ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per the Act of 1853 the Governor-General's Council was enlarged for the purpose of Legislation. ",
            "keyString": "591036s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Narendra MandaI was inaugurated by Duke of Connaught in the year",
            "optionA": "  1920 ",
            "optionB": "  1921 ",
            "optionC": "  1931 ",
            "optionD": "  1910 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNarendra MandaI was inaugurated by Duke of Connaught in the year 1921. ",
            "keyString": "710599s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the founder-editor of the famous newspaper 'Kesari' during the National Struggle?",
            "optionA": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionC": "  Lokmanya Tilak ",
            "optionD": "  Muhannad Iqbal ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKesari is a newspaper founded in 1881 by Lokmanya Bal Gangadhar Tilak, a prominent leader of the Indian Independence movement. ",
            "keyString": "710634s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where did the revolutionaries have their deliberations, which led to the formation of the Hindustan Republican Association?",
            "optionA": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionB": "  Kanpur ",
            "optionC": "  Madras ",
            "optionD": "  Allahabad ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn Kanpur the revolutionaries have their deliberations, which led to the formation of the Hindustan Republican Association. ",
            "keyString": "710648s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "With which of the following would you associate Jyotiba Phule?",
            "optionA": "  Satya Shodhak Samaj ",
            "optionB": "  Theosophical Society ",
            "optionC": "  Tattvabodhini Samaj ",
            "optionD": "  Dharma Sabha ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSatyashodhak Samaj (Truth-seekers' Society) is a social reform society founded by Jyotiba Phule in Pune, India, on 24 September 1873. Its purpose was to liberate the less privileged in the then prevailing society such as women, Shudra, and Dalit from exploitation and oppression. Jyotibha's wife Savitribai was the head of women's section of the society. ",
            "keyString": "710661s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the first leader to preside over the INC?",
            "optionA": "  Ananda Charlu ",
            "optionB": "  S Subramanya Iyer ",
            "optionC": "  WC Banerji ",
            "optionD": "  Surendranath Bannerjee ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWomesh Chandra Banerjee presided over the first session of the Indian National Congress held at Bombay in 1885 from 28 December to 31 December. ",
            "keyString": "710673s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first newspaper which was published in India was",
            "optionA": "  The Calculatta Gazette ",
            "optionB": "  The Bombay Gazette ",
            "optionC": "  The Oriental Maganize of Calculatta ",
            "optionD": "  The Bengal Gazette ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHickey's Bengal Gazette was an English newspaper published from Kolkata (then Calcutta), India. It was the first major newspaper in India, started in 1780. It was published for two years. Founded by James Augustus Hicky, a highly eccentric Irishman who had previously spent two years in Jail for debt. ",
            "keyString": "800779s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "'Lucknow pact' was a deal between",
            "optionA": "  Indians and the British about legislative seats ",
            "optionB": "  Hindus and Muslims regarding seat sharing in legislatures ",
            "optionC": "  Depressed castes and Brahmins about job reservations ",
            "optionD": "  Hindus and Sikhs about job reservations ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t'Lucknow Pact' was deal between Hindus and Muslims regarding seat sharing, it was joint session of the congress held at Lucknow in 1916. ",
            "keyString": "800931s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following leader presided the historic 1916 Lucknow Session of the Congress?",
            "optionA": "  Annie Besant ",
            "optionB": "  Madan Mohan Malviya ",
            "optionC": "  Ambika Charan Majumdar ",
            "optionD": "  Subhas Chandra Bose ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAmbika Charan Majumdar presided over the 1899 Bengal Provincial Conference at Burdwan as well as the 1910 Conference in Calcutta. He had served as the president of the 31st session of the Indian National Congress in 1916 where the famous Lucknow Pact was signed between the Congress and the Muslim league and also moderates and extremists of the Congress party came together once again. ",
            "keyString": "800961s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A new period in__________'s life began in 1913 when she became active in Indian politics, and gave a lead by claiming 'Home Rule' for India",
            "optionA": "  Ammu Swaminathan ",
            "optionB": "  Malati Patwardhan ",
            "optionC": "  Annie Besant ",
            "optionD": "  Ambujammal ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA new period in Annie Besant\u2019s life began in 1913 when she became active in Indian politics, and gave a lead by claiming Home Rule for India.She entered politics because she saw that India\u2019s independence was essential for her age-old wisdom to become a beacon for the whole world.The Home Rule movement she organized spread all over India. ",
            "keyString": "800984s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who did Mahatma Gandhi recognise as his political Guru?",
            "optionA": "  Pheroze Shah Mehta ",
            "optionB": "  ",
            "optionC": " G. Tilak ",
            "optionD": "  Gopal Krishna Gokhale ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGopal Krishna Gokhale was a mentor to both Mohammed Jinnah and Mahatma Gandhi. Born on May 9, 1866, he is known to be a mentor to Mahatma Gandhi. Gopal Krishna Gokhale was also a social reformer whose goals were to promote non-violence and reform within existing government institutions. ",
            "keyString": "801004s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which scripture was called his 'mother' by Gandhiji?",
            "optionA": "  Ramayana ",
            "optionB": "  The New Testament ",
            "optionC": "  Bhagwat Gita ",
            "optionD": "  The Holy Quran ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNo other book or Scripture influenced Gandhi, shaped his character and transformed his life as profoundly and permanently as did the Bhagvad Gita, As a spiritual reference book, the Gita was not only his constant companion, it was his \"eternal mother\" who he esteemed even more than his earthly mother. ",
            "keyString": "885460s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following was established first?",
            "optionA": "  Banaras Hindu University ",
            "optionB": "  University of Bombay ",
            "optionC": "  Aligarh Muslim University ",
            "optionD": "  University of Allahabad ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUniversity of Mumbai, formerly University of Bombay, one of India's first modern universities, established by the British in 1857. ",
            "keyString": "885500s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The joint session of the Congress and Muslim League was held in 1916 at",
            "optionA": "  Delhi ",
            "optionB": "  Kanpur ",
            "optionC": "  Lucknow ",
            "optionD": "  Madras ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Lucknow Pact was an agreement reached between the Indian National Congress and the Muslim League at the joint session of both the parties held in Lucknow in December 1916. ",
            "keyString": "885517s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which year was the All India Muslim League founded?",
            "optionA": "  1903 ",
            "optionB": "  1906 ",
            "optionC": "  1909 ",
            "optionD": "  1912 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFounded in In 30 December 1906, the All-India Muslim League was founded at Dhaka. Founders: Khwaja Salimullah, Vikar-ul-Mulk, Syed Amir Ali, Syed Nabiullah. ",
            "keyString": "885533s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Against Lord and State was written by",
            "optionA": "  K. N. Panikkar ",
            "optionB": "  Sri Ramakrishna ",
            "optionC": "  Chandra Sekhar Deb ",
            "optionD": "  Shyama Charan Sen ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAgainst Lord and State was written by K N Panikkar. ",
            "keyString": "885546s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The ruler of Mysore who secured the rendition of Mysore was",
            "optionA": "  Tippu ",
            "optionB": "  Hyder ",
            "optionC": "  Krishnaraja III ",
            "optionD": "  Rajendra Wodiar ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe ruler of Mysore who secured the rendition of Mysore was Krishnaraja III. ",
            "keyString": "998799s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which governor General abolished the 'Sati System' in India?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Canning ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Ripon ",
            "optionC": "  Lord William Bentinck ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Dalhousie ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSati System in india was abolished by Governor General Lord William Bentinck. Indian Social Reformer Raja Ram Mohan Roy also played an important role to abolish Sati system. ",
            "keyString": "998839s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who started the Sharda Sadan in Bombay?",
            "optionA": "  Ramabai Saraswati ",
            "optionB": "  Sarala Devi Chaudhurani ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Edwin Montague ",
            "optionD": "  Dorothy Jinarajadasa ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1889, Ramabai started Sharada Sadan in the erstwhile Bombay with two students and a principle of observing complete religious freedom. It then moved to Pune and later became Pandita Ramabai Mukti Mission. ",
            "keyString": "998859s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Shuja-ud-Daulah wanted to acquire the territory of",
            "optionA": "  Rohelas ",
            "optionB": "  Marathas ",
            "optionC": "  Sikhs ",
            "optionD": "  Tamils ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShuja-ud-Daulah wanted to acquire the territory of Rohelas. ",
            "keyString": "998875s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "On what charge was Khudiram Bose, a boy of 18, sentenced to death on April 30, 1908?",
            "optionA": "  for being an active member of the Anushilan Samiti, the first  revolutionary organisation in Bengal ",
            "optionB": "  for participating in the Alipur Conspiracy ",
            "optionC": "  for murdering one Kennedy in Muzaffarpur ",
            "optionD": "  for attempting to murder Kingsfords, the Chief Presidency Magistrate at Muzaffarpur, who had ordered severe flogging to some young men for minor offences. ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKhudiram Bose, a boy of 18, was sentenced to death on April 30, 1908 for attempting to murder Kingsfords, the Chief Presidency Magistrate at Muzaffarpur, who had ordered severe flogging to some young men for minor offences. ",
            "keyString": "998888s19m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who had introduced the Indian Universities Act 1904?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Ripon ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Hardinge ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Curzon ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Auckland ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Curzon had introduced the Indian Universities Act 1904. ",
            "keyString": "95331s20m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Name the Commission that came to India in 1928 to reform India's constitutional system",
            "optionA": "  Rowaltt Act ",
            "optionB": "  Pitt's India Act ",
            "optionC": "  Partition of Bengal ",
            "optionD": "  Simon Commission ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSimon Commission came to India in 1928 to reform India's constitutional system. Indian opposed this commission because there were no Indian members in this commission (also called white commission). ",
            "keyString": "95369s20m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said that \"India's Soul live in villages\"?",
            "optionA": "  Vinoba Bhave ",
            "optionB": "  Jayaprakash Narayan ",
            "optionC": "  Jawahar Lal Nehru ",
            "optionD": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahatma Gandhi said that \"India's Soul live in villages.\" ",
            "keyString": "95383s20m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The office of the Secretary of State for India was created by the Act of",
            "optionA": "  1853 ",
            "optionB": "  1858 ",
            "optionC": "  1861 ",
            "optionD": "  1892 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe First Secretary of State of India: Lord Stanley. The first Secretary of state was Lord Stanley, who prior to 2 August 1858, served as President of the Board of Control. The Secretary of State was now the political head of the India. ",
            "keyString": "95394s20m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The system of communal electorate in India was first introduced by",
            "optionA": "  Indian Council Act of 1892 ",
            "optionB": "  Minto-Morley reforms of 1909 ",
            "optionC": "  Montagu-Chelmsford reforms of 1919 ",
            "optionD": "  Government of India of 1935 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCommunal Electorate in India was introduced by Minto Morley reforms (1909). By the reforms of 1909, it introduced separate electorates for Muslims. ",
            "keyString": "95404s20m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first definite and forceful expression of the concept of a separate homeland for the Muslims came from (or the Catcher of the idea of Pakistan was)",
            "optionA": "  Sir Mohammad Iqbal ",
            "optionB": "  Rahmat Ali ",
            "optionC": "  M A Jinnah ",
            "optionD": "  Liaqat Ali ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first definite and forceful expression of the concept of a separate homeland for the Muslims came from (or the Catcher of the idea of Pakistan was) Sir Mohammad Iqbal. ",
            "keyString": "376141s20m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The young Nanu had a keen mind and was sent to a famous scholar, __________ Asan at Karunagapally, a village fifty miles away from his home, at the age of 21",
            "optionA": "  Madan Asan ",
            "optionB": "  Kummampilli Raman Pillai ",
            "optionC": "  Krishnan Vaidyan ",
            "optionD": "  Kumaran Asan ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe young Nanu had a keen mind and was sent to a famous scholar, Kummampilli Raman Pillai Asan at Karunagappally, a village fifty miles away from his home, at the age of 21. ",
            "keyString": "376286s20m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Sir Saiyad was a prophet of education\" who said this?",
            "optionA": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  Sree Narayana Guru ",
            "optionC": "  Chattambi Swamikal ",
            "optionD": "  Tilak ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe words were said by Mahatma Gandhi. ",
            "keyString": "376309s20m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following leader organised the Swaraj Party?",
            "optionA": "  Lala Lajpat Rai and Feroz Shah Mehta ",
            "optionB": "  Sarojini Naidu and Annie Besant ",
            "optionC": "  ",
            "optionD": " R. Das and Motilal Nehru ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Swaraj Party as established as the Congress-Khilafat Swaraj Party. It was a political party formed in India in January 1923 after the Gaya annual conference in December 1922 of the National Congress, that sought greater self-government and political freedom for the Indian people from the British Raj. It was inspired by the concept of Swaraj. In Hindi and many other languages of India, swaraj means \"independence\" or \"self-rule.\" The two most important leaders were Chittaranjan Das, who was its president and Motilal Nehru, who was its secretary. ",
            "keyString": "376325s20m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Why was the Second Round Table Conference failed?",
            "optionA": "  Priority to be given to communal question ",
            "optionB": "  Suspension of Civil Disobedience Movement ",
            "optionC": "  Grant of Dominion Status ",
            "optionD": "  Date of transfer of power ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDue to wide scale participation,the Government claimed that the Congress did not represent the interests of All India. But, Gandhi claimed that Congress Represented India. Gandhi iterated the need of a partnership between Britain and India as between two equal nations. ",
            "keyString": "376342s20m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Deccan Educational Society founded by",
            "optionA": "  Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "optionB": "  Jyotiba Phule ",
            "optionC": "  Firoz Shah Mehta ",
            "optionD": "  Gopal Ganesh Agarkar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1885 Ranade, Vaman Abaji Modak, and historian Dr. R. G. Bhandarkar established the Maharashtra Girls Education Society and Huzurpaga, the oldest girls high school in Maharashtra. ",
            "keyString": "511509s20m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who had succeeded Mir Jafar to the throne?",
            "optionA": "  Haider Ali ",
            "optionB": "  Chandra Sahib ",
            "optionC": "  Tipu Sultan ",
            "optionD": "  Mir Kasim ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMir Qasim was the Nawab of Bengal from 1760 to 1763. He was installed as Nawab with the support of the British East India Company, replacing Mir Jafar, his father-in-law, who had himself been supported earlier by the East India Company after his role in the Battle of Plassey. ",
            "keyString": "511653s20m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"India Wins Freedom\" is the autobiography of",
            "optionA": "  Abdul Kalam Azad ",
            "optionB": "  Muhammad Ali ",
            "optionC": "  Zakir Hussain ",
            "optionD": "  Sayyed Ahmad Khan ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t\"India wins freedom\" is the autobiography of Abul Kalam Azad. His Birthday (11 November) is celebrated as \" National Education day\" Bharat Ratna was conferred to him in 1992 (Posthumously). In 1923 he became the youngest president of Congress in Delhi session and also served as congress president from 1940 to 1945. He became the first education minister of independent India. ",
            "keyString": "511707s20m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Asiatic Society had been established in Calcutta by",
            "optionA": "  TB Macaulay ",
            "optionB": "  Sir William Jones ",
            "optionC": "  GK Gokhale ",
            "optionD": "  Annie Besant ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Asiatic Society was founded by civil servant Sir William Jones on 15 January 1784 in a meeting presided over by Sir William Jones, Justice of the Supreme Court of Judicature at Fort William Calcutta, then capital of the British Raj, to enhance and further the cause of Oriental research. ",
            "keyString": "511732s20m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A 19th century social reformer who is regarded as the bridge between the past and the future is",
            "optionA": "  Keshab Chandra Sen ",
            "optionB": "  Devendra Nath Tagore ",
            "optionC": "  Ishwar chandra ",
            "optionD": "  Raja Ram Mohan Roy ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRaja Ram Mohan Roy is considered to be the first Indian who tried to pull out the Indian society out of the medieval age. He is known as \"Father of Modern India\"; \"Father of Indian Renaissance\" and \"bridge between past and future\". ",
            "keyString": "511756s20m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Satyarth Prakash was written by __________",
            "optionA": "  Lala Lajpat Rai ",
            "optionB": "  Lala Hardyal ",
            "optionC": "  Dayanand Saraswati ",
            "optionD": "  Raja Ram Mohan Roy ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe book Satyarth Prakash was written by Swami Dayanand Saraswati. The word Satya Prakash means \u201cThe Light of Truth\u201d is a book written in Hindi in the year 1875. The major portion of the book is dedicated to laying down the reformist advocacy of Swami Dayanand. ",
            "keyString": "695365s20m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Rabindranath Tagore surrendered his knighthood in protest against",
            "optionA": "  Martial law in the Punjab ",
            "optionB": "  Jallianwala Bagh tragedy ",
            "optionC": "  Rawlatt Acts ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRabindranath Tagore surrendered his knighthood in protest against Jallianwala Bagh tragedy. ",
            "keyString": "695696s20m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not one of the reasons why Mahatma Gandhi is known as the Father of Nation?",
            "optionA": "  He was universally adored, admired and respected by all castes, communities and classes ",
            "optionB": "  Starting with opposition to the Rowlatt Acts, till the Quit India Movement he was the supreme leader and the main spirit behind the national movement ",
            "optionC": "  His social political, economic and religious ideologies were based on Indian values with a very strong moral and ethical content ",
            "optionD": "  He was the founder President of the Indian National Congress ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGandhiji's simplicity and love towards others made him closer to the common man. At all stages during the freedom movement, he preached and practised only Ahimsa or non-violence. He was universally adored, admired and respected by all castes, communities and classes is not one of the reasons why Mahatma Gandhi is known as the Father of Nation. Subhash Chandra Bose in respect of Gandhi gave him the title of 'Father of Nation'. He was not one ofthe founder President of the Indian National Congress.",
            "keyString": "696923s20m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Pazhassi Samarangal (Malayalam) was written by __________",
            "optionA": "  K. K. N. Kurup ",
            "optionB": "  Bhattacharya Sabya ",
            "optionC": "  K. K. Kusuman ",
            "optionD": "  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tK.K.N.Kurup has published numerous works in both English and Malayalam. Pazhassi Samarangal (Malayalam) was written by him. ",
            "keyString": "696994s20m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Constituent Assembly of India was formulated on the recommendation of",
            "optionA": "  Wavel Plan ",
            "optionB": "  Cripps Mission ",
            "optionC": "  August Offer ",
            "optionD": "  Cabinet Mission ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tConstituent assembly of India was formulated on the recommendation of Cabinet mission 1946. The members of Cabinet Misson were Patthick Lawrence, Stafford Cripps and A.B Alexander. ",
            "keyString": "697012s20m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "As per the Act of 1919 which of the following statements was not correct?",
            "optionA": "  British India must remain an integral part of the British Empire. ",
            "optionB": "  Responsible Government would be realised only by the progressive stages. ",
            "optionC": "  Provincial subjects were classified into Reserved subjects and Transferred subjects. ",
            "optionD": "  The salary of the Secretary of State for India was not to be paid by Parliament.  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe salary of the Secretary of State for India was to be paid by Parliament. ",
            "keyString": "831808s20m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The socialist group in the INC during, the 1930s had been led by",
            "optionA": "  Bipin Chandra Pal ",
            "optionB": "  Rajendra Prasad ",
            "optionC": "  Lala Lajpat Rai ",
            "optionD": "  Subhas Chandra Bose ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe socialist group in the INC during, the 1930s had been led by Subhas Chandra Bose. ",
            "keyString": "832321s20m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "'A day of deliverance and thanks giving' was celebrated in 1939 by",
            "optionA": "  Congress Party ",
            "optionB": "  Muslim League ",
            "optionC": "  Forward Bloc ",
            "optionD": "  Communist Party ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 2 December that year, League chief Muhammad Ali Jinnah called upon Indian Muslims to celebrate 22 December as 'Deliverance Day' from Congress. ",
            "keyString": "833048s20m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The revolutionary who was an accused in Lahore Conspiracy Case and who died in Jail after 64 days fast was",
            "optionA": "  Jatin Das ",
            "optionB": "  Sukh Dev ",
            "optionC": "  Raj Guru ",
            "optionD": "  Both A and B above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJatindra Nath Das (27 October 1904 \u2013 13 September 1929), also known as Jatin Das, was an Indian independence activist and revolutionary. He died in Lahore jail after a 63-day hunger strike. ",
            "keyString": "833093s20m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said Ask not, Say not, Think not caste, Think only Gods",
            "optionA": "  Sree Narayana Guru ",
            "optionB": "  William Logan ",
            "optionC": "  Connolly ",
            "optionD": "  S. N. Banerjee ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe slogan popularized by Sree Narayana Guru-\u201cOne caste, one religion and one God for mankind\u201d. He taught \u201cWhatever may be the religion of a man, it is enough if he becomes virtuous\u201d, \u201cAsk not, Say not, think not caste\u201d, \u201cAct that one performs for one's sake should also benefit other\u201d. ",
            "keyString": "833403s20m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "On the Direct Action Day unprecedented bloodshed took place (as a result of Hindu-Muslim riots) in",
            "optionA": "  Dacca ",
            "optionB": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionC": "  Delhi ",
            "optionD": "  Meerut and Karachi ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDirect Action Day or The Great Calcutta Killing was a planned attack on the Hindus of Calcutta by the Muslims under the leadership of Huseyn Shaheed Suhrawardy. On this day more than 5000 Hindus were killed by the fanatic Muslim mob. ",
            "keyString": "948319s20m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which session of India National Congress the tricolour flag was unfurled for the first time?",
            "optionA": "  Calcutta Session, 1920 ",
            "optionB": "  Annual Session of Congress at Nagpur, 1920 ",
            "optionC": "  Lahore Congress, 1929 ",
            "optionD": "  Haripura congress conference, 1938 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAt Lahore congress session, 1929 Indian National Congress unfurled flag first time. ",
            "keyString": "948990s20m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During the Dandi March the song 'Raghupati Raghav Raja Ram' had been sung by the renowned musician",
            "optionA": "  Digambar Vishnu Paluskar ",
            "optionB": "  Onkar Nath Thakur ",
            "optionC": "  Mallikarjun Mansur ",
            "optionD": "  Krishna Rao Shankar Pandit ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe version that is most common was put to music by Vishnu Digambar Paluskar, and was sung by Gandhi and his followers as they walked during the 241 mile Salt March to Dandi. ",
            "keyString": "949580s20m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Swaraj Party was organised by",
            "optionA": "  Lala Lajapat Rai and Feroze Shah Mehta ",
            "optionB": "  Sarojini Naidu and Annie Besant ",
            "optionC": "  CR Das and Motilal Nehru ",
            "optionD": "  C Rajagopalachari and CY Chintamani ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSwaraj Party, Indian political party established in late 1922 \u2013 early 1923 by members of the Indian National Congress (Congress Party), notably Motilal Nehru, one of the most prominent lawyers in northern India (and the father of political leader Jawaharlal Nehru), and Chitta Ranjan Das, a nationalist politician from Bengal. ",
            "keyString": "950123s20m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the first to give the call for Swarajya \u2013 \"India for Indians\"?",
            "optionA": "  Dayanand Saraswati ",
            "optionB": "  Lokmanya Tilak ",
            "optionC": "  Sri Aurobindo ",
            "optionD": "  Bhagat Singh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDayananda Saraswati [1824-1883] was the first to give the call for Swarajya \u2013 \"India for Indians\" \u2013 in 1876. Dayananda Saraswati was the first to dispute the Aryan myth was, rejecting out of hand the entire 19th Century European view of the Veda. ",
            "keyString": "950639s20m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Aligarh Muslim University was founded by",
            "optionA": "  Jinnah ",
            "optionB": "  Syed Ahmed Khan ",
            "optionC": "  Abul Kalam Azad ",
            "optionD": "  Bhutto ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSir Syed Ahmed Khan established the MAO College which eventually became the Aligarh Muslim University. ",
            "keyString": "32706s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "With whom is the slogan \"Do or Die\" associated?",
            "optionA": "  Subhas Chandra Bose ",
            "optionB": "  Lala Lajpat Rai ",
            "optionC": "  Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "optionD": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn the night of 8th August 1942 addressing the Congress delegates Mahatma Gandhi gave the the slogan \"Do or Die\". It means we shall either free India or die in the attempt. ",
            "keyString": "32750s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Charter Act of 1813 left intact the Company's monopoly of __________ trade",
            "optionA": "  China ",
            "optionB": "  Jawa ",
            "optionC": "  Ceylon ",
            "optionD": "  Japan ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Charter act of 1813 ended the monopoly of the East India Company in India, however the company's monopoly in trade with china and trade in tea was remained intact. The charter act of 1813, for the first time explicitly defined the constitutional position of the British territories in India. ",
            "keyString": "32768s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who started the Young Men's Indian Association in 1914?",
            "optionA": "  Annie Besant ",
            "optionB": "  Swarnakumari Devi ",
            "optionC": "  Devendranath Tagore ",
            "optionD": "  Rabindranath Tagore ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1914, when Annie Besant, the president of the Theosophical Society, founded the Young Men's Indian Association (YMIA), she chose Gokhale Hall as its headquarters, where the youth would indulge in sports from table tennis to boxing and sit on the verandahs debating on the nation's affairs. ",
            "keyString": "32784s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main cause of the tribal uprisings of the 19th century was",
            "optionA": "  the British land settlements and land laws had created tension in the tribal society ",
            "optionB": "  Christian Missionary activities in the tribal areas ",
            "optionC": "  the British Forest Laws ",
            "optionD": "  new excise regulations and police exactions ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAn attempt has been made in this unit to show how the peasants and tribes reacted to alien rule in the late 18th and 19th centuries, till 1857. This Unit overs~somehajor peasant and tribal uprisings and the origins and character of such uprisings.",
            "keyString": "32800s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Nawab Siraj-ud-Daulah of Bengal was defeated by the English in the battle of Plassey, mainly",
            "optionA": "  because the English forces were much stronger than those of the Nawab ",
            "optionB": "  because of Clive's conspiracy with the Nawab's Commanderin- Chief Mir Jafar and rich bankers of Bengal ",
            "optionC": "  because of Siraj-ud-Daulah's retirement from the battlefield ",
            "optionD": "  because of the capture of a band of Frenchmen under the Nawab's service by the English ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNawab Siraj-ud-Daulah or Bengal was defeated by the English in the battle of Plassey, mainly because of Clive's conspiracy with the Nawab's Commander-in-Chief Mir Jafar and rich bankers of Bengal. ",
            "keyString": "142492s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the first European to translate the Bhagavad Gita into English?",
            "optionA": "  Alexander Cunningham ",
            "optionB": "  William Jones ",
            "optionC": "  James Prinsep ",
            "optionD": "  Charles Wilkins ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1785, the Bhagavad Gita was first translated into English by Charles Wilkins and published as \u201cBhagvat-geeta or Dialogues of Kreeshna and Arjoon\u201d by the British East India Company with an introduction by Lord Warren Hastings, the first British Governor-General of India. ",
            "keyString": "142685s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was the famous Resolution on non-cooperation under the inspiration of Mahatma Gandhi was adopted in a special session of the Congress held in Calcutta?",
            "optionA": "  September, 1920 ",
            "optionB": "  December, 1922 ",
            "optionC": "  October, 1924 ",
            "optionD": "  November, 1925 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn September, 1920, the famous Resolution on non-cooperation under the inspiration of Mahatma Gandhi was adopted in a special session of the Congress held in Calcutta. ",
            "keyString": "142850s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following leader was associated with the formation of the Congress Socialist Party?",
            "optionA": "  P. ",
            "optionB": " Joshi ",
            "optionC": "  Subhas Chandra Bose ",
            "optionD": "  Acharya Narendra Dev ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAcharya Narendra Dev was associated with the formation of the Congress Socialist Party. Acharya Narendra Deva became president. ",
            "keyString": "143012s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Whom had the rebels of 1857 enthroned as the emperor/emperess of India?",
            "optionA": "  Rani Laxmi Bai of Jhansi ",
            "optionB": "  Tantia Tope ",
            "optionC": "  Bahadur Shah Zafar ",
            "optionD": "  Faqir-ud-din ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter the Indian Rebellion of 1857, the British exiled him from Delhi. Bahadur Shah Zafar was a noted Urdu poet, having written a number of Urdu ghazals. While some part of his opus was lost or destroyed during the Indian Rebellion of 1857, a large collection did survive, and was compiled into the Kulliyyat-i-Zafar. ",
            "keyString": "143387s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Hindustan Republican Association, subsequently styled as the Hindustan Socialist Republican Association (HSRA) was founded in 1924 by",
            "optionA": "  Bhagat Singh ",
            "optionB": "  Chandra Shekhar Azad ",
            "optionC": "  Jogesh Chandra Chatterji ",
            "optionD": "  Sachindra Sanyal ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Hindustan Republican Association, subsequently styled as the Hindustan Socialist Republican Association (HSRA) was founded in 1924 by Sachindra Sanyal. ",
            "keyString": "252156s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main brain behind hurling a bomb at Lord Hardinge, while he was making his state entry into Delhi was",
            "optionA": "  Ras Behari Bose ",
            "optionB": "  Bhagat Singh ",
            "optionC": "  Sachindra Sanyal ",
            "optionD": "  Jatin Das ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Delhi Conspiracy case, also known as the Delhi-Lahore Conspiracy, refers to a conspiracy in 1912 to assassinate the then Viceroy of India, Lord Hardinge, on the occasion of transferring the capital of British India from Calcutta to New Delhi. Hatched by the Indian revolutionary underground in Bengal and Punjab and headed by Rashbehari Bose, the conspiracy culminated on the attempted assassination on 23 December 1912 when a homemade bomb was thrown into the Viceroys's Howdah when the ceremonial procession moved through the Chandni Chowk suburb of Delhi.",
            "keyString": "253089s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following personality is related with the \"Deepavali Declaration\"?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Irwin in 1929 ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Linlithgow in 1940 ",
            "optionC": "  Gandhiji in 1930 ",
            "optionD": "  Subhas Chandra Bose in 1941 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe \"DEEPAVALI DECLARATION\" passed during the tenure of Lord Irwin in 1929(just after simon comission 1928).It was just a show leaf to indians for dominion status that was to be not granted anywhere in the near future. ",
            "keyString": "253457s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The 'political philosophy' was the work of __________",
            "optionA": "  Gopala Krishna Gokhale ",
            "optionB": "  Dadabai Naoroji ",
            "optionC": "  R. ",
            "optionD": " Dutt ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGopal Krishna Gokhale was prominent leader of Indian Independence Movement. Gokhale's political thought revolves around the socio- political issues. He appreciated and welcomed the British rule in India. He was essentially a liberal thinker and preferred constitutional methods for attaining the goal of self government. ",
            "keyString": "253877s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A letter to the Mughal emperor Jahangir from King James I had been presented by",
            "optionA": "  Lord Clive ",
            "optionB": "  Sir Thomas Roe ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Curzon ",
            "optionD": "  Captain Hawkins ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t\u201cIn 1614 Sir Thomas Roe was instructed by James I to visit the court of Jahangir, Emperor Jahangir's letter to James I, King of England, 1617 A.D.It was named after Mughal Emperor Jahangir in 1610. ",
            "keyString": "254190s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1917 Anasuya Sarabhai had led the __________textile workers' strike",
            "optionA": "  Ahmedabad ",
            "optionB": "  Bombay ",
            "optionC": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionD": "  Malabar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSewa founder Ela Bhatt presided over the function. Exactly a century ago on December 4, 1917, 'Motaben' Anasuya Sarabhai had organized the textile labour force under one umbrella organization mentored by Mahatma Gandhi. Back in 1917 textile workers in Ahmedabad were demanding a 50% hike in plague bonus. ",
            "keyString": "426531s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The death of millions of Indian in frequent famines which visited India during the 19th century, were mainly due to",
            "optionA": "  overall shortage of food and its improper distribution ",
            "optionB": "  commercialisation of agriculture ",
            "optionC": "  poor purchasing power of the people due to their extreme poverty and rise in prices ",
            "optionD": "  unremunerative agriculture and fall in agricultural production ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe death of millions of Indian in frequent famines which visited India during the 19th century, were mainly due to poor purchasing power of the people due to their extreme poverty and rise in prices. ",
            "keyString": "427284s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following was the real founder of the Aligarh Muslim University?",
            "optionA": "  Nawab Salimullah ",
            "optionB": "  Syed Ahmad Khan ",
            "optionC": "  Abul Kalam Azad ",
            "optionD": "  Muhhammed Ali Jinnah ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Anglo\u2013Indian statesman Syed Ahmad Khan founded the predecessor of AMU, the Muhammadan Anglo Oriental College, in 1875 having already established two schools. The movement of Muslim awakening associated with Syed Ahmad Khan and M.A.O. College came to be known as Aligarh Movement. ",
            "keyString": "427639s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The revolutionary leader who had organized an attack on the armoury of Chittagong was",
            "optionA": "  Surya Sen ",
            "optionB": "  Jatin Das ",
            "optionC": "  Chandra Shekhar Azad ",
            "optionD": "  CR Das ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Chittagong armoury raid, also known as the Chittagong uprising, was an attempt on 18 April 1930 to raid the armoury of police and auxiliary forces from the Chittagong armoury in the Bengal Presidency of British India (now in Bangladesh) by armed Indian independence fighters led by Surya Sen. ",
            "keyString": "427688s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where was the 'Azad Hind Fauj' founded?",
            "optionA": "  Singapore ",
            "optionB": "  Thailand ",
            "optionC": "  Britain ",
            "optionD": "  Italy ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t\"Azad Hind fauz\" was founded in Singapore. The chief commander of Indian National Army(INA) was Subhash Chandra Bose. ",
            "keyString": "427709s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The use of the mother tongue in India in the law Court was permitted by",
            "optionA": "  Lord Hastings ",
            "optionB": "  Cornwallis ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Dalhousie ",
            "optionD": "  Bentinck ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe use of the mother tongue in India in the law Court was permitted by Bentinck. ",
            "keyString": "557590s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the Ilbert Bill intended for?",
            "optionA": "  To remove racial discrimination in employment ",
            "optionB": "  To enable India District Magistrates and Session Judges to try Europeans ",
            "optionC": "  To save Indians from racial humiliation ",
            "optionD": "  To change the method of recruitment in the Indian Civil Service ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Ilbert Bill was a bill introduced in 1883 during the Viceroyship of the Marquess of Ripon, which was written by Sir Courtenay Peregrine Ilbert (The law member of the Viceroy's Council). According to this act, Indian judges could try Europeans. ",
            "keyString": "560294s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Of the following who was not the leader of the Extremists?",
            "optionA": "  Lokamanya Tilak ",
            "optionB": "  Aurobindo Ghose ",
            "optionC": "  Lala Lajpat Rai ",
            "optionD": "  Hume ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHume was not the leader of the Extremists. ",
            "keyString": "560842s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who had observed that \"Political freedom is the life-breath of a nation\"?",
            "optionA": "  BG Tilak ",
            "optionB": "  Annie Besant ",
            "optionC": "  Sri Aurobindo Ghose ",
            "optionD": "  Rabindranath Tagore ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSri Aurobindo (born Aurobindo Ghose; 15 August 1872 \u2013 5 December 1950) was an Indian philosopher, yogi, guru, poet, and nationalist. He joined the Indian movement for independence from British rule, for a while was one of its influential leaders and then became a spiritual reformer, introducing his visions on human progress and spiritual evolution. Sri Aurobindo said that political freedom is the life breath of a nation. ",
            "keyString": "561358s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "SN Banerjee was appointed Professor in English in the Metropolitan Institute at",
            "optionA": "  Bombay ",
            "optionB": "  Madras ",
            "optionC": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionD": "  Bangalore ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUpon his return to India in June 1875, Banerjee became an English professor at the Metropolitan Institution, the Free Church Institution and at the Rippon College, now Surendranath College, founded by him in 1882. ",
            "keyString": "562702s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Assertion (A): The permanent settlement is said to have initially resulted in increased agricultural production.\nReason (R): In this system the Zamindar could keep for himself any increase in the rental of his estate",
            "optionA": "  Both A and R is true and R is the correct explanation of A ",
            "optionB": "  Both A and R is true but R is not a correct explanation of A ",
            "optionC": "  A is true but R is false ",
            "optionD": "  A is false but R is true ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Permanent Settlement, also known as the Permanent Settlement of Bengal, was an agreement between the East India Company and Bengali landlords to fix revenues to be raised from land, with far-reaching consequences for both agricultural methods and productivity in the entire British Empire and the political realities of the Indian countryside. ",
            "keyString": "693295s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who amidst the following great music composers was the ruler of a  State?",
            "optionA": "  Tyagaraja ",
            "optionB": "  Shyama Shastri ",
            "optionC": "  Muthu Swami Diskshitar ",
            "optionD": "  Swati Thirunal ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSwati Thirunal Rama Verma was the Maharaja of Travancore Kingdom of British India. He was a great musician of both carnatic and Hindustani music.",
            "keyString": "694199s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Muslim League passed a resolution demanding the partition of India in the __________ session held in 1940",
            "optionA": "  Lahore ",
            "optionB": "  Allahabad ",
            "optionC": "  Karachi ",
            "optionD": "  Dacca ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe resolution for the establishment of a separate homeland for the Muslims of British India passed in the annual session of the All India Muslim League held in Lahore on 22\u201324 March 1940 is a landmark document of Pakistan's history. ",
            "keyString": "695592s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The President of the Congress Sessions of 1898 and 1902 was",
            "optionA": "  Hume ",
            "optionB": "  Tilak ",
            "optionC": "  Dadabhai Naoroji ",
            "optionD": "  S. N. Banerjee ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBanerjee played a prominent role in the Indian National Congress from the time of its founding in 1885 in Bombay. Banerjee merged his organization with the INC, owing to their common objectives and memberships. He served as Congress President in 1895 and 1902. ",
            "keyString": "695659s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following was established by B. R. Ambedkar?",
            "optionA": "  Swaraj Party ",
            "optionB": "  Samaj Samata Party ",
            "optionC": "  All India Schedule Castes Federation ",
            "optionD": "  Congress Party ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tScheduled Castes Federation (SCF) was an organisation in India founded by B. R. Ambedkar in 1942 to campaign for the rights of the Dalit community. Ambedkar had founded the Depressed Classes Federation (DCF) in 1930 and the Independent Labour Party (ILP) in 1935. ",
            "keyString": "695681s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Gokhale was born in a Marathi Brahmin family at __________",
            "optionA": "  Ratnagiri ",
            "optionB": "  Poona ",
            "optionC": "  Allahabad ",
            "optionD": "  Assam ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGokhale was born in a Marathi Brahmin family at Ratnagiri. ",
            "keyString": "799326s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Prime causes of the 1857 mutiny did not include",
            "optionA": "  The new system of education ",
            "optionB": "  The Widow Remarriage Act ",
            "optionC": "  The despatch of Indian Sepoys to Afghanistan ",
            "optionD": "  Laws forbidding intermarriages between Indians and the British ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Prime causes of the 1857 mutiny did not include Laws forbidding intermarriages between Indians and the British. ",
            "keyString": "805550s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who established Narayana Gurukulam in 1923 in the Nilgiri Hills with the blessings of Narayana Guru?",
            "optionA": "  Nataraja Guru ",
            "optionB": "  Chattambi Swamikal ",
            "optionC": "  T. K. Madhavan ",
            "optionD": "  Dr. Palpu ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Nataraja Guru, introduced Guru's visions and ideals to the western world and established Narayana Gurukulam in 1923 in the Nilgiri Hills. ",
            "keyString": "806366s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first Indian who was elected to the leadership of the Communist International was",
            "optionA": "  SA Dange ",
            "optionB": "  SS Joshi ",
            "optionC": "  MN Roy ",
            "optionD": "  PC Joshi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first Indian who was elected to the leadership of the Communist International was MN Roy. Manabendra Nath Roy (21 March 1887 \u2013 26 January 1954), born Narendra Nath Bhattacharya, was an Indian revolutionary, radical activist and political theorist, as well as a noted philosopher in the 20th century. Roy was a founder of the Mexican Communist Party and the Communist Party of India. He was also a delegate to congresses of the Communist International and Russia's aide to China.",
            "keyString": "807345s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who had founded the Deccan Educational Society?",
            "optionA": "  Dadabhai Naoroji ",
            "optionB": "  CR Das ",
            "optionC": "  Swami Vivekananda ",
            "optionD": "  Mahadeva Govind Ranade ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahadev Govind Ranade (18 January 1842 - 16 January 1901) was an Indian scholar, social reformer and author. He had founded the Deccan Educational Society. ",
            "keyString": "808792s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the basis of transfer of power to India on 15th August?",
            "optionA": "  On this day the Indian National Congress had demanded \"Poorna Swaraj\" ",
            "optionB": "  On this day Mahatma Gandhi started 'Quit India Movement' ",
            "optionC": "  Anniversary of formation of Interim Government ",
            "optionD": "  Anniversary of the surrender of Japanese army before Admiral Mountbatten ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Mountbatten decided the date of Aug 15 for transfer of power to India, because it was at this day (Aug 15, 1945) Japanese Army in second world war surrendered before him. ",
            "keyString": "930922s21m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the other Congress leader who joined with Motilal Nehru to start the Swaraj Party in 1923?",
            "optionA": "  ",
            "optionB": " G. Tilak ",
            "optionC": "  Chittaranjan Das ",
            "optionD": "  M. K. Gandhi ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn December 1922, Chittaranjan Das, Narasimha Chintaman Kelkar and Motilal Nehru formed the Congress-Khilafat Swarajaya Party with Das as the president and Nehru as one of the secretaries. ",
            "keyString": "12695s22m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sardar Patel brought all the Indian States into the Country's unity",
            "optionA": "  By a bloody revolution ",
            "optionB": "  By using armed forces ",
            "optionC": "  By a bloodless revolution ",
            "optionD": "  With the help of the English ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t\"Sardar Patel is the symbol of India's unity. He had brought the country's 562 principalities under the fold of the union and had achieved this task within a very short span of 70 days through a bloodless revolution\". ",
            "keyString": "13279s22m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The formation of the Self Employed Women's Association (SEWA) at the initiative of __________ in 1972",
            "optionA": "  Ela Bhat ",
            "optionB": "  Roop Kanwar ",
            "optionC": "  Raja radhakant dev ",
            "optionD": "  Dwarkanath Tagore ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSEWA is a trade union registered in 1972. It is an organisation of poor, self-employed women workers. These are women who earn a living through their own labour or small businesses. They do not obtain regular salaried employment with welfare benefits like workers in the organised sector. ",
            "keyString": "14032s22m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Name the 'Political Guru' of Mahatma Gandhi",
            "optionA": "  Gopalkrishna Gokhle ",
            "optionB": "  Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "optionC": "  Aurobindo Ghosh ",
            "optionD": "  Lala Lajpat Rai ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGopal Krishna Gokhle was the \"Political Guru\" of Mahatma Gandhi. Gandhi Ji wrote a book \"Gokhle : My Political Guru\" ",
            "keyString": "14598s22m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following visited Gandhiji in South Africa?",
            "optionA": "  ",
            "optionB": " G. Tilak ",
            "optionC": "  Vallabhbhai Patel ",
            "optionD": "  G. K. Gokhale ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGopal Krishna Gokhale met Gandhiji in South Africa. He was the political guru of Mahatma Gandhi. ",
            "keyString": "22946s22m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "As per provisions of the Charter Act of 1833, a Law Commission (for consolidating, codifying and improving Indian laws) was constituted under the Chairmanship of",
            "optionA": "  Lord Benttick ",
            "optionB": "  Raja Rammohan Roy ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Macaulay ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Dalhousie ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFirst law Commission was established during the British Raj in 1834 by the Charter Act of 1833. Lord Macaulay was the Chairman of this Law Commission. ",
            "keyString": "309500s22m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Ganapati festival was started in __________",
            "optionA": "  1792 ",
            "optionB": "  1793 ",
            "optionC": "  1893 ",
            "optionD": "  1904 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1893, the Indian freedom fighter Lokmanya Tilak praised the celebration of sarvajanik Ganesha utsav in his newspaper, Kesari, and dedicated his efforts to launch the annual domestic festival into a large, well-organised public event. ",
            "keyString": "310000s22m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who scripted Gandhiji's favorite song 'Vaishnav Jan to __________ '?",
            "optionA": "  Narsi Mehta ",
            "optionB": "  Premanand ",
            "optionC": "  Chunilal ",
            "optionD": "  Dharmiklal ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNarsi Mehta composed the song (Vaishnav Jan to). He was also known as pillar of Gujarati literature.",
            "keyString": "313980s22m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A Royal Commission on the Public Service was appointed in the year",
            "optionA": "  1912 ",
            "optionB": "  1915 ",
            "optionC": "  1910 ",
            "optionD": "  1918 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIslington Commission, 1912 a Royal Commission formed to recommend reforms in the Public Service of British India with Lord Islington as its chairman. ",
            "keyString": "317076s22m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Battle of Plassey is a particularly important event in Indian history because",
            "optionA": "  The Nawab of Bengal lost in it ",
            "optionB": "  It enabled the British to have power in Bengal ",
            "optionC": "  It laid the foundation for British rule in India ",
            "optionD": "  It enabled the British to reap higher trade profits ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Battle of Plassey was a decisive victory of the British East India Company over the Nawab of Bengal and his French allies on 23 June 1757, under the leadership of Robert Clive. The battle consolidated the Company's presence in Bengal, which later expanded to cover much of India over the next hundred years. The Battle of Plassey is a particularly important event in Indian history because it laid the foundation for British rule in India. ",
            "keyString": "317649s22m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following was not one of the cardinal principles of Mahatma Gandhi doctrine of Satyagraha?",
            "optionA": "  Truthfulness ",
            "optionB": "  Non-Violence ",
            "optionC": "  Fearlessness ",
            "optionD": "  Abstinence ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFor Gandhi, satyagraha went far beyond mere \"passive resistance\" and became strength in practising non-violent methods. In his words: Truth (satya) implies love, and firmness (agraha) engenders and therefore serves as a synonym for force. Abstinence was not one of the cardinal principles of Mahatma Gandhi doctrine of Satyahraha. ",
            "keyString": "422630s22m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The only AICC session Gandhiji presided was held at",
            "optionA": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionB": "  Madras ",
            "optionC": "  Belgaum ",
            "optionD": "  Lahore ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe only AICC session Gandhi ji presided was the Belagam session of 1924. The Belagam session is known for the readmittance of the swarajist into the Congress. ",
            "keyString": "423131s22m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first organisation in the Madras Presidency to agitate for the rights of Indians was the Madras Native Association which was established by publicist __________ Chetty in 1849. This organisation did not survive for long and was eventually disbanded.",
            "optionA": "  Gazulu Lakshminarasu ",
            "optionB": "  S. Ramaswami Mudaliar ",
            "optionC": "  P. Anandacharlu ",
            "optionD": "  R. Balaji Rao ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first organisation in the Madras Presidency to agitate for the rights of Indians was the Madras Native Association which was established by publicist Gazulu Lakshminarasu Chetty in 1849. This organisation did not survive for long and was eventually disbanded. ",
            "keyString": "423567s22m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "To which personality Mahatma Gandhi gave the title \"Deen Bandhu\"?",
            "optionA": "  Sri Aurobindo ",
            "optionB": "  CF Andrews ",
            "optionC": "  Vinoba Bhave ",
            "optionD": "  CR Das ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTo CF Andrews Mahatma Gandhi gave the title \"Deen Bandhu\". ",
            "keyString": "424058s22m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Why was the Simon Commission boycotted?",
            "optionA": "  Simon was not known to be a great supporter of the Indian cause ",
            "optionB": "  All the members of the commission were Englishmen ",
            "optionC": "  It was appointed before the expiry of the statutory period ",
            "optionD": "  Peaceful demonstrators were severely beaten by the police ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Simon Commission was opposed primarily because it did not have any Indian representation in the assemblage. The government of Britain had appointed this Commission in 1927. The goal of the Simon Commission was to give an account of how the Indian constitution was working. All the members of the commission were Englishmen. ",
            "keyString": "614196s22m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who had formulated and perfected the use of the subsidiary alliance system?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Mayo ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Curzon ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Dalhousie ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Wellesley ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Subsidiary Alliance System was \u201cNon-Intervention Policy\u201d used by Lord Wellesley who was the Governor-General (1798-1805) to establish British Empire in India. According to this system, every ruler in India had to accept to pay a subsidy to the British for the maintenance of British army. ",
            "keyString": "615366s22m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following writers did not have a profound influence on the thinking of Mahatma Gandhi?",
            "optionA": "  Tolstoy ",
            "optionB": "  Thoreau ",
            "optionC": "  Ruskin ",
            "optionD": "  Marx ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWriter Marx did not have a profound influence on the thinking of Mahatma Gandhi. ",
            "keyString": "616033s22m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The word Pakistan was coined by",
            "optionA": "  Mohammed Iqbal ",
            "optionB": "  Jinnah ",
            "optionC": "  Abul Kalam Azad ",
            "optionD": "  Rahmat Ali ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe name of the country was coined in 1933 as Pakistan by Choudhry Rahmat Ali, a Pakistan Movement activist, who published it in his pamphlet Now or Never, using it as an acronym (\"thirty million Muslim brethren who live in PAKISTAN\") referring to the names of the five northern regions of British India. ",
            "keyString": "616524s22m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Provision was made in the Act of 1919, for the appointment of a Commission in __________ to investigate the working of the Constitution",
            "optionA": "  1930 ",
            "optionB": "  1929 ",
            "optionC": "  1939 ",
            "optionD": "  1925 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tProvision was made in the Act of 1919, for the appointment of a Commission in 1929 to investigate the working of the Constitution. ",
            "keyString": "617000s22m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which year was the partition of Bengal scrapped?",
            "optionA": "  1908 ",
            "optionB": "  1911 ",
            "optionC": "  1923 ",
            "optionD": "  1931 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe decision to effect the Partition of Bengal was announced in July 1905 by the Viceroy of India, Lord Curzon. The partition took effect in October 1905 and separated the largely Muslim eastern areas from the largely Hindu western areas. Indians were outraged at what they recognised as a \"divide and rule\" policy, where the colonisers turned the native population against itself in order to rule, even though Curzon stressed it would produce administrative efficiency. The partition animated the Hindus and led the Muslims to form their own national organization. Bengal was reunited in 1911. ",
            "keyString": "772707s22m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "PIassey is located near",
            "optionA": "  Murshidabad in West Bengal ",
            "optionB": "  Rajashahi in Bangladesh ",
            "optionC": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionD": "  Monghyr in Bihar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPalashi, also known as Plassey, is a village on the Hooghly River, located approximately 50 kilometres north of the city of Krishnanagar in Kaliganj CD Block in the Nadia District of West Bengal, India. ",
            "keyString": "773271s22m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which city of South Africa was Gandhi beaten up and thrown off the pavement by the white people?",
            "optionA": "  Cape town ",
            "optionB": "  Durban ",
            "optionC": "  Johannesburg ",
            "optionD": "  Pretoria ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGandhi arrived in Durban, Natal in 1893 to serve as legal council to a merchant Dada Abdullah, he asked him to under take a rail trip, where Gandhi was seated in first-Class compartment. A white person who entered the compartment hastened to summon the white railway officials and ordered Gandhi to remove himself, but herefused to comply with the order then a white police officer pushed him out of the train. ",
            "keyString": "773919s22m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said that \"My ultimate aim is to wipe every tear from every eye\"?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Curzon ",
            "optionB": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionC": "  Jawahar Lal Nehru ",
            "optionD": "  Daya Nand Saraswati ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJawahar Lal Nehru said that \"My ultimate aim is to wipe every tear from every eye\". ",
            "keyString": "774399s22m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Advaita Deepika is the work of __________",
            "optionA": "  Sree Narayana Guru ",
            "optionB": "  Chattambi Swamikal ",
            "optionC": "  ",
            "optionD": "Kesavan ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAdvaita Deepika is the work of Sree Narayana Guru. ",
            "keyString": "774866s22m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The author of 'A Nation in the Making' was",
            "optionA": "  SN Banerjee ",
            "optionB": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionC": "  Hume ",
            "optionD": "  Tilak ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSN Banerjee defeat at the polls in 1923 brought his political career to a close and he went on to write the widely acclaimed A Nation in Making, published in 1925. ",
            "keyString": "994486s22m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under pressure from his family, Nanu married__________, the daughter of a traditional village doctor",
            "optionA": "  Kaliamma ",
            "optionB": "  Kaliamma ",
            "optionC": "  Rohini ",
            "optionD": "  Meenkshi Amma ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder pressure from his family, Nanu married Kaliamma, the daughter of a traditional village doctor. The marriage was a simple affair with the groom's sisters themselves investing the bride with the 'Thaali' (wedding knot) on his behalf. The bride remained with her parents, since Nanu asan became a wanderer not long after. ",
            "keyString": "994999s22m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one among the following pairs of battle is correctly matched?",
            "optionA": "  The 2nd battle of Tarain : Defeat of Jaichand\u00a0of Kannauj by Muhammad Ghori ",
            "optionB": "  The first battle of Panipat :\u00a0Defeat of Sikander Lodi by Babur ",
            "optionC": "  The battle of Chausa : Defeat of Humayun by SherShah ",
            "optionD": "  The battle of Khanwa :\u00a0Defeat of Rana Pratap by Akbar ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Battle of Chausa was a notable military engagement between the Mughal emperor, Humayun, and the Afghan, Sher Shah Suri. It was fought on 26 June 1539 at Chausa, 10 miles southwest of Buxar in modern-day Bihar, India. Sher Shah was victorious and crowned himself Farid al-Din Sher Shah. ",
            "keyString": "995481s22m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The famous resolution on Non-Cooperation under the inspiration of Mahatma Gandhi was adopted in a special session of Congress held at Calcutta in",
            "optionA": "  September 1920. ",
            "optionB": "  December 1922. ",
            "optionC": "  October 1924. ",
            "optionD": "  November 1925. ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe famous resolution on Non-Cooperation under the inspiration of Mahatma Gandhi was adopted in a special session of Congress held at Calcutta in September 1920. ",
            "keyString": "996222s22m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sindhia's troops were defeated by General Wellesley at",
            "optionA": "  Bessein ",
            "optionB": "  Assaye ",
            "optionC": "  Tanjore ",
            "optionD": "  Poona ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe battle of Assaye, fought on September 23, 1803 between the Maratha and British armies, is largely forgotten in India. Yet it remains an amazing story of gallantry and skill on both sides. Assaye was a hard-won victory for the British, one that challenges common assumptions about how Europeans conquered the subcontinent. ",
            "keyString": "996795s22m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which town/city in India has got a tower (minar) named after Muhammad Ali Jinnah?",
            "optionA": "  Mumbai ",
            "optionB": "  Aligarh ",
            "optionC": "  Calicut ",
            "optionD": "  Guntur ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJinnah tower is a landmark monument in the city of Guntur in Andhra Pradesh. It is a Symbol of Peace and harmony. ",
            "keyString": "128943s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Provision was made by the Charter Act of 1813 for the establishment of a Church at __________",
            "optionA": "  Madras ",
            "optionB": "  Bombay ",
            "optionC": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionD": "  Pondicherry ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Charter Act of 1813 marked an important stage in the later history of East India company of India. This inclided provisions for the creation of an anglican church establishment in Calcutta, the opening-up of the country to Christian missionaries, and the encouragement of the Indian education. ",
            "keyString": "129390s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which state was the first non-Congress Government set up in independent India?",
            "optionA": "  Punjab ",
            "optionB": "  Bihar ",
            "optionC": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionD": "  Kerala ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1957, CPI defeated congress in legislative assembly elections in the southern state of Kerala and formed the first non-congress government in independent India. ",
            "keyString": "129806s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the first Indian ruler to apply the western methods to his administration?",
            "optionA": "  Haider Ali ",
            "optionB": "  Tipu Sultan ",
            "optionC": "  Murshid Quli Khan ",
            "optionD": "  Malhar Rao Holkar ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTipu Sultan was the first indian ruler to apply the western methods to his administration. Sultan Fateh Ali Sahab Tipu, also known as the Tipu Sahib, was a ruler of the Kingdom of Mysore. ",
            "keyString": "130212s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1946, the Interim Government was formed under",
            "optionA": "  Patel ",
            "optionB": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionC": "  Rajaji ",
            "optionD": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1946, the Interim Government was formed under Jawaharlal Nehru. ",
            "keyString": "130681s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Purna Swaraj was declared as the goal of the Congress in the Congress session held at Lahore under the Presidentship of",
            "optionA": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionB": "  CR Das ",
            "optionC": "  Maulana Abul Kalam Azad ",
            "optionD": "  Gokhale ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPurna Swaraj was declared as the goal of the Congress in the Congress session held at Lahore under the Presidentship of Jawaharlal Nehru. ",
            "keyString": "229936s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Government of India Act of 1919 made provision for the appointment of a/an __________ for India in the United Kingdom",
            "optionA": "  Ambassador ",
            "optionB": "  Council ",
            "optionC": "  High Commissioner ",
            "optionD": "  Indian Member in the parliament of England ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGovernment of India Act 1919 - An Act to make further provision with respect to the Government of India. The Government of India Act 1919 was an Act of the Parliament of the United Kingdom. It was passed to expand participation of Indians in the government of India. ",
            "keyString": "229980s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the author of 'Esoteric Christianity'?",
            "optionA": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionB": "  J. Krishnamurti ",
            "optionC": "  Sarala Devi Chaudhurani ",
            "optionD": "  Annie Besant ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnnie Besant was the author of 'Esoteric Christianity'. ",
            "keyString": "230003s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1893 __________ landed in India, made a tour of the country in the company of H. S. Olcott, and by her splendid presentation of Indian philosophy and her undisguised personal preference for the Indian spiritual heritage, won the support of orthodox Brahmins to Theosophy",
            "optionA": "  Annie Besant ",
            "optionB": "  Upendranath Basu ",
            "optionC": "  I. N. Gurtu ",
            "optionD": "  George Thompson ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1893 Annie Besant landed in India, made a tour of the country in the company of H. S. Olcott, and by her splendid presentation of Indian philosophy and her undisguised personal preference for the Indian spiritual heritage, won the support of orthodox Brahmins to Theosophy.The transformation of the religious life in India, particularly among Hindus, is one of the wonders she performed. ",
            "keyString": "230024s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Cabinet Mission Plan ruled out the possibility of the formation of",
            "optionA": "  Union of India ",
            "optionB": "  Pakistan ",
            "optionC": "  Constituent Assembly ",
            "optionD": "  Groups by Provinces ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Cabinet Mission Plan ruled out the possibility of the formation of Pakistan. ",
            "keyString": "230042s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Home Rule League was formed during the",
            "optionA": "  First World War ",
            "optionB": "  Partition of Bengal ",
            "optionC": "  Struggle following the Jallianwala Bagh Massacre ",
            "optionD": "  Implementation of Minto-Morley Reforms ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHome Rule League, either of two short-lived organizations of the same name in India established in April and September 1916, respectively, by Indian nationalist Bal Gangadhar Tilak and British social reformer and Indian independence leader Annie Besant during first world war. ",
            "keyString": "325455s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel was the leader of__________",
            "optionA": "  Bhoodan Movement ",
            "optionB": "  Rowlatt Satyagraha ",
            "optionC": "  Bardoli Satyagraha ",
            "optionD": "  Swadeshi Movement ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Bardoli Satyagraha of 1928, in the state of Gujarat, India during the period of the British Raj, was a major episode of civil disobedience and revolt in the Indian Independence Movement. The movement was eventually led by Vallabhbhai Patel, and its success gave rise to Patel becoming one of the main leaders of the independence movement. ",
            "keyString": "326038s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The immortal national Song 'Vande Mataram' has been written by",
            "optionA": "  Rabindranath Tagore ",
            "optionB": "  Sarat Chandra Chattopadhyaya ",
            "optionC": "  Bankim Chandra Chattopadhyaya ",
            "optionD": "  Surendranath Bandopadhyaya ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNational Song \"Vande Mataram\" is a part of Anand Math written by Bankim Chandra Chattopadhyaya. ",
            "keyString": "326547s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Before the passing of the Act of 1773, each of the three English Settlement in India was governed by",
            "optionA": "  Viceroy ",
            "optionB": "  President ",
            "optionC": "  Secretary ",
            "optionD": "  Director ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBefore the passing of the Act of 1773, each of the three English Settlement in India was governed by President. ",
            "keyString": "327066s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following was the most important feature of the Montague-Chelmsford reforms?",
            "optionA": "  Self-government ",
            "optionB": "  The Factory Act ",
            "optionC": "  System of Dyarchy ",
            "optionD": "  Transfer of Power of Congress ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDyarchy, also spelled diarchy, system of double government introduced by the Government of India Act (1919) for the provinces of British India. Dyarchy was introduced as a constitutional reform by Edwin Samuel Montagu (secretary of state for India, 1917\u201322) and Lord Chelmsford (viceroy of India, 1916\u201321). ",
            "keyString": "327598s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Azad Hind Fauz or the Indian National Army (INA) was founded by",
            "optionA": "  Subhash Bose ",
            "optionB": "  Rash Behari Bose ",
            "optionC": "  General Mohan Singh ",
            "optionD": "  Shah Nawaz ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKuala Lumpur fell on 11 January 1942 with 3,500 Indian prisoners of war, and Singapore on 15 February with 85,000 British troops, of whom 45,000 were Indians. Mohan Singh asked for volunteers who would form the Azad Hind Fauj (Free India Army) to fight for Indian independence from the British rule. ",
            "keyString": "433367s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Madam Bhikaji Cama unfolded the National Flag of India in 1907 at",
            "optionA": "  India House, London ",
            "optionB": "  International Socialist Congress Stuttgart ",
            "optionC": "  Vande Mataram Office at San Francisco ",
            "optionD": "  Indian Workers Meet Vancouver ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t\u201cBehold, the flag of independent India is born! It has been made sacred by the blood of young Indians who sacrificed their lives in its honour. In the name of this flag, I appeal to lovers of freedom all over the world to support this struggle.\u201d \u2013 Bhikaji Cama. Madam Bhikaji Cama unfolded the National Flag of India in 1907 at International Socialist Congress Stuttgart. ",
            "keyString": "433626s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A focal point of all revolutionary activities in London was",
            "optionA": "  India House ",
            "optionB": "  Kaiser House ",
            "optionC": "  Singh Sabha Building ",
            "optionD": "  Dadabhai Naoroji's House ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA focal point of all revolutionary activities in London was India House. ",
            "keyString": "433812s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The last of the Charter Act concerning India was the Act of",
            "optionA": "  1773 ",
            "optionB": "  1813 ",
            "optionC": "  1853 ",
            "optionD": "  1793 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCharter Act of 1853 was the last charter act passed for East India Company. It was passed on expiry of charter act of 1833. The charter was renewed but no substantial changes were made. ",
            "keyString": "434880s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which day was declared as the 'Direct Action Day' by the Muslim League?",
            "optionA": "  3rd September, 1946 ",
            "optionB": "  16th August, 1946 ",
            "optionC": "  16th May, 1946 ",
            "optionD": "  4th Decembar, 1946 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 16th August,1946 Direct Action Day was declared, the day also known as the Great Calcutta killings. Itwas a day of widespread riots and manslaughter between Hindus and Muslims in Bengal. ",
            "keyString": "435304s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The social reformer of Maharashtra who became famous by his pen name lokhitwadi was",
            "optionA": "  Atmaram Panduranga ",
            "optionB": "  Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "optionC": "  Gopal Hari Deshmukh ",
            "optionD": "  KS Chaplunkar ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGopal Hari Deshmukh (18 February 1823 \u2013 9 October 1892) was an Indian activist, thinker, social reformer and writer from Maharashtra. His original surname was Shidhaye. Because of 'Vatan' (right of Tax collection) that the family had received,the family was later called Deshmukh. Deshmukh is regarded as an important figure of the Social Reform Movement in Maharashtra. ",
            "keyString": "546416s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Tomar Rajputs, were defeated in the middle of the twelfth century by the Chauhans of __________",
            "optionA": "  Ayodhya ",
            "optionB": "  Ajmer ",
            "optionC": "  Gwalior ",
            "optionD": "  Dwarka ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Tomar Rajputs, were defeated in the middle of the twelfth century by the Chauhans of Ajmer. ",
            "keyString": "546741s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The State, from among the following, which was not annexed by the 'doctrine of lapse' is",
            "optionA": "  Baghat ",
            "optionB": "  Gwalior ",
            "optionC": "  Sambalpur ",
            "optionD": "  Satara ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe company took over the princely states of Satara (1848), Jaitpur and Sambalpur (1849), Nagpur and Jhansi (1854), Tore and Arcot (1855) and Udaipur (Chhattisgarh) under the terms of the doctrine of lapse. Oudh (1856) is widely believed to have under the Doctrine of Lapse. The State which was not annexed by the 'doctrine of lapse' is Gwalior. ",
            "keyString": "546961s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Headquarters of the Ramakrishna Math and Mission established by Vivekananda in 1898 are at",
            "optionA": "  Kanyakumari ",
            "optionB": "  Belur ",
            "optionC": "  Hyderabad ",
            "optionD": "  Murshidabad ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRamakrishna Mission (RKM) is a Hindu religious and spiritual organisation which forms the the core of a worldwide spiritual movement known as the Ramakrishna Movement or the Vedanta Movement. The headquarters of Ramakrishna Math at Belur ( popularly known as Belur Math). It was at Belur Math that Swami Vivekananda (1863-1902), the foremost disciple of Sri Ramakrishna (1836-1886), lived the last years of his brief life. ",
            "keyString": "547166s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said \"Sir Saiyad was an ardent reformer and he wanted to reconcile modern scientific thought with religion by rationalistic interpretations and not by attacking basic belief. He was anxious to push new education. He was in no way communally separatist. Repeatedly he emphasized that religious differences should have no political and national significance\"",
            "optionA": "  Inder Kumar Gujral ",
            "optionB": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionC": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionD": "  Mohammad Iqbal ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJawaharlal Nehru said \"Sir Saiyad was an ardent reformer and he wanted to reconcile modern scientific thought with religion by rationalistic interpretations and not by attacking basic belief. He was anxious to push new education. He was in no way communally separatist. Repeatedly he emphasized that religious differences should have no political and national significance\". ",
            "keyString": "547351s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "After leaving the Congress, Subhash Chandra Bose formed, in 1939, his own party, named",
            "optionA": "  Socialist Bloc ",
            "optionB": "  Revolutionary Socialist Bloc ",
            "optionC": "  Forward Bloc ",
            "optionD": "  Socialist-Congress Bloc ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSubhash Chandra Bose was an Indian Nationalist, he had been a leader of Indian National Congress in the late 1920's and 1930's and leaving from Congress leadership positions in 1939 due to dispute with Gandhiji and formed a new party named Forward bloc. ",
            "keyString": "628193s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is considered the Magna Carta of the Indian people?",
            "optionA": "  The Government of India Act, 1858 ",
            "optionB": "  The Ilbert Bill ",
            "optionC": "  Indian Councils Act of 1892 ",
            "optionD": "  Queen Victoria's Proclamation ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tQueen Victoria's proclamation assumed the character of a Magna Carta which was often referred to by Indian nationalists. ",
            "keyString": "628878s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Diwani Adalat was presided over by",
            "optionA": "  Collector ",
            "optionB": "  Governor ",
            "optionC": "  Resident ",
            "optionD": "  Nawabs ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the Diwani Adalat, the Collector was to preside assisted by this 'native dewan'. ",
            "keyString": "629426s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "An emigre (a person or thing who/which has emigrated) communist journal brought out by M N Roy was",
            "optionA": "  Anushilan ",
            "optionB": "  The Worker ",
            "optionC": "  Kisan Sabha ",
            "optionD": "  Vanguard ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAn emigre (a person or thing who/which has emigrated) communist journal brought out by M N Roy was Vanguard. ",
            "keyString": "629919s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who designed the national flag of Independent India?",
            "optionA": "  Bankim Chandra Chatterjee ",
            "optionB": "  Rabindranath Tagore ",
            "optionC": "  Mahatma Ghandhi ",
            "optionD": "  Pingali Venkaiya ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGandhi Ji first proposed a flag to the Indian National congress in 1921, after that Pingali Venkaiya designed the National flag, in the centre was traditional spinning wheel, symbolising Gandhi's goal of making Indians self reliant India adopted it on 22 July 1942. ",
            "keyString": "630377s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following had attended all the three Round Table Conferences in London?",
            "optionA": "  M. K. Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  ",
            "optionC": " R. Ambedkar ",
            "optionD": "  J. L. Nehru ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAmbedkar and Tej Bahadur Sapru took part in all the three round table conferences. ",
            "keyString": "712979s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following incident ended the historic fast of Gandhi?",
            "optionA": "  Poona Pact ",
            "optionB": "  Issue of White Paper ",
            "optionC": "  Gandhi-Irwin Pact ",
            "optionD": "  Arrival of Simon Commission ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPoona Pact was an agreement between Dr. Bhimrao Ambedkar and Mahatma Gandhi signed on September 24, 1932. This pact ended Gandhi's fast unto death. ",
            "keyString": "714043s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who started the journal 'The Commonweal'?",
            "optionA": "  N. G. Chandavarkar ",
            "optionB": "  Annie Besant ",
            "optionC": "  M. G. Ranade ",
            "optionD": "  R. G. Bhandarkar ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnnie Besant is responsible for introducing two journals: The Commonweal and New India, while the former was a weekly that looked into issues related to national reform, the latter was a daily newspaper that went on for fifteen years. It was a powerful newspaper that spread the idea of revolutionizing journalism and encouraged Home Rule Movement. ",
            "keyString": "714594s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The partition of Bengal had to be annulled in __________",
            "optionA": "  1907 ",
            "optionB": "  1911 ",
            "optionC": "  1928 ",
            "optionD": "  1929 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe partition of Bengal had to be annulled in 1911. ",
            "keyString": "716670s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "After Tilak's deportation which of the following extremist leaders was not similarly deported to Mandalay prison in Burma?",
            "optionA": "  Lala Lajpat Rai ",
            "optionB": "  Bipin Chandra Pal ",
            "optionC": "  Aswini Kumar Datta ",
            "optionD": "  CR Das ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter Tilak's deportation CR Das extremist leader was not similarly deported to Mandalay prison in Burma. ",
            "keyString": "718049s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Simon Commission was formed to review",
            "optionA": "  Legislatures in India ",
            "optionB": "  Fitness of India for further reforms ",
            "optionC": "  The position of the viceroy ",
            "optionD": "  A constitution for India ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Simon Commission was formed to review the working of Government of India Act, 1919 and suggest further constitutional and administrative reforms in the British colonial rule of India. ",
            "keyString": "796430s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Assertion (A): English was taken as the medium of instruction in India by the William Bentinck. \nReason (R): William Bentinck wanted to promote western culture in India",
            "optionA": "  Both A and R is true and R is the correct explanation of A ",
            "optionB": "  Both A and R is true but R is not a correct explanation of A ",
            "optionC": "  A is true but R is false ",
            "optionD": "  A is false but R is true ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWilliam Bentinck reformed the finances, opened up judicial posts to Indians, and suppressed such practices as sati, or widow burning, and thuggee, or ritual murder by robber gangs. The innovations effected in his years of office were milestones in creating a much more interventionist style of government than preceding ones, a style that involved the westernization of Indian society and culture. He introduced English in India. ",
            "keyString": "797020s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Rowlatt after whom Rowlatt Act was named was a",
            "optionA": "  Justice ",
            "optionB": "  General ",
            "optionC": "  Member of Parliament ",
            "optionD": "  Secretary of State for India ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPassed on the recommendations of the Rowlatt Committee and named after its president, British judge Sir Sidney Rowlatt, this act effectively authorized the government to imprison any person suspected of terrorism living in British India for up to two years without a trial, and gave the imperial authorities power to deal with all revolutionary activities. ",
            "keyString": "797529s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following system of land settlement adopted by the English did provide more protection\nto the interest of farmers?",
            "optionA": "  Permanent Settlement of Bengal ",
            "optionB": "  Ryotwari Settlement of Madras ",
            "optionC": "  Zamindari Settlement of Central States ",
            "optionD": "  Malgujari (land revenue) Settlement of United\nState ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRyotwari Settlement of Madras was the land settlement system adopted by the English to provide moreprotection to the interests of farmers. Under the Ryotwari System, settlement of land revenue was made directly between the government and the ryots the cultivator. ",
            "keyString": "798058s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Swami Vivekananda was born in an affluent family in __________ on 12 January 1863",
            "optionA": "  Bombay ",
            "optionB": "  Ajmer ",
            "optionC": "  Kolkata ",
            "optionD": "  Orrisa ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSwamiji was born on 12 January 1863 in Calcutta (now Kolkata). Swami Vivekananda died on 4 July, 1902 in Kolkata. ",
            "keyString": "798527s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following treaties brought an end to the independent existence of Peshwa Baji Rao-II?",
            "optionA": "  The Treaty of Purandhar ",
            "optionB": "  Convention of Wadgaon ",
            "optionC": "  Treaty of Bassein ",
            "optionD": "  Treaty of Salbai ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBaji Rao-II was the last Peshwa of the Maratha Empire who governed from 1795 to 1818. He was installed as a puppet ruler by the Maratha Nobles, whose growing power prompted him to flee his capital and sign the treaty of Bassein 1802 with British. ",
            "keyString": "905814s23m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Rowlatt Act was passed in the year",
            "optionA": "  1919 ",
            "optionB": "  1925 ",
            "optionC": "  1927 ",
            "optionD": "  1930 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Anarchical and Revolutionary Crimes Act of 1919 , popularly known as the Rowlatt Act or Black Act, was a legislative act passed by the Imperial Legislative Council in Delhi on 10 March 1919, indefinitely extending the emergency measures of preventive indefinite detention, incarceration without trial and judicial review enacted in the Defence of India Act 1915 during the First World War. ",
            "keyString": "66187s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "India attained 'Dominion  status' on",
            "optionA": "  15th January, 1947 ",
            "optionB": "  15th August, 1947 ",
            "optionC": "  15th August, 1950 ",
            "optionD": "  15th October, 1947 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia attained \"Dominion Status\" on 15 Aug 1947 by the Mountbattan plan, two dominian state came in existence first Pakistan (14th August 1947) and second India (15th August 1947). ",
            "keyString": "66287s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the first Indian Governor General of India?",
            "optionA": "  ",
            "optionB": " R. Ambedkar ",
            "optionC": "  ",
            "optionD": " Raja Gopalachari ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tC Raja Gopalachari became the only and the first Indian Governor General of Independent India. ",
            "keyString": "67235s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The INC for the first time passed the resolutions on Swaraj, Boycott and National Education at its annual session held at",
            "optionA": "  Banaras (1905) ",
            "optionB": "  Calcutta (1906) ",
            "optionC": "  Surat (1907) ",
            "optionD": "  Madras (1908) ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe INC (Indian National Congress) for the first time passed the resolutions on Swaraj, Boycott and National Education at its annual session held atCalcutta (1906). ",
            "keyString": "68427s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When did the Cripps Mission, which had practically repeated the August Offer 1940 visit India?",
            "optionA": "  1941 ",
            "optionB": "  1942 ",
            "optionC": "  1943 ",
            "optionD": "  1944 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Cripps Mission was a failed attempt in late March 1942 by the British government to secure full Indian cooperation and support for their efforts in World War II. ",
            "keyString": "68555s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The sole representative of the Congress in the Second Round Table Conference was",
            "optionA": "  Subhas Chandra Bose ",
            "optionB": "  Sir Tej Bahadur Sapru ",
            "optionC": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionD": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahatma Gandhi was the sole representative of the Indian National Congress at the Second Round Table Conference held at London in 1931. ",
            "keyString": "145605s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1908, Bal Gangadhar Tilak was imprisoned for six years and sent to",
            "optionA": "  Mandalay ",
            "optionB": "  Delhi ",
            "optionC": "  Singapore ",
            "optionD": "  Andaman and Nicobar Island ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTilak was sentenced to a jail term from 1908 to 1914 in Mandalay in Burma. While in prison, Tilak read and wrote extensively and developed his ideas on the Indian nationalism movement. ",
            "keyString": "146021s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Province of Bengal was partitioned into two parts in 1905 by",
            "optionA": "  Lord Lytton ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Ripon ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Dufferin ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Curzon ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Partition was made on 16 oct,1905 by Lord Curzon, the first Partition in Bengal was implemented as an administrative making governing the two provinces, West and East Bengal (Bengali- Hindu or Bengali- Muslim). ",
            "keyString": "146437s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In the . . . . . . Provinces were allowed to form groups with common executives and legislatures",
            "optionA": "  Wavell Plan ",
            "optionB": "  Dikie Bird Plan ",
            "optionC": "  Cabinet Mission Plan ",
            "optionD": "  Mountbatten Plan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Cabinet Mission of 1946 came to India aimed to discuss the transfer of power from the British government to the Indian leadership, with the aim of preserving India's unity and granting it independence.",
            "keyString": "146841s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mahatma Gandhi got his inspiration for Civil Disobedience from",
            "optionA": "  Thoureau ",
            "optionB": "  Ruskin ",
            "optionC": "  Confucius ",
            "optionD": "  Tolstoy ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGandhiji got his inspiration of 'Civil Disobedience' after reading the Thoureau's essay on duty of Civil disobedience movement. ",
            "keyString": "147438s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following was the 'Newspaper' of Annie Besant?",
            "optionA": "  The Hindu ",
            "optionB": "  Indian Express ",
            "optionC": "  The Times of India ",
            "optionD": "  New India ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1914, Annie Besant purchased an Indian newspaper, the Madras Standard, and on August 1 of that year changed its name to New India. ",
            "keyString": "263472s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In the Battle of Buxar the English army was commanded by",
            "optionA": "  Major Munro ",
            "optionB": "  Clive ",
            "optionC": "  Rojer Drake ",
            "optionD": "  Boughton ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Battle of Buxar was fought on 22 October 1764, during the Bengal War was between the forces under the command of the British East India Company, led by Hector Munro, and the combined armies of Mir Qasim, Nawab of Bengal till 1763; the Nawab of Awadh; and the Mughal Emperor Shah Alam II. ",
            "keyString": "263974s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Sikhs were defeated by the English at __________ in 1856",
            "optionA": "  Sobraon ",
            "optionB": "  Amritsar ",
            "optionC": "  Lahore ",
            "optionD": "  Kashmir ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Battle of Sobraon was fought on 10 February 1846, between the forces of the East India Company and the Sikh Khalsa Army, the army of the Sikh Empire of the Punjab. The Sikhs were completely defeated, making this the decisive battle of the First Anglo-Sikh War. ",
            "keyString": "264666s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following was not included in the early three English Settlements in India?",
            "optionA": "  Madras ",
            "optionB": "  The Punjab ",
            "optionC": "  Bombay ",
            "optionD": "  Calcutta ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Punjab was not included in the early three English Settlements in India. ",
            "keyString": "264734s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following tribal rebellions did two tribal brothers, Kanhu and Sidhu, proclaim the end of the Company's rule in their region, and to supress their rebellion the government had to use military force?",
            "optionA": "  Khasi Rebellion in Assam (1855)  ",
            "optionB": "  Naika Tribal Uprising in Gujarat (1868) ",
            "optionC": "  Munda Rebellion in Ranchi (1899) ",
            "optionD": "  Santhal Rebellion in Bihar (1855-56) ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Santhal rebellion (sometimes referred to as the Sonthal rebellion), commonly known as Santhal Hool, was a native rebellion in present-day Jharkhand, in eastern India against both the British colonial authority and zamindari system by the Santhal people. It started on June 30, 1855 and on November 10, 1855 martial law was proclaimed which lasted until January 3, 1856 when martial law was suspended and the movement was brutally ended by troops loyal to the British. The rebellion was led by the four Murmu Brothers - Sidhu, Kanhu, Chand and Bhairav. ",
            "keyString": "265155s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Long years ago we made a tryst with destiny and now the time comes when we shall redeem our pledge\" - this was stated on the night of August 14, 1947 by",
            "optionA": "  Dr. B R Ambedkar ",
            "optionB": "  C Raja Gopalchari ",
            "optionC": "  Jawaharlal Neheru ",
            "optionD": "  Dr. Rajendra Prasad ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJawaharlal Nehru stated this on the night of 14 Aug, 1947. ",
            "keyString": "377381s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Of the following who did not oppose the Non-cooperation resolution?",
            "optionA": "  C R Das ",
            "optionB": "  Madan Mohan Malaviya ",
            "optionC": "  Mrs Besant ",
            "optionD": "  Nehru ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Non-cooperation movement was withdrawn because of the Chauri Chaura incident. Although he had stopped the national revolt single-handedly, on 10 March 1922, Gandhi was arrested. Motilal Nehru and Chittaranjan Das formed the Swaraj Party, rejecting Gandhi's leadership. ",
            "keyString": "380927s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following was the first to sign the 'Instruments of Accession'?",
            "optionA": "  The Maharaja of Baroda ",
            "optionB": "  The Dewan of Travancore ",
            "optionC": "  The Nizam of Hyderabad ",
            "optionD": "  The Raja of Jodhpur ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tInstrument of Accession was a legal document first introduced by Government of India Act, 1935. It was used in and after 1947 to enable each of rulers of princely states under British parliamentary to join one of the new dominions of India or Pakistan. Dewan of Travancore was the first to sign 'Instrument of Accession'. ",
            "keyString": "381134s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following leader headed the interim Government of 1946?",
            "optionA": "  ",
            "optionB": " Rajagopalachari ",
            "optionC": "  M.K Gandhi ",
            "optionD": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Viceroy's Executive Council became the executive branch of the interim government. Originally headed by the Viceroy of India, it was transformed into a council of ministers, with the powers of a prime minister bestowed on the vice-president of the Council, a position held by the Congress leader Jawaharlal Nehru. ",
            "keyString": "381236s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The United Nations declared __________ as the International Year of Women",
            "optionA": "  1875 ",
            "optionB": "  1878 ",
            "optionC": "  1975 ",
            "optionD": "  1956 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tInternational Women's Year (IWY) was the name given to 1975 by the United Nations. Since that year March 8 has been celebrated as International Women's Day, and the United Nations Decade for Women, from 1976 to 1985, was also established. ",
            "keyString": "381329s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Gandhiji considered Khadi as a symbol of",
            "optionA": "  Industrialisation ",
            "optionB": "  Economic independence ",
            "optionC": "  Economic growth ",
            "optionD": "  Moral purity ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKhadi was used a symbol of economic independence and promoted in Vijayawada session of INC (1921). ",
            "keyString": "517722s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following institutions was not founded by Gandhi?",
            "optionA": "  Sevagram Ashram ",
            "optionB": "  Ramakrishna Mission ",
            "optionC": "  Phoenix Ashram ",
            "optionD": "  Sabarmati Ashram ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRamakrishna Mission (RKM) is a Hindu religious and spiritual organisation which forms the core of a worldwide spiritual movement known as the Ramakrishna Movement or the Vedanta Movement. The mission is named after and inspired by the Indian saint Ramakrishna Paramahamsa and founded by Ramakrishna's chief disciple Swami Vivekananda on 1 May 1897. ",
            "keyString": "518344s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indian Association formed in __________ was one of the pioneer political associations with an all India outlook",
            "optionA": "  1769 ",
            "optionB": "  1776 ",
            "optionC": "  1874 ",
            "optionD": "  1876 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian Association formed in 1876 was one of the pioneer political associations with an all India outlook. During the second half of the 19th century India witnessed marked changes in social and economic life. ",
            "keyString": "518520s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "On April 12, 1944 Subhash Chandra Bose hoisted the INA Flag in a town. In which State/Union Territory is that town now?",
            "optionA": "  Tripura ",
            "optionB": "  Culcutta ",
            "optionC": "  Manipur ",
            "optionD": "  Mizoram ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMoirang is a city and Municipal council in the state of Manipur where Subhash Chandra Bose hoisted the INA flag. During world war-II Moirang was the head quarters of Azad Hind Fauz, colonel Shaukat Malik of INA hoisted the Tri-colour for the first on Indian soil on 14 April 1944 in Moirang with the help of Manipuris. ",
            "keyString": "518681s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "China invaded Indian frontiers in the year __________",
            "optionA": "  1956 ",
            "optionB": "  1960 ",
            "optionC": "  1962 ",
            "optionD": "  1965 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tExactly 55 years ago, a full-fledge war broke out between India and China. The Sino-India war began on October 20, 1962 when the People's Liberation Army of China invaded Ladakh and Arunachal Pradesh (then known as the North East Frontier Agency) in a synchronised move. ",
            "keyString": "518840s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Golden Jubilee of the Indian National Congress (1885-1935) fell in 1935, which was observed during the session  held at",
            "optionA": "  Karachi ",
            "optionB": "  Lucknow ",
            "optionC": "  Faizpur ",
            "optionD": "  Nowhere ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Golden Jubilee of the Indian National Congress (1885-1935) fell in 1935, which was observed during the session held at nowhere. ",
            "keyString": "661900s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mahatma Gandhi had been joined the Champaran struggle by",
            "optionA": "  Vallabhbhai Patel and Vinoba Bhave ",
            "optionB": "  Rajendra Prasad and Anugraha Narayan Sinha ",
            "optionC": "  Mahadev Desai and Maniben Patel ",
            "optionD": "  Rajendra Prasad and Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahatma Gandhi had been joined the Champaran struggle by Rajendra Prasad and Anugraha Narayan Sinha. The Champaran Satyagraha of 1917 was the first Satyagraha movement inspired by Gandhi. The Champaran Satyagraha gave direction to India's youth and freedom struggle.",
            "keyString": "661936s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Guru died on 20 September, __________",
            "optionA": "  1902 ",
            "optionB": "  1908 ",
            "optionC": "  1918 ",
            "optionD": "  1928 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 20 September 1928, Sree Narayana Guru, great social and religious reformer from Kerala died at Sivagiri, Kerala. ",
            "keyString": "661951s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1913 . . . . . founded the Advaita Ashram at Aluva.",
            "optionA": "  Narayana Guru ",
            "optionB": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionC": "  Chattambi Swamikal ",
            "optionD": "  K.Madhavan ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAlwaye Advaita Ashram - the ashrams in Alwaye, founded in 1913 by Sree Narayana Guru in order to reach, propagate as well as live the Advaita philosophy. ",
            "keyString": "661966s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Congress leader rejected the 'August Offer' of 1940?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Wavell ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Linlithgow ",
            "optionC": "  Sir George Stanley ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Willingdon ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Viceroy of India, Lord Linlithgow, issued a statement from Simla on 8 August 1940 in the response of when congress formally ask England to affirm its adherence to the goal of Independence for India which is popularly known August Offer. ",
            "keyString": "661982s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Mohammadan Anglo-Oriental College at Aligarh was founded by",
            "optionA": "  Md. Ali Jinnah ",
            "optionB": "  Mohammad Ali ",
            "optionC": "  Saukat Ali ",
            "optionD": "  Sir Sayyed Ahmad Khan ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSir Sayyid Ahmad Khan founded Mohammadan Anglo oriental college in 1875 and it was renamed as Aligarh muslim university in 1920. He also established 'Scientific Society\" and published magazine 'RAJBHART MUSALMAN'. ",
            "keyString": "794922s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was first telegraph line started in India?",
            "optionA": "  1851 ",
            "optionB": "  1875 ",
            "optionC": "  1884 ",
            "optionD": "  1900 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe British India opened the first telegraph line and office in October 1851, between Calcutta and Diamond Harbour. ",
            "keyString": "795516s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When Mahatma Gandhi was assassinated, who said, \"None will believe that a man like this in body and soul ever walked on this earth.\"?",
            "optionA": "  Bertrand Russell ",
            "optionB": "  Leo Tolstoy ",
            "optionC": "  Albert Einstein ",
            "optionD": "  Khan Abdul Ghaffar Khan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAlbert Einstein was highly impressed with Mahatma Gandhi and he stated this statement when Gandhi was assassinated. ",
            "keyString": "795793s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is generally acknowledged as the pioneer of local self-government in modern India?",
            "optionA": "  Ripon ",
            "optionB": "  Mayo ",
            "optionC": "  Lytton ",
            "optionD": "  Curzon ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Ripon, the pioneer of local self-government, a resolution of 1882 set off the institution of localself-government in India. Ripon also known as the father of Local self government in India and real liberal of goldstein era. \"The Duty of Age\" was written by him. ",
            "keyString": "796100s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who had been the first to emphasise the instruction in literature and science through the English Language was essential for building a modern India?",
            "optionA": "  Ishwar Chandra Vidyasagar ",
            "optionB": "  GK Gokhale ",
            "optionC": "  Raj Ram Mohun Roy ",
            "optionD": "  MM Malaviya ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRaj Ram Mohun Roy had been the first to emphasise the instruction in literature and science through the English Language was essential for building a modern India. ",
            "keyString": "796279s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "On October 16, 1905, when the partition of Bengal was enforced, the great poet Rabindranath Tagore, to emphasise the unity of Bengal, suggested the programme of",
            "optionA": "  singing Bande Mataram ",
            "optionB": "  tying of Rakhi on each other's wrists ",
            "optionC": "  composing of patriotic songs ",
            "optionD": "  establishing national educational institutions ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRabindranath Tagore used Raksha Bandhan or Rakhi Utsav to symbolize unity between Hindus and Muslims. It was held in 1905 to prevent Bengal partition. Thousands of Hindus and Muslims came forward to support Tagore and tied Rakhi on each other's hand. The thread became the symbol of unity and harmony. ",
            "keyString": "871033s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Daiva Dasakam is a Malayalam work of __________",
            "optionA": "  Sree Narayana Guru ",
            "optionB": "  Chattambi Swamikal ",
            "optionC": "  ",
            "optionD": " Kesavan ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDaiva Dasakam is a Malayalam work of Sree Narayana Guru. ",
            "keyString": "871229s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who gave the title or \"Mahamana\" to Madan Mohan Malviya?",
            "optionA": "  Dada Bhai Naoroji ",
            "optionB": "  Gopal Krishna Gokhale ",
            "optionC": "  Rabindra Nath Tagore ",
            "optionD": "  Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMadan Mohan Malviya was the most prominent leader of INC. He was most remembered as the founder of Banaras Hindu University (B.H.U) at Varansi in 1916. Rabindra Nath Tagore titled him \"Mahamana\" and he awarded by Bharat Ratna in 2015 (Posthumous). ",
            "keyString": "871393s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In early 1898 Swami Vivekananda acquired a big plot of land on the western bank of the Ganga at a place called . . . . . to have a permanent abode for the monastery and monastic order originally started at Baranagar, and got it registered as Ramakrishna Math after a couple of years",
            "optionA": "  Allahabad ",
            "optionB": "  Lahore ",
            "optionC": "  Amritsar ",
            "optionD": "  Belur ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn early 1898 Swami Vivekananda acquired a big plot of land on the western bank of the Ganga at a place called Belur to have a permanent abode for the monastery and monastic Order originally started at Baranagar, and got it registered as Ramakrishna Math after a couple of years. ",
            "keyString": "871553s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Calcutta medical college in__________",
            "optionA": "  1735 ",
            "optionB": "  1745 ",
            "optionC": "  1832 ",
            "optionD": "  1835 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMedical College and Hospital, Kolkata, commonly referred to as Calcutta Medical College, formerly Medical College, Bengal, is a medical school and hospital in the city of Kolkata in the state of West Bengal, India. It was established in 1835 by William Bentinck. ",
            "keyString": "871712s24m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first Shivaji festival was held at Raigarh in __________",
            "optionA": "  1890 ",
            "optionB": "  1892 ",
            "optionC": "  1895 ",
            "optionD": "  1899 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first Shivaji festival was held at Raigarh in 1895. ",
            "keyString": "40016s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Swami Vivekananda attended the World's Parliament of Religions held in Chicago in __________",
            "optionA": "  1863 ",
            "optionB": "  1876 ",
            "optionC": "  1893 ",
            "optionD": "  1897 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSwami Vivekananda represented India and Hinduism at the Parliament of the World's Religions (1893). This was the first World's Parliament of Religions and it was held from 11 to 27 September 1893. Delegates from all over the world joined this Parliament. ",
            "keyString": "40233s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Jawaharlal Nehru had helped to start the newspaper",
            "optionA": "  Pioneer ",
            "optionB": "  National Herald ",
            "optionC": "  Kesari ",
            "optionD": "  Patriot ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNational Herald is an Indian newspaper published by The Associated Journals Ltd. It was founded by India's first prime minister Jawaharlal Nehru in 1938 as a tool to win independence. ",
            "keyString": "40397s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Mayo College was started at",
            "optionA": "  Delhi ",
            "optionB": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionC": "  Agra ",
            "optionD": "  Ajmer ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMayo College is a boys' residential public school in Ajmer, Rajasthan, India. It was founded in 1875 by Richard Bourke, 6th Earl of Mayo who was also the Viceroy of India from 1869 to 1872. ",
            "keyString": "40556s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The INA was largely composed of",
            "optionA": "  Indian Revolutionaries ",
            "optionB": "  Overseas Indians ",
            "optionC": "  Indian Prisoners of war under the Japanese ",
            "optionD": "  Deserters from the British Indian Army ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring early 1942 the Japanese conducted a campaign to persuade Indian prisoners of war in Hongkong, Shanghai, and Singapore that they should fight along with the Japanese for the \u201cliberation\u201d of India. In June 1942 the Japanese sponsored a conference in Bangkok at which the INA was formally launched, originally headed by Capt. Mohan Singh, and by November 1942 the Japanese claimed that the strength of the force was 16,000 troops.",
            "keyString": "40727s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "'The Times of India' which celebrated its 150th anniversary in 1988, was first published in 1838 as",
            "optionA": "  Bombay Chronicle ",
            "optionB": "  Bombay Times ",
            "optionC": "  Indian Times ",
            "optionD": "  National Times  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Times of India issued its first edition on 3 November 1838 as The Bombay Times and Journal of Commerce. ",
            "keyString": "291880s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "At the historic Tripuri Session of the Congress (March 1939) Subhas Bose defeated Mahatma Gandhi's official candidate for the Presidentship of the Congress. Who was Mahatma Gandhi's nominee?",
            "optionA": "  Abdul Kalam Azad ",
            "optionB": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionC": "  Pattabhi Sitaramayya ",
            "optionD": "  Vallabhbhai Patel ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPattabhi Sitaramayya ran for the presidency of the Indian National Congress as the candidate closest to Mohandas Gandhi, against the more radical Netaji Subash Chandra Bose in Tripuri Session of 1939. ",
            "keyString": "292105s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "As per the Act of 1919 which of the following was not a transferred subject?",
            "optionA": "  Education ",
            "optionB": "  Museum ",
            "optionC": "  Medical Relief ",
            "optionD": "  Land Revenue ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per the Act of 1919 land Revenue was not a transferred subject. ",
            "keyString": "292290s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Provincial autonomy was introduced in India by the",
            "optionA": "  Indian Councils Act, 1909 ",
            "optionB": "  Govemment of India Act, 1919 ",
            "optionC": "  Govemment of India Act, 1935 ",
            "optionD": "  Indian Independence Act, 1947 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tProvincial autonomy was introduced under the Government of India Act, 1935 it was called the first federal constitution of India as it recognized the separate existence of provinces.",
            "keyString": "292467s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Federal form of government at centre was introduced in India under",
            "optionA": "  Government of India Act of 1909 ",
            "optionB": "  Indian Councils Act of 1909 ",
            "optionC": "  Government of India Act of 1935 ",
            "optionD": "  Indian Independence Act of 1947 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFederal form of government was introduced under government of India act 1935 which was based on Simon commission report. This act was proved to be the second milestone in the introduction of responsible government in India. The act abolished dyarchy in provinces in April 1907 in the journal Bande Mataram. ",
            "keyString": "292708s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said that 'the real seat of taste is not the tongue but the mind.'?",
            "optionA": "  Aurobindo Ghosh ",
            "optionB": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionC": "  Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "optionD": "  Swami Vivekananda ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt is the statement from the autobiography of Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi which contains the life incidents of Gandhi ji from his childhood. It was published weekly in his other journal , Navjeevan. ",
            "keyString": "400185s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Rabindranath Tagore had renounced his knighthood because",
            "optionA": "  He wanted to join the Congress ",
            "optionB": "  Of a sense of solidarity with the Indian royalty robbed of its power and honour ",
            "optionC": "  Of the Jallianwala Bagh tragedy ",
            "optionD": "  He was given to occasional eccentric quirks ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRabindranath Tagore had renounced his knighthood because of the Jallianwala Bagh tragedy. ",
            "keyString": "400383s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who, among the following, has been known as the 'Frontier Gandhi'?",
            "optionA": "  Khan Abdul Ghaffar Khan ",
            "optionB": "  Khan Saheb ",
            "optionC": "  Chaudhary Shaukatullah ",
            "optionD": "  Liaquat Ali Khan ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKhan Abdul Gaffar Khan is known as the 'Frontier Gandhi'. Red Shirt Movement was started by Khan Abdul Ghaffar Khan. ",
            "keyString": "400721s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When Ramakrishna Mission was founded?",
            "optionA": "  1795 ",
            "optionB": "  1797 ",
            "optionC": "  1894 ",
            "optionD": "  1897 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVivekananda went on lecture tours and held private discourses on Hinduism and spirituality. He also founded the first Vedanta Society in the United States at New York. He returned to India in 1897 and founded the Ramakrishna Mission on 1 May 1897. ",
            "keyString": "400940s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who wrote the song 'Sare Jahan Se Accha Hindoostan Hamara'?",
            "optionA": "  Ashafaqullah Khan ",
            "optionB": "  Sahir Ludhianvi ",
            "optionC": "  Mohammad Iqbal ",
            "optionD": "  Ramprasad Bisrnil ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPoet and Politician Mohammad Iqbal wrote the song \"Sare Jahan Se Accha Hindoostan Hamara\". Iqbal was also known as the founder of Two Nation Theory. ",
            "keyString": "401122s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following newspaper was started by Annie Besant?",
            "optionA": "  The Hindu ",
            "optionB": "  Indian Express ",
            "optionC": "  The Times of India ",
            "optionD": "  New India ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNew India was an early 20th century daily newspaper published in India by Annie Besant. New India was a newspaper founded as a means to spread news related to the Indian freedom struggle. ",
            "keyString": "537040s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following started Bengali weekly newspaper 'Sambad Kaumudi' in year 1821?",
            "optionA": "  Raja Ram Mohan Roy ",
            "optionB": "  Aurobindo Ghosh ",
            "optionC": "  Ramkrishna Paramhans ",
            "optionD": "  Debendranath Tagore ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSambad Kaumudi was a Bengali weekly newspaper published from Kolkata in the first half of the 19th century by Ram Mohan Roy. It was a noted pro-Reformist publication that actively campaigned for the abolition of the Sati Pratha. ",
            "keyString": "539876s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "With whom was the seven-year rule of' \"missions, omissions and commissions' associated?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Dalhousie ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Curzon ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Lytton ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Mayo ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe seven-year rule of 'Mission, Omissions and Commission' was associated with Lord Curzon. ",
            "keyString": "542177s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Narayana Guru started a Sanskrit school in __________",
            "optionA": "  Varkala ",
            "optionB": "  Kottayam ",
            "optionC": "  Mahi ",
            "optionD": "  Calicut ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1904 he decided to settle down in a place to continue his spiritual practices. He chose Sivagiri at Varkala, twenty miles north of Thiruvananthapuram. He started a Sanskrit school in Varkala and poor boys and orphans were given free education regardless of their caste. ",
            "keyString": "542649s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sarvodaya stands for",
            "optionA": "  Total revolution ",
            "optionB": "  Non-cooperation ",
            "optionC": "  Upliftment of all ",
            "optionD": "  Non-violence ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSarvodaya (Which means universal upliftment or progress of all), used by Mahatma Gandhi in 1908 for the title of his translation of John Ruskin's \"Unto The Last\". ",
            "keyString": "542838s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The most famous woman disciple of Vivekananda was",
            "optionA": "  Madam Blavatsky ",
            "optionB": "  Annie Besant ",
            "optionC": "  Sister Nivedita ",
            "optionD": "  Sarojini Naidu ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSister Nivedita born Margaret Elizabeth Noble; 28 October 1867 \u2013 13 October 1911) was an Irish teacher, author, social activist, school founder and disciple of Swami Vivekananda. ",
            "keyString": "675509s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "After the defeat at Plassey, Siraj-ud-daullah was assassinated __________and was made the nawab",
            "optionA": "  Mir Jafar ",
            "optionB": "  Mir Qasim ",
            "optionC": "  Haider Ali ",
            "optionD": "  Tipu Sultan ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Battle of Plassey was fought of 23 June, 1757Company's Army was lead by the Robert Clive. Nawab was defeated by The East India Company and Mir Jafar was made the Nawab. ",
            "keyString": "675733s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of these battles proved decisive in the Anglo French rivalry in India?",
            "optionA": "  Battle of Wandiwash ",
            "optionB": "  Battle of Plassey ",
            "optionC": "  Battle of Mysore ",
            "optionD": "  Battle of Seringapatnam ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Battle of Wandiwash was a decisive battle in India during the Seven Years' War. Having made substantial gains in Bengal and Hyderabad, the British, after collecting huge amount of revenue, were fully equipped to face the French in Wandiwash, whom they defeated. ",
            "keyString": "675900s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The capital of Tipu Sultan, where he died while fighting the Fourth Anglo-Mysore war in 1799, was",
            "optionA": "  Bangalore ",
            "optionB": "  Mysore ",
            "optionC": "  Seringapatam ",
            "optionD": "  Hellebid or Halebid ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe capital of Tipu Sultan, where he died while fighting the Fourth Anglo-Mysore war in 1799, was Seringapatam. ",
            "keyString": "676061s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which year was the Indian Home Rule Society founded?",
            "optionA": "  1905 ",
            "optionB": "  1908 ",
            "optionC": "  1911 ",
            "optionD": "  1914 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indian Home Rule Society (IHRS) was an Indian organisation founded in London in 1905 that sought to promote the cause of self-rule in British India. ",
            "keyString": "676219s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Cripps Offer was regarded as a 'post dated cheque' by",
            "optionA": "  Nehru ",
            "optionB": "  Jinnah ",
            "optionC": "  Gandhi ",
            "optionD": "  Rajaji ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Congress stopped talks with Cripps and, guided by Gandhi, the national leadership demanded immediate self-government in return for war support. Gandhi said that Cripps' offer of Dominion Status after the war was a \"post-dated cheque drawn on a failing bank\". ",
            "keyString": "816989s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The last constitutional provision (covering undivided India) passed by the House of Commons was",
            "optionA": "  Government of India Act 1935 ",
            "optionB": "  Cabinet Mission Plan ",
            "optionC": "  Mountabatten (or June 3) Plan ",
            "optionD": "  Indian Independence Bill ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe last constitutional provision (covering undivided India) passed by the House of Commons was Government of India Act 1935. ",
            "keyString": "817211s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who termed Cripps proposals as  \" a post dated cheque in a crashing bank\"?",
            "optionA": "  Ambedkar ",
            "optionB": "  Annie Besant ",
            "optionC": "  Patel ",
            "optionD": "  Gandhiji ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGandhi ji termed Cripp's proposals as \" a post dated Cheque in a crashing Bank\". ",
            "keyString": "817383s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In . . . . . Derozio founded with his students the 'Academic Association' which organised debates on various subjects",
            "optionA": "  1824 ",
            "optionB": "  1825 ",
            "optionC": "  1828 ",
            "optionD": "  1834 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1828 Derozio founded with his students the 'Academic Association', which organised debates on various subjects. Derozio's students read the writings of Voltaire, Hume, Locke, Tom Paine and others and quoted them freely in their debates. ",
            "keyString": "817544s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Cabinet Mission which arrived Delhi in 1946 was headed by",
            "optionA": "  Lord Pethrick Lawrence ",
            "optionB": "  Sir Stafford Cripps ",
            "optionC": "  AV Alexander ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Attlee ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Cabinet Mission which arrived Delhi in 1946 was headed by Lord Pethrick Lawrence. ",
            "keyString": "817703s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which reforms Act had created the office of the secretary of state for India?",
            "optionA": "  Montague-Chelmsford Reforms ",
            "optionB": "  The Government of India Act, 1858 ",
            "optionC": "  The Indian Councils Act, 1861 ",
            "optionD": "  Minto-Morley Reforms, 1908 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEdward Henry Stanley, 15th Earl of Derby (who would later become the first Secretary of State for India) introduced another bill which was originally titled as \"An Act for the Better Government of India\" and it was passed on 2 August 1858. ",
            "keyString": "881060s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Government of India Act of 1935 consists of __________ sections and 10 schedules",
            "optionA": "  300 ",
            "optionB": "  330 ",
            "optionC": "  321 ",
            "optionD": "  331 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe 1935 Act was the second installment of constitutional reforms passed by British Parliament for implementing the ideal of responsible government in India. The Act of 1935 was quite a lengthy and detailed document. It consisted of 321 sections and 10 schedules. ",
            "keyString": "881248s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indian Universities Act, 1904 was passed during the governorship of",
            "optionA": "  Lord Lytton ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Curzon ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Ripon ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Hardinge-I ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder the governorship of Lord Curzon Indian Universities act was passed in 1904. The provision of this act was that the governing bodies of the universities were reconstituted and the size of sevates was reduced. ",
            "keyString": "881410s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The doctrine of lapse had been put to much use by",
            "optionA": "  Lord Dalhousie ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Bentick ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Curzon ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Ripon ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOudh (1856) is widely believed to have under the Doctrine of Lapse. However it was annexed by Lord Dalhousie under the pretext of mis-governance. The princely state of Kittur was taken over by the East India Company in 1824 by imposing a 'doctrine of lapse'. ",
            "keyString": "881760s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Treaty of Bassein (1802) was signed between",
            "optionA": "  The British and the Peshwa ",
            "optionB": "  The British and the Nizam ",
            "optionC": "  The British and Sikh ",
            "optionD": "  The British and Nawab of Arcot ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Treaty of Bassein (Now called Vasai) was a pact signed on 31 December 1802 between the British East India Company and Baji Rao II, the Maratha Peshwa of Pune (Poona) in India after the Battle of Poona. ",
            "keyString": "881931s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is the first female governor of Independent India?",
            "optionA": "  Vijayalakshmi Pandit ",
            "optionB": "  Sharda Mukherjee ",
            "optionC": "  Fathima Beevi ",
            "optionD": "  Sarojini Naidu ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSarojini Naidu became the first female governor of Independent India, she is known as Nightangle of India. ",
            "keyString": "972529s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In __________, the First National Trade union organization (The All India Trade Union Congress (AITUC)) was established",
            "optionA": "  1904 ",
            "optionB": "  1908 ",
            "optionC": "  1917 ",
            "optionD": "  1920 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll India Trade Union Congress (AITUC) was founded in 1920 with Lala Lajpat Rai as its first president. Upto 1945 Congressmen, Socialists, Communists worked in the AITUC which was the central trade union organisation of workers of India. ",
            "keyString": "972745s25m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Queen Victoria became the Empress of India according to the Act of",
            "optionA": "  1858 ",
            "optionB": "  1861 ",
            "optionC": "  1876 ",
            "optionD": "  1909 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDisraeli also pushed the Royal Titles Act 1876 through Parliament, so that Victoria took the title \"Empress of India\" from 1 May 1876. ",
            "keyString": "49391s26m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Tashkent Agreement was signed between India and Pakistan in the year",
            "optionA": "  1960 ",
            "optionB": "  1966 ",
            "optionC": "  1970 ",
            "optionD": "  1950 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Tashkent Declaration was a peace agreement between India and Pakistan signed on 10 January 1966 that resolved the Indo-Pakistani War of 1965. ",
            "keyString": "49600s26m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first political association of India founded in 1891 was the",
            "optionA": "  Landholders Society of Calcutta ",
            "optionB": "  Indian Association ",
            "optionC": "  British Indian Association ",
            "optionD": "  Madras Native Association ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Zamindari Association, which was later renamed Landholders' Society, was established in 12 November 1837 by Dwarkanath Tagore, Prasanna Kumar Tagore, Radhakanta Deb, Ramkamal Sen and Bhabani Charan Mitra. It has been described as \"the first organisation of Bengal with distinct political object.\" ",
            "keyString": "49983s26m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "After the ruin of India's trade, industries and handicrafts, the burden of taxation in India had to be mainly borne by",
            "optionA": "  Zamindars ",
            "optionB": "  Peasantry ",
            "optionC": "  Income-tax payers ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter the ruin of India's trade, Industries and handicrafts, the burden of taxation in India had to be mainly borne by peasantry. ",
            "keyString": "50177s26m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The National Anthem was first sung in year 1911 at the Annual session of the India National Congress held at",
            "optionA": "  Pune ",
            "optionB": "  Mumbai ",
            "optionC": "  Kolkata ",
            "optionD": "  Lucknow ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNational anthem (Jana-gana-mana song) was originally composed by the Rabindranath Tagore in Bengali. It was first sung in Calcutta in the meeting of Indian National Congress on 27th of December in 1911. ",
            "keyString": "50348s26m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Sepoy Mutiny broke out on May 10, 1857 at __________",
            "optionA": "  Meerut ",
            "optionB": "  Gwalior ",
            "optionC": "  Jhansi ",
            "optionD": "  Agra ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt was on May 10, 1857 that the Indian soldiers at the Meerut cantonment in modern UP revolted against the British. ",
            "keyString": "140551s26m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The programme of Swadeshi and Boycott against the partition of Bengal was visualised by",
            "optionA": "  Surendra Nath Bennerjee ",
            "optionB": "  BC Pal ",
            "optionC": "  Aurobindo Ghose ",
            "optionD": "  Rash Behari Bose ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Swadeshi movement started with the partition of Bengal by the Viceroy of India, Lord Curzon in 1905 and continued up to 1911. It was the most successful of the pre-Gandhian movement. Its chief architects was Aurobindo Ghosh. ",
            "keyString": "140788s26m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "As per 'August Offer 1940' the Constitution of India would be drawn by",
            "optionA": "  House of Commons ",
            "optionB": "  House of Lords ",
            "optionC": "  Princely States ",
            "optionD": "  Indians ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe August Offer was a proposal made by the British government in 1940 promising the expansion of the Executive Council of the Viceroy of India to include more Indians, the establishment of an advisory war council, giving full weight to minority opinion, and the recognition of Indians' right to frame their own constitution (after the end of the war). ",
            "keyString": "140956s26m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first Carnatic War in India was an extension of the Anglo-French War in",
            "optionA": "  Canada ",
            "optionB": "  Europe ",
            "optionC": "  Africa ",
            "optionD": "  America ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFirst Carnatic War was an extension of the Anglo-French War in Europe which was caused by the Austrian War of Succession. ",
            "keyString": "141116s26m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement is related with the provision of the Charter Act of 1833?",
            "optionA": "  Allowed the Company's monopoly of tea trade and trade with China ",
            "optionB": "  Put an end to the Company's tea trade and trade with China ",
            "optionC": "  Has not interfered with Company's tea trade and trade with China ",
            "optionD": "  Allowed the Company's monopoly of tea trade and trade with China for ten years ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe East India Company Act 1813, also known as the Charter Act 1813, was an Act of the Parliament of the United Kingdom which renewed the charter issued to the British East India Company, and continued the Company's rule in India. However, the Company's commercial monopoly was ended, except for the tea and opium trade and the trade with China, this reflecting the growth of British power in India. ",
            "keyString": "141283s26m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1920 under her leadership the__________, the Ahmedabad textile mill workers union was established",
            "optionA": "  Majoor Mahajan ",
            "optionB": "  Ushabai Dange ",
            "optionC": "  Parvati Bhore ",
            "optionD": "  Maniben Kara ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1920 under her leadership the Majoor Mahajan, the Ahmedabad textile mill workers union was established. ",
            "keyString": "239724s26m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Brigadier was associated with Jallianwala Bagh tragedy?",
            "optionA": "  General Dyer ",
            "optionB": "  Arthur Wellesly ",
            "optionC": "  General Harris ",
            "optionD": "  Colonel Wellesly ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Jallianwala Bagh massacre, also known as the Amritsar massacre, took place on 13 April 1919 when troops of the British Indian Army under the command of Colonel Reginald Dyer fired rifles into a crowd of Punjabis, who had gathered in Jallianwala Bagh, Amritsar, Punjab. ",
            "keyString": "239764s26m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1942, Europe had witnessed a great war between",
            "optionA": "  Sweden and Russia ",
            "optionB": "  France and Germany ",
            "optionC": "  France and England ",
            "optionD": "  Germany and Russia ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1942, Europe had witnessed a great war between Germany and Russia. ",
            "keyString": "239779s26m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Jyotirao's family belonged to __________ caste",
            "optionA": "  Mali ",
            "optionB": "  Thiyya ",
            "optionC": "  Pulaya ",
            "optionD": "  Mahar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJyotirao's family belonged to 'mali' caste and their original title was 'Gorhay'. Mali's were considered as an inferior caste by the Brahmins and were shunned socially. Jyotirao's father and uncles served as florists, so the family came to be known as 'Phule'. ",
            "keyString": "239791s26m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Editor of 'Young India' and 'Harijan' was",
            "optionA": "  Nehru ",
            "optionB": "  Ambedkar ",
            "optionC": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionD": "  Subhash Chandra bose ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tYoung India was a weekly paper or journal in English published by Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi from 1919 to 1931. Gandhi wrote various quotations in this journal that inspired many. ",
            "keyString": "239803s26m4h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        }
    ]
}